<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ultimas manus being letters between Mr. John Humphrey, and Mr. Samuel Clark, in reference to the point of justification : written upon the occasion of Mr. Clark's printing his book upon that subject, after Mr. Humfrey's book entituled The righteousness of God, and published for vindication of that doctrine wherein they agree, as found, by shewing the difference of it from that of the Papist, and the mistakes of our common Protestant : in order to an impartial and more full understanding of that great article, by the improvement of that whereto they have attained, or correction of any thing wherein they err, by better judgments : together with animadversions on some late papers between Presbyterian and Independent, in order to reconcile the difference, and fix the Doctrine of Christ's satisfaction.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 273 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3715</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16520</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12859876</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12859876</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94667</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45162)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94667)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 985:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ultimas manus being letters between Mr. John Humphrey, and Mr. Samuel Clark, in reference to the point of justification : written upon the occasion of Mr. Clark's printing his book upon that subject, after Mr. Humfrey's book entituled The righteousness of God, and published for vindication of that doctrine wherein they agree, as found, by shewing the difference of it from that of the Papist, and the mistakes of our common Protestant : in order to an impartial and more full understanding of that great article, by the improvement of that whereto they have attained, or correction of any thing wherein they err, by better judgments : together with animadversions on some late papers between Presbyterian and Independent, in order to reconcile the difference, and fix the Doctrine of Christ's satisfaction.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 92, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 92.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clark, Samuel, 1626-1701. --  Scripture-justification.</term>
               <term>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719. --  Righteousness of God.</term>
               <term>Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94667:1"/>
            <p>ULTIMA MANUS. BEING LETTERS BETWEEN M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>John Humfrey,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Samuel Clark,</hi> In reference to the Point of Juſtification; Written upon the Occaſion of Mr. <hi>Clark</hi>'s Printing his Book on that Subject, after Mr. <hi>Humfrey</hi>'s Book entituled <hi>The Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God;</hi> and publiſhed for Vindication of that Doctrine where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they agree, as ſound, by ſhewing the difference of it from that of the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and the Miſtake of our common <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order to an impartial and more full underſtanding of that great Article, by the <hi>Improvement</hi> of that <hi>whereto they have attained,</hi> or <hi>Correction</hi> of any thing wherein they err, by better Judgments.</p>
            <p>Together with <hi>Animadverſions</hi> on ſome late Papers between Presbyterian and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, in order to reconcile the Difference, and fix the Doctrine of Chriſt's <hi>Satisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mediocria firma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> the lower End of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chapel.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:94667:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94667:2"/>
            <head>THE LETTERS.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To Mr. CLARK.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My very worthy Brother,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received your Letter, and your Book; that elaborate Book, writ long ſince, and deſir'd to be printed by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and which I longed to ſee. And whereas I find it, upon reading it twice over, to be an induſtrious, clear, honeſt and faithful Work; ſo methodical, eaſie for the Reader, profitable and full in exhauſting its Subject; beſides, ſo concordant in the main with my Sentiments, and when we differ, ſo much more entertaining for the variety; you may be ſure that for all theſe Faults, I can do no leſs than judge it to the <hi>Preſs</hi> (where it muſt confeſs them) ſeeing you committed it to my Judgment.</p>
               <p>As for your Letter and Remarks with it on mine, I thank you. I ſhall at preſent ſay two things to you;</p>
               <p n="1">1. The one is, That whereas I make our Goſpel-righteouſneſs the Form, or formal Cauſe of our Juſtification, which you can hardly ſwallow, the reaſon of the ſtop is not really (I judge) becauſe you have conſidered more of the matter, but leſs. I wonder not at you to be ſhy about this, when Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf has not ſpoken here ſo fully, as being againſt the ſtream of our Proteſtants, and he had never digeſted the Notion (I think) of the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> which you have done. <hi>Faith,</hi> you acknowledge to be our formal Righteouſneſs, and underſtand it clearly (as you ſeem to do all you aſſent to.) Your words are, <hi>I freely grant that Faith, or Goſpel obedience, is formal Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; that is, It has the Form of Righteouſneſs, to wit, Conformity to the Law of the Goſpel, or Covenant of Grace:</hi> And yet you are ſo maidenly modeſt for all that, as you dare not ſay it doth juſtifie us <hi>formaliter,</hi> or is the formal Reaſon of our Juſtification. It is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the common Sentiment, and what you have not found aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, that you are ſo tender about it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is a Sentence you will find ſomewhere in my Book, which has not (I perceive) entred your Mind, as it has mine, that does bring light with it. It could not have been ſaid at firſt, but by one
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94667:3"/>more thoroughly ſtudied (Academically) in the Learned part of this Controverſie than you or I, and accordingly is worthy your reception. The Sentence is this. <hi>Performalem juſtificationis cauſam juſti conſtituimur.</hi> It is profound Truth. Conſider now, I pray, what is that Righteouſneſs which you believe indeed to be it <hi>quâ,</hi> or <hi>per quam juſti conſtituimur?</hi> Is it Chriſts Righteouſneſs, or our performance of the Evangelick Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? If with you and I it be the laſt, what then is <hi>Juſtification active</hi> (or the Form of it) but Gods imputing this to us for Righteouſneſs? And what <hi>Juſtification Paſſive,</hi> but this Evangelick Performance ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted? Certainly, my Brother, till you come up to this, you do but grope in the dark: You and but in fear of all you ſay, and can have no ſtedfaſtneſs or foundation in the point.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Anthony Wotton,</hi> who underſtood himſelf ſo thoroughly, and was the Man who broke the Ice, in the denial of Chriſts Righteouſneſs to be our formal Righteouſneſs, does ſet up therefore (as he muſt) another thing in the room of it. A Righteouſneſs there muſt be that conſtitutes us Righteous, and if it be not Chriſts, what is it? Why, Mr. <hi>Wotton</hi> makes this to be <hi>Pardon;</hi> the Righteouſneſs of Pardon, Righteouſneſs, I ſay, is the Form of Juſtification; or, the Form of Juſtification does con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in a Righteouſneſs; and Mr. <hi>Wotton</hi> ſets himſelf to prove that Pardon is it; which others avouch after him, as the only Righteouſneſs whereof a Sinner is capable. It is this therefore is another ſaying of the ſame Sort and Author, which muſt be here taken in, as it is alſo in my Book. <hi>Juſtifications forman juſtitiâ conſtare cerium eſt.</hi> Well, this <hi>Juſtitia,</hi> which is <hi>Juſtificationis forma,</hi> our former learnedſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Divines, have generally own'd and held to be the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed: A conceit very ſtrangely hard, I believe, at firſt to be let in, and too crude at laſt to be digeſted. To make Pardon it, has a great deal of ſenſe in it, but the Scripture never calls this our Righteouſneſs; nor will the word it ſelf allow it. It being a third thing which is it, you have hit on the right, and that is the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> which you underſtand ſo well, and you define, <hi>The way or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of becoming righteous, which is of Gods ordaining or appoinring;</hi> A Righteouſneſs <hi>which is of,</hi> on which we attain by <hi>Faith.</hi> This is that Righteouſneſs in oppoſition to <hi>Works</hi> (when the <hi>righteouſneſs of Chriſt</hi> can't be ſo oppoſed) that <hi>Paul</hi> has reveal'd. This is that <hi>juſtitia,</hi> which is the <hi>Juſtificationis forma,</hi> we ſeek in the buſineſs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And herein, you ſeeing more (I believe) than Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> there is one thing that he ſaw and you ſee not. Juſtification, (you ſay) is Gods <hi>accounting</hi> and <hi>uſing</hi> us as juſt; but you have not taken in what he ſaith further, That it is alſo the <hi>making</hi> us juſt I apprehend
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94667:3"/>the firſt thoughts of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> here, ſprang from his reading Mr. <hi>Wotton,</hi> who will have ſuch a Righteouſneſs to juſtifie us, as makes us righteous; that is, (I have told) <hi>Pardon;</hi> which, by <hi>Conſtituting</hi> a man <hi>juſt,</hi> I think Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> at firſt underſtood too. But whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he thought firſt or laſt, I am come to ſee, what you muſt come to ſee alſo, that by <hi>Conſtitutive Juſtification</hi> God muſt firſt both <hi>make</hi> and <hi>account</hi> us juſt, or by <hi>Sentential,</hi> he cannot <hi>declare</hi> us ſo at the great Day. Now how that is you have in my Book (p. 24.) Not by <hi>Infuſion,</hi> as the Papiſt; nor by <hi>Non-imputation;</hi> as <hi>Wotton;</hi> but by <hi>Imputation:</hi> God imputing our Faith for Righteouſneſs. God by his Evangelick Law, has conſtituted Faith and Repentance to be a Righteouſneſs, to ſerve us inſtead of perfect Works. When a Man then believes and repents, he is thereby conſtituted Righteous. By vertue, (I ſay) of that Law he is <hi>made</hi> ſuch, or accepted as ſuch (in regard to the benefit) as if he were ſuch by the <hi>Law of Works;</hi> when yet by this he is ſtill unrighteous. And when you believe this ſo; you need no further conſideration to underſtand what <hi>that</hi> Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is, and how it ſo becomes, <hi>which</hi> is the Form, formal Cauſe, or formal Reaſon of our Juſtification.</p>
               <p>If this term <hi>[formal cauſe]</hi> will not yet paſs with you, I will make it paſs. The imputing of our Faith to us for Righteouſneſs (I have ſaid) is <hi>Juſtification.</hi> I will more unfold theſe words, and ſay thus, Gods making or conſtituting us juſt, by the imputing our Faith to us for Righteouſneſs, is <hi>Juſtification Active:</hi> Our being <hi>made</hi> juſt, or <hi>conſtituted</hi> righteous by that Imputation, is <hi>Juſtification Paſſive.</hi> This I hope is plain and undeniable. Now this Faith then thus imputed, being the Righteouſneſs whereby God <hi>conſtitutes,</hi> and we are <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted</hi> righteous (which is inſtrumentally by his Law of the Goſpel) it muſt be the Form, or formal Cauſe of our Juſtification; Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaying mentioned, <hi>Performalem Juſtificationis cauſam juſti conſtituimur;</hi> which I take to be as good as any Oracle, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to us how that Term was formerly, and is ſtill to be underſtood. The Proteſtants (I will repeat) ſay, Chriſt's Righteouſneſs being imputed is that whereby we are <hi>made just</hi> in Gods ſight, and ſo becomes our formal Righteouſneſs: I ſay, it is the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God in him</hi> (that is, through him, or through his Merits imputed to us for Righteouſneſs) that makes us ſo, and is this formal Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and it is but an abſurd thing to ſay the other: for which Time alone will give ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Let me yet inculcate this. The Papiſts, you know, ſay, Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is <hi>making us juſt</hi> (the firſt way before, by <hi>Infuſion</hi>) and that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94667:4"/>our inherent Righteouſneſs therefore it the Form of our <hi>Juſtification.</hi> You ſay that this making us juſt (in their ſenſe) is <hi>Sanctification,</hi> and our inherent Righteouſneſs is indeed the Form, formal Cauſe, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Reaſon of our Sanctification. Well, now the Papiſts and we do not differ in our Notion of the Term [<hi>Form</hi> or <hi>formal Cauſe:</hi>] For if Juſtification was that they ſay it is, <hi>the making us juſt,</hi> you grant it were the Form, formal Cauſe, or formal Reaſon thereof. You underſtand me, Brother, when I tell you that which you knew not before, that Juſtification is the <hi>making us juſt</hi> (and I tell you how) as well as the <hi>accounting</hi> us juſt; I tell you alſo, and I tell you how, this Righteouſneſs is and muſt thereby become the formal Cauſe of it. Our Terms we take from the Papiſts and the Schools: And when our Learnedſt Proteſtants have made Chriſt's Righteouſneſs the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Cauſe,</hi> in the ſenſe they made <hi>that</hi> ſo, you and I muſt make the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> ſo, or we ſtand not to our tackle, but fail in Judgment.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The other thing I muſt tell you is, That there are two leaves inſerted in your Book, at the end of the ninth Chapter, which you call a <hi>Scheme of Juſtification,</hi> which was a puzling Matter to my ſelf, when I wrote my own Book. They ſpeak of a twofold <hi>Charge,</hi> of the Law and of the Goſpel; and accordingly of a twofold Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Primary</hi> (you ſay): <hi>Subordinate</hi> and <hi>Conſequent.</hi> You ſeem to me to have put this into your Book, after another rate than the reſt, which you weighed ſo well before you wrote. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing there is you are afraid of, but do you know what? Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and others have ſaid ſome ſuch thing, and you have ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, leſt a diſreſpect be offer'd to Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, if you ſay not the like too. Thus the ingenuous Mr. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams,</hi> when they have made and held out a <hi>Goſpel-righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Juſtification</hi> accordingly, muſt have a <hi>Legal</hi> one alſo, that Chriſt's Righteouſneſs may be imputed, or elſe their Doctrine will not down. The Brethren elſe will be offended, and that is it.</p>
               <p n="7">7. It is true that Chriſt by his Satisfaction, (conſiſting of his Paſſive and Active Obedience both, for performing the Law of our Redemption) has freed us from the Law of Works, and Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by it; but is this <hi>Juſtification?</hi> No; it is not: This is <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> which precedes, and is in order as a means to our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which is plain by the Text, <hi>Being juſtified freely by his grace, through the Redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> The freeing us from the Law, is freeing us from it as a <hi>Rule of Judgment,</hi> when it remains a <hi>Rule of Life</hi> (as you may ſee at large in my <hi>Pacification</hi>)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94667:4"/>and ſeeing we are not to be judged by it, we cannot be condemned and juſtified by it: <hi>By the Law ſhall no fleſh living be juſtified.</hi> When it is by the Goſpel therefore that we are to be judged, there can be no other but one <hi>Evangelical</hi> Juſtification.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The truth is, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> has confounded us with two Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Subordinate;</hi> or elſe you and others confound your ſelves by underſtanding him ſo; when there is indeed, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Him and the Truth, a <hi>double Righteouſneſs</hi> (you may call them <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Subordinate,</hi> with him, if you pleaſe) but this double Righteouſneſs muſt not make a <hi>double Juſtification,</hi> as you apprehend, ſeeing they both go (or are fellow-ingredients) into one and the ſame Juſtification. The one as the <hi>Meritorions,</hi> the other as the <hi>Formal</hi> Cauſe of it. You ſee what need there is, when a Man has wrote a Book, for himſelf or ſome other to come after, to enlighten and confirm the ſame Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Mr. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> eſpecially, are gravel'd here, about the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, which ſticks ſo much with that conſiderable Man. Let me therefore tell you truly what there is in it: There are theſe two things in it; The one is, that God did account, or allow indeed of what Chriſt did and ſuffered, to be really in our behalf, for our ſakes, <hi>for us,</hi> in our ſtead (ſo as it may be ſaid, <hi>in ſe</hi> imputed) as to the <hi>Impetration</hi> of the benefits we have by him upon <hi>condition:</hi> And the other is, our having thoſe benefits, as to the <hi>Application</hi> upon the <hi>performance;</hi> and that is, the having his Righteouſneſs to be ours, <hi>really</hi> in the Effects, and <hi>relatively</hi> in regard to them. This is all, and no more in it. Pray ſee my <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification,</hi> p. 30, 31, 32. or my laſt Book, p. 35, 36. where (in the Margin) the ſame is repeated, and give me your conſidered and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Judgment thereupon, which before this, I expected in print from Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> but am fruſtrate of that Satisfaction.</p>
               <p n="10">10. As for your Remarks, our difference is not <hi>tanti,</hi> that I ſhould examine them. Only one Queſtion you ask me that I muſt not paſs over, <hi>Will it not ſerve as well to all intents and purpoſes to ſay, That we are juſtified by Faith, as the condition or way only, as by the term</hi> Cauſa formalis <hi>of our Juſtification?</hi> I Anſwer, No, by no means, my prudential Brother. If I ſhould reſt there, when I acknowledge both, I ſhould account my ſelf one that ſought to pleaſe Men, or ſave my ſelf, rather than ſerve the Truth; that is, to be tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd, as moſt I perceive are apt to be (I mean not you my worthy Brother) when they come over to any ſuch hard ſaying, as they ſee will make their Diſciples draw back, and walk no more with them. I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94667:5"/>muſt add, that although an abſtracting this great Doctrine from <hi>Logical</hi> or <hi>Metaphiſical</hi> Terms, according to the Biſhop of <hi>Wroceſter</hi> and you, may be adviſeable (with the limitation, <hi>as much as we can</hi>) in regard to the Vulgar, or in our Preaching to the People, yet in regard to the Learned, and the Verſed in this Controverſie, it is quite otherwiſe, or at leaſt, there muſt be an exception as to this Particular, which is not here only neceſſary in regard to ſuch, but is the <hi>all in all</hi> in the buſineſs. The point is hereby brought, as it were, to a word: as in the matter of the Trinity, it was brought to that of <hi>Homoouſios,</hi> no more to be diſcarded. I will yet ſay, that here is the <hi>Criterion,</hi> according to a more ſhallow or deep imbibing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I do reckon for my own part, ſuch or ſo much to be the meaſure of knowledge that I have attained, as to the critical bottom of this Matter. With reverence be it ſpoken to extraordinary Men, who being above all mean or colloguing ends, do, we may ſuppoſe very throughly ſee the ſame, when prudentially they decline to ſay it; and when they yet would be more generous too, in a Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Teſtimony to it. <hi>To this end was I born</hi> (ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) <hi>and for this cauſe came I into the World, that I ſhould bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. I will yet inſtance for your Conviction. The Scripture in one place is expreſs, <hi>By the obedience of one, ſhall many be made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> One may ask here, Is not Chriſts Obedience therefore ours? Is not the <hi>being made righteous,</hi> to be juſtified? I Anſwer, Yes: Chriſts Obedience is ours in the Effects, and as to this effect, in making us righteous upon our Faith, and ſo juſtifying us. But here is the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the point, Chriſts Obedience does make us righteous, or juſtifies us <hi>per modum couſae meritoriae,</hi> but not <hi>per modum cauſae for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malis</hi> (which the Doctrine of Imputation intended at firſt) <hi>noſtrae juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificationis.</hi> We are to enlarge here by ſhewing how <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin brought in death, which paſſes upon all Men, and ſo is imputed to all, as to that effect: Likewiſe, how Chriſt's obedient ſuffering, or ſuffering obedience, has procured the Grace, that we may be juſtified by Faith without Works, and are ſo, upon our believing. We are <hi>made ſinners</hi> then by <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin, and <hi>made righteous</hi> by Chriſts obedience <hi>per modum meriti,</hi> not otherwiſe. This is ſatisfaction to this Text; this the core of the Controverſie. Again, Chriſt is <hi>made ſin for us,</hi> in another place (our ſins procuring his ſufferings) and <hi>we the righteouſneſs of God in him.</hi> How is that? <hi>Per modum meriti,</hi> I ſay ſtill; <hi>Effective,</hi> in ſhort, <hi>non Formaliter.</hi> See what need we have of ſuch Terms. See how ſpeedily and compleatly they do
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94667:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>our buſineſs, when a whole Book at once is as good as wrapt up in them.</p>
               <p n="12">12. As for your Diſſertation upon the Queſtion, whether Chriſt's <hi>Active</hi> as well as <hi>Paſſive</hi> Obedience is imputed in our Juſtification, I did think to adviſe you to be content with what is ſaid in the Book, and ſo leave it. My Reaſons are two.
<list>
                     <item>1. Becauſe this Diſpute is a Point not proper for you and I, but needleſs. They that hold a <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal</hi> Juſtification by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, may contend which of the two is imputed: But we that ſay, it is not <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Righteouſneſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, but the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> that juſtifies us, may leave them fighting, and we be quiet.</item>
                     <item>2. Becauſe as to the Point, I think ſuch may with <hi>Anth. Burgeſſe</hi> be well at a ſtand about it.</item>
                  </list> You ſay Chriſt being a <hi>Divine,</hi> not <hi>Human</hi> perſon, was under no obligation of duty. How then does Chriſt ſay, <hi>His Father was greater than He,</hi> and that in regard to his Authority? How came he down to do his Fathers Commandment, and yet be under no Obligation? Here you muſt come off and ſay, He was not bound on his own account, but <hi>for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> he was. Well then, for us he was bound to <hi>obey;</hi> and how then do you ſay, he only <hi>ſuffered</hi> for us, and not <hi>obeyed</hi> for us? You muſt come off again, and ſay, <hi>For us</hi> may be taken <hi>for our Benefit,</hi> or <hi>in our ſtead.</hi> He was indeed bound to obey for our benefit, but not in our ſtead. Well! but what if you are out here at laſt? Let me mind you that Chriſt who redeemed us from the Condemnation of the Law, redeemed us alſo from the Obligation of perfect fulfilling it as the Condition of Life. And as by his ſufferings he freed us not from all ſuffering but Eternal: ſo by his Obedience, though he freed us not from obeying God according to the Goſpel, yet he did from obeying him according to the Law as the <hi>Condition of Salvation.</hi> In this ſenſe, and to this purpoſe he obeyed, that we might not <hi>ſo</hi> obey, as well as he ſuffered, that we might not <hi>ſo</hi> ſuffer: that is, upon this account, not all accounts, obeyed and ſuffered both in our ſtead.</p>
               <p>Before I leave you, for the ſake of the Reader when this is Printed, I muſt wiſh you again to take heed that when I ſay that Chriſt hath <hi>obeyed for us,</hi> in the ſenſe of <hi>in our ſtead,</hi> you do not miſconſtrue me. To do a thing in ones ſtead, is to do it ſo as to free the other from doing it. Though Chriſt's perfect obeying the Law did (I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend) free us from thoſe Terms, yet did he not obey the Law for us ſo as ſome would have it, that no other Obedience is neceſſary to our Juſtification, or that his Obeying does thereby become ours, or is <hi>in ſe</hi> imputed to us, as formally to juſtifie us. This is that Doctrine you diſpute againſt in your <hi>Diſſertation;</hi> and I find in ſome Notes which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94667:6"/>I writ for a <hi>Memor andum</hi> to my ſelf upon reading ſome Author (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the words be my own, or his, or mixt) thus much which I will ſet down to confirm your Determination.</p>
               <p>There is a double Debt, the Principal perfect Obedience: and <hi>Nomine poena,</hi> ſatisfaction for our failing. It is ſaid, Chriſt paid both for us, and both imputed. But if his Obedience, being ſuch as that he omitted no duty, and committed no ſin, be imputed, there is no need of his ſuffering. It is replied, we muſt ſuppoſe his ſatisfaction for ſin to precede, and when we are pardoned, and freed from puniſhment, then muſt his Active Obedience be alſo imputed to give us right to Heaven. It is anſwered.
<list>
                     <item>1. Suppoſing a Righteouſneſs now required; it muſt not be his Righteouſneſs imputed; for then we muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted as never lapſed, nor once omitted any duty, and that is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with his Satisfaction preceding.</item>
                     <item>2. Puniſhment is <hi>Damni</hi> or <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> Though one might be freed from the <hi>poena ſenſus,</hi> and yet have no right to Heaven, we cannot be freed from the <hi>poena damni</hi> alſo, the loſs of the Reward, but we muſt have right to Heaven together with our freedom from Condemnation. It may be ſaid further, a man may be forgiven, but yet not reputed never to have broken the Law; God cannot account any thing other than it is, and the man was a ſinner. This now being true, it appears how Chriſt's Righteouſneſs therefore cannot be thus imputed (as our formal Righteouſneſs) becauſe, then as he, we ſhould be look'd on as if we had never ſinned, when we ſhall ever even in Heaven be judged as ſuch that once had ſinned, but now forgiven. The root of the Errour (as I have ſaid ever) lies here, to think we muſt be juſtified by the <hi>Law of Innocency</hi> as Chriſt himſelf, which does ſubvert the Goſpel.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your aſſured Friend and loving Brother,</hi> John Humfrey.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>To</hi> Mr. Humfrey.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend and dear Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THAT you have taken ſo much pains to open my Underſtanding, and to make an Eye-ſalve to clear my ſight, I count a great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and take my ſelf to be much obliged to you for it: For I deſire to <hi>underſtand my Errors,</hi> in every ſenſe. I am willing to open my eyes and all my Powers to let in <hi>Light,</hi> which is ſo ſweet and grateful; <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.7. I ſay, not <hi>vale,</hi> as he, but <hi>ſalvelumen amicum.</hi> Some points indeed are clog'd with <hi>Intereſt,</hi> which dims the <hi>ſight,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94667:6"/>or bribes and biaſſes the Judgment, that either it cannot diſcern the Truth, or at leaſt, not entertain and embrace it: Either <hi>ſecular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> lies in the way, as in the Controverſie about Conformity; or <hi>carnal Intereſt,</hi> as in the <hi>Antinomian</hi> Opinions, which ſerve to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie Perſons in a Licentious Courſe of Life, and ſo they find it agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to eſpouſe them; for, as what we would have to be true we are eaſily perſwaded that it is true; ſo what we would have not to be true, we are hardly convinc'd that it is true: Here it muſt be a ſtrong and a clear Light that will pierce a Mans eyes, which he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely ſhuts againſt it. But that is not the caſe here. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the power of Truth to ſway the Judgment, either one way or other; which, unto thoſe that <hi>dig</hi> and delve <hi>for it, as for bid Treaſures,</hi> that do <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14) <hi>hunt</hi> and purſue after it, by an impartial Examination and Conſideration, it will be found one time or other, and manifeſt it ſelf in its native Beauty, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 1,—5.</p>
               <p>How far forth the Light in your Papers has cleared my Eye-ſight, and contributed towards a cure of my Miſtakes, will be ſeen in what follows.</p>
               <p>Only premiſing this, That beſides what I have ſaid by way of Anſwer or Reply, I have added ſome Figures at the beginning of every Break in your Letter, without reference to the ſenſe, and not conſidering whether that will bear them or no, but only for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience of Quotation, that the Paſſages I reply to, may be more readily found out.</p>
               <p>In the beginning you tell me, that my Diſcourſe is <hi>very concordant in the main with my Sentiments.</hi> I am ſure we did not confer Notes, nor play the Plagiaries one with another; my Diſcourſe being writ almoſt twenty Years ago, and with little aſſiſtance from Books, more than the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Concordance;</hi> as is expreſt in the Epiſtle.</p>
               <p>§ 1. You obſerve my ſhineſs to admit of Faith, or Goſpel-righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to be the Form of Juſtification. I granted it may be Formal-righteouſneſs or Goſpel-righteouſneſs, and yet not the formal Cauſe of Juſtification; for Love, Hope, Fear of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces, and conſequently Goſpel-righteouſneſs, and yet none of our Proteſtants ſay that they are the formal Cauſe of our Juſtification, (though you ſay Faith working by Love is) and therefore I thought there might be a diſtinction between them, and that one did not neceſſarily infer the other: But upon further conſideration of what you ſay upon that point, I don't ſee at preſent how I can evade or avoid the dint and force of your Reaſoning, to prove that Faith is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94667:7"/>the formal Cauſe of Juſtification. But however, I would not lay too much ſtreſs upon a Logical Notion, or Term of Art. He that will grant we are juſtified by Faith in a plain ſenſe, without Tropes or Figures, ſhall paſs for found in the Faith with me, whether he will call it the Form or formal Cauſe of Juſtification or no, I'll contend with no Body about ſuch Terms; and why you ſhould inſiſt ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently upon that Term, I know not.</p>
               <p>This ſerves for Anſwer alſo to § 2. and § 3. which do but perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the ſame point.</p>
               <p>§ 4. <hi>Herein you ſeeing more (I believe) than Mr.</hi> Baxter, <hi>there is one thing that he ſaw and you ſee not. Juſtification, you ſay, is Gods accounting and uſing us as juſt; but you have not taken in what he ſaith further, That it is alſo the making of us juſt.—How is that? Not by Infuſion, as the Papiſts; nor by Non-imputation, as Mr.</hi> Wotton; <hi>but by Imputation; God imputing our Faith for Righteouſneſs.</hi>] To this I Reply, In my Explication of Juſtification <hi>Active,</hi> (as you call it) or beſtowed by God, ſay I, I took in every thing that I found any ground in Scripture for; for I fetch'd it wholly out of thoſe places of Scripture, there quoted: And whereas it is commonly ſaid to be a Law Term, and therefore we muſt have recourſe to Lawyers to underſtand the true ſenſe of it, I have there, I think, fully opened the nature of it, purely out of Scripture; and, if I miſtake not, more fully and plainly than was done before; and I have ſometimes thought that that was one of the cleareſt things in all my Book. If you think my account defective, and would have any thing elſe added to it, give me your Scripture for it, as I have done for what I ſay, and I'll add it. Till then, here I ſtick.</p>
               <p>But to make my ſenſe more plain, I'll give you a Scheme, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my conception of the whole Matter. There are theſe ſeveral things which muſt be carefully diſtinguiſh'd and conſidered as diſtinct in this caſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Chriſt has obtained at Gods hands, That Faith ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for Righteouſneſs. This is enacting the Law; fixing and eſtabliſhing the Rule, according to which Judgment muſt paſs. None can ſay that this is either making us juſt, or juſtifying us, becauſe it is but a General, as all Laws are.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is the beſtowing of Faith upon us, which is our Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel righteouſneſs; and this now is <hi>making us juſt,</hi> with the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Sanctification; or enduing us with the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> whereby we become conformable to the Rule: Neither is this Juſtification, but Sanctification, or effectual Calling, Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94667:7"/>Converſion, Forming Chriſt in us; all which, with ſome other ſuch Expreſſions, I take to be Synonymous, and to ſignifie the firſt Grace.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Then comes Juſtification, which is judging us conformable to the Rule, or to have performed the Conditions of the Covenant; and this includes three things, which are ſo many Branches or Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients of which it does conſiſt.
<list>
                     <item>(1.) Counting us juſt.</item>
                     <item>(2.) Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. with us as juſt, by beſtowing the benefits of the Covenant, <hi>viz.</hi> Pardon (<hi>that</hi> comes in here) and a Right or Title to the heavenly Inheritance.</item>
                     <item>(3.) Solemnly pronouncing us juſt at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to have performed the Conditions of the Covenant, and ſo abſolving or acquitting us from the Curſe or penalty of the Law, and Adjudging us to Life Eternal.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>§ 5. The ſubſtance of your Diſcourſe in this Paragraph is ſpoken to already in § 4. and your Concluſion in § 1.</p>
               <p>§ 6. You have hit the Nail on the Head, and gueſt very right, both that thoſe two Leaves were inſerted after (it was many Years after) the Book was finiſhed: As alſo that I am afraid of ſpeaking the leaſt tittle that may be derogatory to the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, I ſay it again, and can never inculcate it often enough, That I am afraid of ſpeaking any thing that may be derogatory to the Honour of Chriſt in any reſpect, and would not for all the World be guilty of it: And therefore if any thing ſaid by me here, or there, or any where, be really ſo, I renounce, revoke, recal and condemn it all. Upon this account I added thoſe Leaves to clear the Point, as I thought under conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I cannot call to mind particularly all that is in them; but I think the Scheme in general may be uſeful, though that particular of two Juſtifications ſhould not paſs the Teſt: And indeed as to that, your Argument (§ 7.) is good; <hi>The freeing as from the Law</hi> (ſay you) <hi>is freeing us from it, as a Rule of Judgment, whenas it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains a Rule of Life;</hi> (this is ſo plain, that there can be no ſcruple about it, being underſtood of Believers) <hi>and ſeeing we are not to be judged by it, we cannot be condemned or juſtified by it.</hi> By the Law ſhall no fleſh living be juſtified. <hi>Since therefore it is by the Goſpel that we are to be judged, there can be no other, but one Evangelical Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> This Argument has fully ſatisfied me, that but one Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is to be admitted; and ſo I aſſent to what you add § 8.</p>
               <p>§ 9. If I apprehend your Notion and Senſe aright, it plainly amounts to this, That Chriſt by his Sufferings obtained of God (there is his <hi>Impetration</hi>) that Faith ſhould be <hi>counted for Righteouſneſs:</hi> When we believe, all the ſaving benefits of his Death or Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94667:8"/>(which is his Righteouſneſs or Obedience) are actually applied to, and beſtowed on us. And this I take to be the plain truth alſo.</p>
               <p>§ 10. Your Anſwer to my Queſtion does not ſatisfie me: You don't ſhow what intents and purpoſes the phraſe of <hi>formal Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> ſerves for, which the word [<hi>Way,</hi> or <hi>Condition</hi>] will not anſwer; ſurely there is not as wide a difference between <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> in this caſe, as between <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the point of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Son of God: Neither doth ſo great a weight in point of Doctrine hang upon our difference, as doth upon that. Certainly, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing to uſe a word that may be offenſive, and ſubſtituting another leſs exceptionable in the room of it, may be done without deſerting the Truth, or deſerving a blot. I grant an apt word doth ſometimes decide a Controverſie, where there is a good foundation for it; but that is the Queſtion here, and there does not appear to me any ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for the uſe of it: Tho' that you maintain ſhould be a Truth, yet all Truth is not to be inſiſted upon at all times; eſpecially when it is but a fourth or fifth-rate Truth. What I have ſaid in my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning the intereſt of Faith in Juſtification, I think is both ſafe, inoffenſive and ſatisfactory.</p>
               <p>§ 11. I fully agree to all.</p>
               <p>§ 12. To what you ſay about the <hi>Theſis</hi> or Diſſertation, I conceive it may very fitly be annexed to the Diſcourſe of Juſtification; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the clearing of that Queſtion, which is there handled, but for what you can't deny, to wit, the ſtrengthening of what is there deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. Your Reaſons for me to omit them don't ſatisfie me. Not the firſt; for tho' we don't hold that Chriſt's Righteouſneſs imputed is the <hi>formul Cauſe</hi> of our Juſtification; yet we hold it is the <hi>meritorious Cauſe;</hi> and ſo 'tis as proper for us to diſcuſs this point as for them. For whatſoever difficulty occurs concerning the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt conſidered as the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of Juſtification, the ſame occurs alſo concerning it, conſidered as the <hi>meritorious Cauſe.</hi> Nor the ſecond; for when I ſay, that Chriſt being a Divine, not Human Perſon, was under no obligation of duty, I underſtand it <hi>Originally;</hi> purely upon the account of his being Man, and antecedently to his own volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary undertaking.</p>
               <p>You Object, <hi>How doth Chriſt ſay his Father was greater than he?</hi>] Tell me how you will reconcile that with <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. <hi>He thought it no robbery to be equal with God;</hi> and you will anſwer your ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here you muſt come off and ſay]</hi> I thank you for the Aſſiſtance you lend me; but I am of Age to Anſwer for my ſelf; which with your leave, I do thus,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>How came he down,</hi> ſay you, <hi>to do
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94667:8"/>his Fathers Commandement, and yet be under no Obligation?</hi>] I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Becauſe he voluntarily took that work upon himſelf; for that is it (as far as I remember) that I am there ſpeaking of, That he was not bound by vertue of his Aſſumption of the Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to obey the Law, but only becauſe he agreed ſo to do.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>How do you ſay he only ſuffered for us, and not obeyed for us?]</hi> I anſwer, I deny not his obeying for us in ſome Senſe, but reckon it to his Sufferings.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Well, but what if you are out here at laſt?]</hi> I anſwer, It's poſſible I may; but how does it appear that I am out at laſt? Your enlargement afterwards (for it does not ſeem to me to have the force of a Reaſon or Argument, which) if it were to the purpoſe, muſt be formed thus, Chriſt was obliged to obey the Law for us, becauſe he redeemed us from the Obligation of perfect fulfilling it, as the Condition of Life (for that is it you inſiſt upon, to prove that I am out;) But this (ſay I) is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>; nothing to the purpoſe.</item>
                  </list> That Chriſt redeemed us from the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of perfect fulfilling the Law, as the Condition of Life, I agree; but how does that prove, that he obeyed the Law in our ſtead? However, as to the thing it ſelf, his freeing us from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect obedience to the Law as the Condition of Life, I don't take to be the immediate effect of his Obedience: I don't reckon that that was obtain'd immediately by his obeying the Law in our ſtead, but by his obtaining the New Covenant for us, which promiſes Life upon eaſier Terms than the Law, or Old one did.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He obeyed and ſuffered both in our ſtead.]</hi> That Notion I cannot ſwallow. I cannot apprehend that we are bound to obey and ſuffer both. But I think this is ſpoken to in the <hi>Theſis,</hi> whither I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you.</p>
               <p>Thus I have gone through the ſeveral Paragraphs in your Letter, whereby you will find your labour has not been in vain, but has had ſome ſucceſs upon me. I am a Searcher after, and a Servant of Truth, and don't count my ſelf too old to learn, eſpecially of you, who have look'd ſo throughly into and round about this Point of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. How far forth my Reply, in thoſe things wherein we differ, will approve it ſelf to you, and find acceptance with you, muſt be left to the Tryal. In the whole I have deſign'd nothing but words both of Truth and Kindneſs; and ſo do hope that you will find no reaſon to judge otherwiſe of me than that I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your reſpectful Friend and Fellow-labourer,</hi> Samuel Clark.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:94667:9"/>
               <head>To Mr. <hi>Clark.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear and worthy Brother,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>JUſtification is <hi>Conſtitutive</hi> and <hi>Sentential; Juris</hi> and <hi>Judicis:</hi> Conſtitutive is <hi>making, accounting</hi> and <hi>uſing</hi> us as <hi>juſt;</hi> Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial <hi>declares</hi> us ſo at the great day. This I hold to be good from Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who in all his Books ſays the like; but in his own manner and words. See <hi>Cath. Theol.</hi> Book I. Part. II. Pag. 69, 70. <hi>Life of Faith.</hi> Pag. 326. <hi>End of Controverſies.</hi> Pag. 242. Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication then with us is Making, Eſteeming and Uſing us as Righteous, which are diſtinguiſhed, but not to be divided. <hi>Conſtitutive</hi> Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication (you ſay) is a phraſe of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s coyning, and the word <hi>[Juſtifie]</hi> (which you have ſo throughly canvaſed) neither in the Hebrew or Greek, will bear it. For my part ſo long as the Engliſh and Latine word <hi>Juſtify</hi> (as Sanctifie, Glorifie) does ſpeak <hi>making juſt,</hi> and we have the very term expreſſed (<hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>made righteous</hi> (which is all one as to be juſtified.) I think that place alone ground enough, for Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s word <hi>Conſtitutive,</hi> and whether the word will or no, the matter will bear it. When I read <hi>Contarenus de Juſtificatione,</hi> I admired to ſee the Doctrine of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſo fully embraced by a <hi>Cardinal,</hi> who telling us of a twofold Righteouſneſs we attained by Faith, a <hi>Juſtitia inbarons,</hi> and a <hi>Juſtitia donata &amp; imputata Chriſti,</hi> and propoſing the Queſtion, <hi>Utra num debeamus niti &amp; exiſtimal nos juſtificari coram Deo, id eſt, ſanctos &amp; juſtos haberi, an hac an illa;</hi> he cleaves to the laſt with theſe words I have quoted. <hi>Pacif.</hi> p. 15. <hi>Ego prorſus exiſtimo</hi>— And moreover he tells us, <hi>Fide juſtificamur, non formaliter</hi> but<note n="†" place="margin">It is falſe that Faith juſtifies us <hi>Efficiently:</hi> but it is true that Faith juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth <hi>Conſtitutively,</hi> ſo far as it is it ſelf our perſonal inherent rightcouſneſs. <hi>Bax. End of Cont.</hi> p. 270.</note> 
                  <hi>Efficienter,</hi> which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt my Judgment, yet do I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that this he lays down at firſt as a thing unqueſtionable, that <hi>Juſtificari</hi> is <hi>Juſtum fieri, &amp; propterea juſtum haberi.</hi> I confeſs my ſelf was long before I could aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in this, becauſe he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me uncertain, or confuſed, when by <hi>making juſt,</hi> he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times underſtands (as you) <hi>Regeneration;</hi> ſometimes <hi>Pardon,</hi> after Mr. <hi>Wotton,</hi> from whom I believe he took it; and ſometimes both, as appears in the place you cite, <hi>Cath. Theol.</hi> Book II. Pag. 239. <hi>By and upon believing, we are firſt</hi> made juſt, <hi>by free-given Pardon and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94667:9"/>Right to Life, and true Sanctification with it, and we are ſentenced</hi> juſt, <hi>becauſe ſo firſt made juſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Papiſt ſay, Juſtification makes us juſt, by the infuſion of inherent Holineſs, and that this infuſed Grace or inherent Holineſs is therefore the formal Cauſe of our Juſtification, which we know confounds <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Sactification.</hi> The Proteſtant in oppoſition to this have generally ſaid that we are <hi>made juſt,</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19.) by Chriſts Righteouſneſs, and that his Righteouſneſs imputed, muſt be conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently our formal Righteouſneſs, tho' ſeveral of late more cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, take heed how they ſay that. <hi>Sententia illorum qui Chriſti Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam &amp; juſtitiam nobis imputatam ſtatuunt eſſe formalem cauſam juſtificationis, communis eſt noſtrorum omnium ſententia,</hi> ſays <hi>Davenant,</hi> Mr: <hi>Wotton,</hi> that Scholaſtically deep Man, in oppoſition to both, does ſay that it is <hi>Pardon</hi> makes the ſinner righteous, and conſequently that <hi>Pardon</hi> is the Form or formal Reaſon of our Juſtification. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> you ſee before accounts we are made righteous by Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Pardon both our Evengelical Righteouſneſs muſt be with him both the <hi>formal</hi> Cauſe, though the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt be the <hi>material</hi> (he ſays) and <hi>meritorius</hi> Cauſe, of it. Leading <hi>Calvin</hi> hath gone before our <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and tells us, <hi>Nos Juſtificationem ſimpliciter interpretamur acceptionem qua nos Deus in gratiam receptos pro juſtis habet: Eam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in peccatorum remiſſione, ac juſtitiae Chriſti imputatione poſitam eſſe dicimus.</hi> Inſt. l. 3. c. 11. For my own part, I am here exactly for neither of theſe, but ſay, that it is the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God revealed in the Goſpel,</hi> that makes us juſt, and that this is the <hi>formal Reaſon</hi> of our Juſtification.</p>
               <p>I will recite it; The <hi>Infuſion</hi> of inherent Grace, is Juſtification <hi>Active</hi> with the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and this inherent Grace infuſed, Juſtification <hi>Paſſive.</hi> The <hi>Imputation</hi> of Chriſts Righteouſneſs is Juſtification <hi>Active</hi> with the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and that Righteouſneſs imputed Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Paſſive.</hi> Pardon with Mr. <hi>Wotton.</hi> Both Pardon and a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſubordinate to Chriſts, with Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> But as to me, I continue and ſay, the <hi>Imputation</hi> of the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> or of <hi>Faith for Righteouſneſs,</hi> is <hi>Active</hi> Juſtification, and the <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God</hi> or <hi>Faith,</hi> ſo <hi>imputed,</hi> is Juſtification <hi>Paſſive,</hi> or the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> (as <hi>Paſſive</hi>) of it.</p>
               <p>This one thing I take to be certain, that the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> which the Apoſtle tells us, is <hi>now revealed,</hi> and therefore <hi>before,</hi> tho' <hi>occult</hi> in the World, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> hath it, is that Righteouſneſs in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to any other whereby we are juſtified, and you having given
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94667:10"/>us ſo good an account and right Notion of it in your <hi>Annotations</hi> on the <hi>Old,</hi> and on the <hi>New</hi> Teſtament, beſides what you have ſaid in your preſent Book, it is fit you go thro' and perfect it. By this <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> you underſtand not the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, with the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ordinarily, nor yet the Righteouſneſs Inherent the <hi>Papiſts</hi> contend for, whereof indeed you are over-afraid. <hi>Not by the Works of Righteouſneſs we have done,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle in one place, where he means the Righteouſneſs according to the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> or our <hi>Natural Righteouſneſs,</hi> which is <hi>Mans,</hi> not <hi>this</hi> Righteouſneſs of <hi>God,</hi> but <hi>that</hi> which by <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall we have quite loſt, inſomuch as there could be no Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Earth any more (as I ſay in my Books) if it were not for another brought in, and there is one brought in by the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and as <hi>ſlain</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> that is, procured by Chriſts Death, and which you in your <hi>Annotations</hi> tells us right, is this <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> intended by the Apoſtle. <hi>Of God,</hi> being of his inſtitution in diſtinction to that of <hi>Nature,</hi> or of <hi>Man,</hi> and is otherwhere call'd the Righteouſneſs <hi>which is of Faith,</hi> and the Righteouſneſs, <hi>of Faith.</hi> Which is of <hi>Faith,</hi> that is, (ſay you) obtained by Faith, and <hi>of Faith;</hi> Faith it ſelf being it, as imputed to us for Righteouſneſs by the Law of the Goſpel, which is ſtyled therefore, the <hi>Miniſtration of Righteouſneſs.</hi> Now when we ſhall find this Notion in the particular places of your <hi>Annotations</hi> ſo well propoſed, you muſt give me leave to carry it thro' to what it leads, and let you know (which indeed makes it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie) that it is this <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and no other is that which is the Form, <hi>formal Cauſe,</hi> or formal Reaſon, of our Juſtification.</p>
               <p>Note I pray, once for all, that in putting in the word, <hi>[our]</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, by me, is ſignified to be <hi>paſſively</hi> taken, as it muſt be taken, and is by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in their Diſpute about it; and by the Apoſtle, when he diſputes that it is by Faith, and not <hi>Works,</hi> that <hi>Abraham</hi> was, and we are <hi>juſtified.</hi> And here then have we indeed an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a thing you have found out, wherein the Cautious of our Proteſtants of late have been, and are at a loſs, even the knowledge (when they durſt neither allow Chriſts Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, nor our own to be the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi>) what indeed the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> is. For making which appear, and that I ſpeak not without Book, be pleaſed to know. It is an Objection which muſt needs be ready to come into every ones mind, that if we be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Chriſts Righteouſneſs imputed, that is, ſo as his Righteouſneſs be accounted ours formally, to juſtifie us, then muſt we be thereby as righteous (in Law ſenſe) as Chriſt himſelf. This Argument be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94667:10"/>urged by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> our <hi>Ameſius</hi> thus Anſwers, <hi>Has non eſt noſtra ſententia, ſed Chriſti juſtitiam eatenus robis imputari, ut ejus virtute nos perinde juſti cenſeamur coram Deo, ac ſi noſmetipſi in nobis habere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quo juſti cenſeamur.</hi> See here the ſtreight this throwly vers'd Man in theſe Diſputes is brought to. He muſt deny this at firſt, that Chriſts Righteouſneſs is <hi>noſtra &amp; formalis juſtitia,</hi> which <hi>Davenant,</hi> with others maintain. And if Chriſts be not, what is? A Righteouſneſs there muſt be to make us Righreous; and to be the Form of our Juſtification, and what is it? Note, Secondly, That Chriſts Righteouſneſs muſt be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but nor imputed as <hi>ours,</hi> for then it will be our formal Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But ſo far imputed. (Note Thirdly) that by verture of it we ſhall be accounted juſt before God. Well then (Note fourthly) I muſt ask, what Righteouſneſs that is, wherein or whereby we are accounted righteous before God? Is it <hi>his?</hi> No, for then it were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us as ours, and it were our <hi>formal</hi> Righteouſneſs, which at firſt he renounces as not the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Opinion: It it our <hi>own</hi> inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Righteouſneſs? He dares not own that, as ſuppoſing it altogether the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Opinion. What Righteouſneſs then? Why, ſuch (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it be) that is <hi>all one as if we our ſelves had in us that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may be adjudged righteous before God.</hi> Note it; it is not <hi>qua,</hi> referring to Chriſts Righteouſueſs, but <hi>quo,</hi> referring to one under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that is, not in us, but as good as if it were in us; and that not <hi>Chriſts</hi> (I ſay) neither, but one by vertue of his Righteouſneſs imputed, and is not. If Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> had known our <hi>middle way,</hi> there needed no ſuch ſhifting as this, to make us juſtified without a Righteouſneſs, or <hi>formal</hi> Righteouſneſs, neither in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for fear of this <hi>Objection,</hi> nor in our ſelves for fear of <hi>Popery.</hi> For God be thanked, there is a Righteouſneſs, and that whereby we are juſtified, that is neither of them, even the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> which is not the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Chriſt</hi> who is God, nor the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Works,</hi> or Papiſtical Righteouſneſs, but a Righteouſneſs <hi>revealed</hi> in the Goſpel, in oppoſition to Works, or the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Faith</hi> imputed to the Believer for Righteouſneſs, through the vertue or merit of our Redeemer, for his Juſtification and Salvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whenever we read if imputing or accounting to a Man, a thing that is good, it is an Act of Grace, and ſignifies ſomething which is not,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>Truman.</hi> It is ſo in the imputing Faith for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, for there is a donation of two things by it, which in us are not. One is <hi>Chriſts Merit,</hi> or the virtue of it to render our Faith accepted, and the other a <hi>Right</hi> to the benefits, or reward, which a perfect Righteouſneſs would give us if we had it. Our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94667:11"/>Faith or Evangelical Righteouſneſs, being imperfect and no Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs by the Law, it is, upon theſe two things conferred, made ſuch a Righteouſneſs (being <hi>imputed</hi> to us <hi>for Righteouſneſs</hi>) by the Law of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I hope now Brother you will be leſs afraid of our falling in with the Papiſts, though Juſtification is the <hi>making</hi> us juſt, as well as <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting</hi> us juſt; and though our inchoate Grace, our Faith, our Evangelick Performance, acceped through Chriſt, be our <hi>formal Righteouſneſs,</hi> (which you are ſo backward to conſent to) becauſe, beſides that this Righteouſneſs hath not the ſame <hi>Rule</hi> to be judged by, with theirs, nor is of the ſame <hi>Quality</hi> as theirs, for they mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the ſame by the <hi>Law,</hi> and yet maintain a <hi>Meritorius</hi> Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and <hi>Perfection</hi> (which difference you find in my Book); I ſay, beſides this, the inherent Righteouſneſs it ſelf of our <hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> is not the ſame with theirs of <hi>Regeneration.</hi> It is the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs <hi>of God,</hi> which is of his inſtitution, to be diſtinguiſhed from that of ours, whether it be the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Nature</hi> (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) which we have not, or of the inherent <hi>Grace</hi> we have; the one coming to us by <hi>Infuſion,</hi> the other by <hi>Imputation;</hi> God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting (I ſay) to us that imperfect Grace for Righteouſneſs, by this Law of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>This will appear yet further, by my proceeding to your Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions. <hi>I grant</hi> (you ſay in one of your Letters) <hi>that we muſt be made juſt before we can be accounted juſt, but that is by beſtowing Faith upon us, Juſtification is relative Grace, and that is founded in Real, or ſuppoſes Real Grace, as the Foundation of it, and making us juſt, which is Real Grace, muſt not be reduced to Juſtification, that is Grace Relative.</hi> This is ſomething in the Ore, but let us melt it and improve it; and I ſay, that here is Confuſion indeed, but I hope not mine. You miſtake firſt in not diſtinguiſhing <hi>making juſt.</hi> All making juſt is not <hi>Real</hi> Grace, or by giving Faith, but there is a making juſt alſo which is <hi>Relative</hi> Grace, (if Juſtification it ſelf be Relative Grace) and that is not by <hi>beſtowing,</hi> but by <hi>imputing</hi> Faith already beſtowed to us, <hi>for Righteouſneſs.</hi> You miſtake next in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I reduce your <hi>making just</hi> to <hi>Juſtification,</hi> (by <hi>reducing,</hi> you mean rendring them one) for <hi>your</hi> making juſt by beſtowing Faith; is <hi>Regeneration,</hi> which I diſtinguiſh from <hi>Juſtification,</hi> as you and all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do. Juſtification <hi>makes juſt,</hi> otherwiſe. In the next place you tell me of <hi>Relative</hi> Grace being founded on <hi>Real</hi> Grace, but I ſee not wherein that ſerves you, or oppoſes me. <hi>Real</hi> Grace I take it, is that which makes a change on the <hi>Perſon,</hi> but <hi>Relative</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94667:11"/>Grace only on the <hi>State,</hi> giving right to the benefits which belongs to the Perſon. I apprehend ſo of that Diſtinction, and if I do not apprehend you right, you muſt help my Underſtanding. Well, now <hi>Regeneration,</hi> I count with you, muſt precede <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that is, <hi>Real</hi> Grace. Upon this Real Grace then is founded that <hi>making us righteous,</hi> which is <hi>Relative.</hi> There is Faith already wrought and preſuppoſed, and God in juſtifying us, does by his Goſpel-Law (I count) <hi>conſtitute,</hi> or make that <hi>Faith</hi> to be a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs (which otherwiſe it was not) that gives right to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits that a perfect Righteouſneſs, if performed, would give: The Regenerate Man (I ſay) believes; Upon his believing, the Goſpel-Law, or God by that Law, does <hi>impute</hi> that believing to him <hi>for Righteouſneſs:</hi> By which <hi>Imputation</hi> be is made, accounted and uſed as a righteous Perſon, and ſo reaps the benefit. All which toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is his Juſtification.</p>
               <p>Let us here ſet our Horſes together. There is a Righteouſneſs, or the Grace of <hi>Regeneration;</hi> or a Righteouſneſs, or the Grace of <hi>Juſtification.</hi> One is <hi>Real</hi> Grace, and the other <hi>Relative,</hi> you ſay, and therefore two. Nevertheleſs, when you ſay the Righteouſneſs that <hi>makes us juſt,</hi> is <hi>Regeneration,</hi> you do not ſee that this Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs muſt not therefore be that which juſtifies us, or that which I ſay is the formal Cauſe of our Juſtification. It is true, that our Righteouſneſs or Faith wrought in us by Vocation, Regeneration, or Sanctification is the ſame Righteouſneſs <hi>materially,</hi> but not the ſame <hi>formally</hi> with this Righteouſneſs of Juſtification; for if a Man were the moſt righteous Perſon upon Earth, there were no reward due to it, being imperfect, and it could not be this Righteouſneſs in Gods ſight, giving right to the benefit (that is, this <hi>Relative</hi> Grace) but for the Law of Grace and his Inſtitution by it. A right to Impunity and Life, is Righteouſneſs, and that is not the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Regeneration.</p>
               <p>You ſay, God Regenerates us, and that makes us righteous: Very well, and I tell you that this is the Righteouſneſs of the <hi>Perſon,</hi> which juſtifies not (and ſo I am no <hi>Papiſt:</hi>) but it is a Righteouſneſs of the <hi>State,</hi> the Righteouſneſs (I ſay) which is <hi>made</hi> ſo by the Goſpel-Law, or that <hi>Relative</hi> Righteouſneſs, which does give right to the reward or benefit, when the other imperfect cannot, is the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs we intend. When a Man then is <hi>made righteous</hi> by God, or by his Law upon his believing, who was made righteous before by <hi>Regeneration;</hi> or when a Man hath Faith beſtowed on him in his effectual Vocation, and that <hi>Faith</hi> after is <hi>imputed</hi> to him <hi>for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs;</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:94667:12"/>it is not his Faith and Righteouſneſs as inherent, but as ſo <hi>imputed,</hi> is that Righteouſneſs which juſtifies him, or that <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> that is the <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>formal</hi> Cauſe of his Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>You may ſee here how by going to avoid Popery, by denying that we are <hi>made juſt</hi> by Juſtification, you take away that <hi>Medium,</hi> which by the granting and maintaining, we muſt obtain our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <hi>God</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Baxter) as Law-giver above his Laws, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth us juſt by his pardoning Law or Covenant; and as determining Judge, be juſtifies us by Eſteeming and Sentencing us juſt; and as Executioner, he uſes us as juſt.</hi> All know ſuch things are ſpoken in order of <hi>nature,</hi> not of <hi>time,</hi> which I need not mention before, or now, but to avoid Cavil. You deny this <hi>Conſtitutive</hi> Juſtification, but what ſay you to the Matter? Does God by his Law of Grace make a Man juſt upon his believing? To be <hi>made righteous</hi> is to be <hi>juſtified</hi> in Law-ſenſe, and <hi>juſtifiable</hi> by Sentence. If God do ſo, as the Law is general, then muſt a particular Man believing, be in the applying only that Law to him, made righteous; <hi>made</hi> ſo in order to his being <hi>accounted,</hi> and uſed as ſuch. And if God, by that Law applyed to him, makes the Perſon righteous, it is that Righteouſneſs muſt be, and is the formal Cauſe of his Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>This my dear Brother you did not perceive, nor (as I think) Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> quite, who came ſo near it. He never let the right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> (preceding actual Pardon) ſink into his Thoughts; if he had, he would have ſet it into ſuch a Light, as there would have been no need of my Book; and if he had roundly told you, as I, what is the <hi>formal Righteouſneſs</hi> that juſtifies the Believer, notwithſtanding other <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſay it not, you might have received it. Though as to that <hi>Particular</hi> Juſtification, or <hi>Part</hi> of Juſtification, againſt the Goſpel-charge that a Man is an Unbeliever and Impenitent, and hath no right to Pardon and Life, he accounts that his Faith and Repentance is that <hi>Subordinate Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> which juſtifies him, and that muſt be <hi>formaliter,</hi> as I ſay. And to ſatisfie Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> fully, there is, and there can be <hi>no charge but this</hi> againſt any; for the Goſpel-Law it ſelf, the Univerſal Pardon, or Grace of the Goſpel it ſelf (which in the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> as to Gods part, is included) does alone take off, or anſwers <hi>all others.</hi> But now ſeeing I am yet in doubt that your fear of me, and therefore of other Friends, is not yet gone, in regard to my allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we are juſtified by a Righteouſneſs <hi>within us,</hi> or by our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94667:12"/>inherent Grace, for that I percieve it is you fear even as rank Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, under the preſent apprehenſion, when Juſtification yet by <hi>Works,</hi> you maintain without ſcruple: I will endeavour over again to deliver you and them out of it. Faith, you know, (and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) to be Grace inherent, and a Righteouſneſs in us, and you are not afraid (I hope) to affirm that we are <hi>juſtified by Faith.</hi> Well then, there is according to your Self before, and the Truth, a double Grace; <hi>Real</hi> Grace, and <hi>Relative</hi> Grace, and <hi>Juſtification</hi> you ſay, is <hi>Relative</hi> Grace, <hi>Regeneration</hi> Real. I ſay again accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, there muſt be <hi>a double Righteouſneſs,</hi> the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Sanctification</hi> or <hi>Regeneration,</hi> and the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Juſtification.</hi> 0103 0 The one entitles to no Reward, being ſhort of perfect, the other (through the imputation of Chriſts Merits) entitles to Impunity and Life; for the imputing Chriſts Merits to our Faith, or inherent Grace to make it accepted (as hath already been intimated) for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, which elſe were none, is to be underſtood in Gods <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Faith for Righteouſneſs.</hi> It is the Righteouſneſs of the <hi>laſt,</hi> now be it known, and not of the <hi>former,</hi> by which we are juſtified. It is the Righteouſneſs of the <hi>laſt,</hi> not of the <hi>former,</hi> which is the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſtification. Here then do I at once diſcharge you from your Fear. The Papiſts ſay we are juſtified by the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of <hi>Regeneration,</hi> and they are out: We ſay, and are right, by the other.</p>
               <p>Let me ſay this yet fuller again, for when the Mind is prepoſſeſt with a contrary belief, and the <hi>Intùs exiſtens</hi> does prohibit <hi>alienum,</hi> there is no hope for a New Notion to be received without inculcation, which therefore is to be uſed and approved. Thus far for certain you and I do agree: <hi>Regeneration</hi> is one thing, and <hi>Juſtification</hi> another, when the <hi>Papiſt</hi> ſay they are the ſame. We agree conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that there is a double Grace and Righteouſneſs, of the one, and of the other. We agree ſtill, that one is <hi>Real</hi> Grace, the other <hi>Relative,</hi> and muſt be different. The one, I have ſaid, makes a change on the <hi>Perſon,</hi> the other on the <hi>State</hi> only, or <hi>Condition;</hi> that is, the one does endue the Soul with a New Quality, which of a <hi>wicked</hi> Man makes him <hi>godly;</hi> the other confers no New <hi>Quality,</hi> but a New <hi>Relation</hi> upon that Quality; (<hi>Relative</hi> Grace, as you ſay, being founded on <hi>Real</hi>) that is, the Relation of a juſtified Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or righteous Man in Gods ſight, which brings a right to the Benefits or Reward due to a righteous Perſon, or due to one if he had perfectly fulfill'd the Law of God: This ſure are we agreed in, that Juſtification does confer a right of Impunity and Glory (which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94667:13"/>is the Summ of thoſe Benefits) to a Perſon which was not due to his Faith and imperfect Obedience, but that God does impute them to him for Righteouſneſs; ſo that this Right therefore does come to him, not by <hi>Infuſion,</hi> (I ſay in my Book) but <hi>Imputation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To be ſhort and full: Righteouſneſs conſiſts in a Conformity to a Law. A Law hath its <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Sanction.</hi> Faith is a Conformity to, and a Righteouſneſs according to the <hi>Precept</hi> of the Law of Grace. A Right to pardon and Glory is a Conformity to, and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs according to the <hi>Premium Sanction.</hi> When a Man believes the Law of Grace (or God by that Law) does impute his Faith to him for Righteouſneſs, and thereby conſtitutes him righteous, and with that Righteouſneſs confers on him a Right to the Reward of it. This Right to the Reward, or Righteouſneſs conſiſting in this Right, is (and can be only) <hi>Relative</hi> Grace, not <hi>Regeneration</hi> or <hi>Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> which is <hi>Real</hi> Grace, but the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and this diſtinguiſhes our Doctrine from the Papiſts. A Right (I muſt ſay it again) to Impunity and Life is a <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and that Righteouſneſs not the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Regneration,</hi> but <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts,</hi> I repeat, do ſay it is by the <hi>One</hi> that we are juſtified, <hi>We</hi> ſay it is by the <hi>Other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you have my account of Juſtification <hi>Conſtitutive,</hi> and hence you may have an account of that Text which is elſe ſo hard in Words, and various in the Interpretation. <hi>God juſtifies the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly.</hi> The Man who is juſtified is a Believer, but notwithſtanding his Faith and imperfect Obedience he is <hi>legally</hi> Unrighteous, <hi>Ungodly,</hi> a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Now if Juſtification be only the <hi>Accounting,</hi> not <hi>Making</hi> a Man Righteous, how can God juſtifie the Unrighteous, or him that is <hi>Ungodly?</hi> The Judgment of God is according to Truth, and it were impoſſible. But when Juſtification is the <hi>Making</hi> or <hi>Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> a Man righteous (to wit, not by Infuſion, I ſay, but by Imputation) and <hi>propterea</hi> (as <hi>Contarenus</hi> before hath it) the <hi>Accounting</hi> and <hi>Uſing</hi> him as ſuch, we ſee how the Believer, though <hi>Ungodly,</hi> is juſtified.</p>
               <p>If any Catholick hereupon ſhall receive this, and will expreſs his Doctrine of <hi>Inherent Grace,</hi> as I do, and ſay, that it is not by a Righteouſneſs according to the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> which though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſed, and by the Spirit is <hi>Mans</hi> Righteouſneſs ſtill and imperfect, but by the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> (which is ours, and yet not ours as to what is imputed to it) that is, by a Righteouſneſs of Gods making or inſtituting, by the law of the Goſpel, that he is juſtified; then were he in the right, and I ſhould embrace that Papiſt, as I do you and Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> Let a Man be a <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> or <hi>Arminian,</hi> or <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:94667:13"/>or <hi>Socinian,</hi> the truth in his Mouth is truth, as well as in the Mouth of our Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> or in the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the Scheme you offer in laying matters together upon ſuppoſition, that Juſtification is not <hi>Conſtitutive,</hi> or <hi>Making,</hi> but only the <hi>accounting</hi> and <hi>uſing</hi> us as juſt, I acknowledge it very agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; but we muſt not yield to you (you ſee all this while, we muſt not) that ſuppoſition; it would undo us. No, we muſt for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler comprehending this Frame or Order of Things, take more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs than you do, and which may confirm what is ſpoken. We muſt firſt then conſider that there is an <hi>Act of Grace</hi> procured for us by Chriſt, which is the <hi>Law of the Goſpel,</hi> whereby all Perſons, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding our ſins, ſhall upon their Faith and Repentance be, pardoned and ſaved; and in order hereunto this Law does Enact That ſuch Perſons as believe and repent ſhall (as ſet before God) be <hi>judged</hi> righteous, according to this <hi>Act,</hi> (notwithſtanding there is no Man but is unrighteous, according to the Law of <hi>Nature</hi>) and upon that <hi>Judgment</hi> of him to be righteous, or upon that <hi>judicial Proceeding</hi> in the mind of God (as we muſt ſuppoſe Juſtification to be) he ſhall have the Benefit of the <hi>Act,</hi> and no otherwiſe. Now Sir, the firſt thing in the applying the <hi>Act</hi> to the Believer therefore is this, that upon his believing and repenting, it <hi>Makes</hi> him righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, for elſe his being a ſinner, notwithſtanding his Faith, he could not be judged righteous, but being <hi>made</hi> ſo, he is <hi>judged</hi> ſo by the ſame <hi>Acts,</hi> and is to be ſo uſed. It is not the <hi>Pardon</hi> which makes him righteous, becauſe he muſt be judged by the Law and found righteous, before he have that Pardon, or Benefit of the <hi>Act,</hi> which is <hi>That,</hi> and <hi>Life.</hi> And it is not <hi>Regeneration</hi> or <hi>Faith</hi> makes him righteous, becauſe that is prerequired as the Condition to his being <hi>made</hi> ſo, and that is no Righteouſneſs as yet: But it is God by this Act <hi>imputing</hi> this Faith and Repentance (which is wrought in our Regeneration) <hi>for Righteouſneſs,</hi> that <hi>makes</hi> him righteous, and being (I ſay) ſo <hi>made,</hi> he does judge, account and uſe him ſo, in confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Benefits, which altogether go in to Juſtification.</p>
               <p>I proceed to another paſſage in your Letter. <hi>I do not ſee at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> (ſay you) <hi>how to avoid the dint and force of your Reaſoning, that Faith is the formal Cauſe of our Juſtification: However I would not lay too much ſtreſs upon a Logical or Metaphiſical Term. They that will grant we are juſtified by Faith is aplain ſenſe, without Tropes or Figures, ſhall paſs for ſound in the Faith for me, whether they call it the Form or formal Cauſe, or no.</hi> I thank my Friend for this <hi>Item.</hi> It is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94667:14"/>by Tropes and Figures our Proteſtants ſpeak or dinarily, when they ſay we are juſtified by Faith <hi>Objectivè, in ſenſu correlativo,</hi> that is by Chriſt, or his Righteouſneſs apprehended by Faith. Put <hi>Chriſt</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) for <hi>Faith,</hi> and read ſuch and ſuch Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſee what ſtrange ſenſe it will make. It is our Doctrine which is plain without ſuch Tropes and Figures. And for what you ſay, that if any ſhall ſet forth the true Doctrine, without any <hi>Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> and <hi>Metaphiſical</hi> Terms, you ſhall approve them; I ſay the ſame, if they can indeed but ſoundly do it without them. But for all that, we muſt (by your leave) keep faſt to this Term; for there is more weight lies upon it than to part with it, and the conſequence is yet more than you ſee. We know what Controverſies we <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have among our ſelves, as well as with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> about the <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs;</hi> and you may be pleaſed alſo to know, that a right and ſavoury Uſe of this Term will reconcile the ſound among us, I mean be a ground for it, or at leaſt go ſo far toward it as to ſhield us from the Antinomian Errors, which are here mainly to be feared. If a Man in good earneſt ſhall believe that Chriſts Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, is ſo imputed to him as to be made <hi>formally</hi> his, he muſt then needs think that God can ſee no ſin in ſuch a Righteouſneſs as his, and that then he hath no need of Repentance, or indeed of any farther Holy Living (retaining but ſtill his Faith) in order to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Heaven. You know the train unto which ſuch Doctrine does lead. Whereas if we but diſtinguiſh now of Chriſts Righteouſneſs being ours <hi>meritoriè,</hi> not <hi>formaliter,</hi> if we ſay we are juſtified by it <hi>per modum meriti,</hi> not <hi>per modum cauſae formalis,</hi> which is all one as to ſay it is <hi>imputed,</hi> but not as <hi>ours, in ſe,</hi> but in the <hi>effects,</hi> then is this great Article preſently ſtated; the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> I ſay, that are ſound, reconciled, the <hi>Antinomian</hi> Concluſions diſcarded, and all danger in our Differences quite over.</p>
               <p>There are Scriptures, <hi>He is made to us Righteouſneſs. By his Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience we are made Righteous. The Lord our Righteouſneſs,</hi> and the like. I never could come to have ſatisfaction about them in my mind, but by the Impreſſion of this diſtinction upon it. The definition of Juſtification by the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> if our being <hi>accounted righteous for the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> were underſtood <hi>formaliter,</hi> it were not to be born. And yet how few of our Miniſters themſelves have underſtood otherwiſe, and knew it not but they underſtood it right? There are Paſſages collected out of Dr. <hi>Bates</hi>'s <hi>Harmony,</hi> to confront ſome others out of the Books of Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> (the induſtrious Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector did wiſely to make the Doctor, not himſelf the Accuſer): But
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94667:14"/>let this grain of Salt be applyed (with the conſent of the good Doctor) and the jarr may ceaſe eaſily, when our Brethren in their Differences elſe are <hi>Andabata</hi> to one another without it. <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who in his Diſpute with us about Juſtification, does reduce all our Differences with them to this Point, whether it be <hi>Chriſts</hi> Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs or our own <hi>inherent</hi> Righteouſneſs that is the <hi>Cauſa formalis</hi> of it; and ſuppoſing he hath evinced that it cannot be <hi>Chriſts,</hi> he fears not to be thus laviſh in granting to us as follows, <hi>Dicitur Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus juſtitia noſira, quoniam ſatisfecit Patri pro nobis, &amp; eam ſatisfactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ita nobis donat &amp; communicat cum nos juſtificat, ut noſtra ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factio &amp; juſtitia dici poteſt. Hoc modo nou eſſet abſurdum ſi quis dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret nobis imputari Chriſti juſtitiam &amp; merita, cum nobis donarentur &amp; applicentur ac ſi nos ipſi Deo ſatisfeciſſemus.</hi> By this paſſage of the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> who looks on his cauſe, not to ſuffer by his giving thus much, (that is, more than what I can tell in his ſenſe to make of) ſo long only as the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt be not made our <hi>formal Righteouſneſs,</hi> (the negative whereof be ſure he holds faſt, and it muſt be yielded him) I am convinced, and will make bold to avouch, that let our Proteſtants expreſs their Sentiments about this great Article, with ſo much variety as they do, and as much as they will, yet if they, in their fierceſt Conteſts for a Righteouſneſs <hi>without us,</hi> againſt a Righteouſneſs <hi>within us</hi> to be juſtified, do but underſtand, and will yield to be underſtood with this <hi>Salvo,</hi> or under this Confinement of <hi>Per modum Meriti, non formaliter,</hi> (which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alone thinks worthy the confuting) the danger (I ſaid before) is over, and they agreed.</p>
               <p>Alas! what an abſurd thing was it at firſt, to the <hi>Papiſts</hi> for the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to ſay that we are juſtified by <hi>Chriſts</hi> Righteouſneſs, it was all one as to ſay a Man is learn'd with anothers Learning, or Rich with anothers Riches. Let me tell you Brother, that to ſay we are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>formaliter</hi> by Chriſts Righteouſneſs, is the ſame abſurd Thing ſtill, and the Abſurdity is ſeen ſufficiently of late by our more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate Divines, as appears in my Quotation of Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> in yours of Mr. <hi>Anthony Burgeſſe,</hi> in Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> of <hi>Prideux,</hi> and many others occaſionally in his Books. Upon which account you are to conſider, that whereas you and I do go a middle way, between <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> and <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and conſequently diſſent from, and agree with both in ſome reſpects, there is this great Reaſon (which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of me) for our keeping up theſe <hi>Terms,</hi> which <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and <hi>Papiſt</hi> were engaged in, becauſe we have hereby a ground for the ſure forming of our Difference in regard to the Common <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:94667:15"/>when otherwiſe it would be difficult to ſay, what that is wherein we differ from them, without raiſing great prejudice againſt our Cauſe. While we ſeek to make our Difference from the <hi>Papiſt</hi> more clear than yet it hath been made, we may be glad that we need no more but the uſe of theſe Terms <hi>[Form, formal Cauſe]</hi> for declaring our Difference from the Brethren, that are for maintaining the formerly received Doctrine of the Proteſtant in this great Article. <hi>Juſtificabitur ille fide</hi> (ſays <hi>Calvin</hi>) <hi>qui operum juſtitia excluſus, Chriſti juſtitiam per fidem apprehendit, qua veſtitus in Dei conſpectis non ut peccator, ſed tanquam juſtus apparet.</hi> Note I pray, the word <hi>[tanquam]</hi> which manifeſtly ſhews a Reluctancy in that great Mans Mind, ſo that he could not ſay <hi>juſtus,</hi> which our Common Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant apprehends. Nay, indeed if we were thus <hi>cloathed</hi> with Chriſts Righteouſneſs, (and that as to our <hi>Perſons,</hi> when our accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation through Chriſt is of what we ſincerely <hi>Do,</hi> God being no <hi>Accepter of Perſons</hi>) or if Faith ſo receives his Righteouſneſs, as to make it ours <hi>in ſe,</hi> for our Juſtification, then could it not be ſaid by the Apoſtle, that <hi>God juſtifies the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly,</hi> unto which <hi>non pecoator ſed juſtus apparet</hi> is directly contrary, and that in the true ſenſe of it before ſpoken.</p>
               <p>You object, and in one of your Letters told me that as ſome Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians have their <hi>Noſtrum,</hi> this is my <hi>Veſtrum,</hi> that is, that I ſay thus, but not others. Our Divines ſay, Faith is the <hi>Condition,</hi> or the <hi>Inſtrument;</hi> but not the <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This I acknowledge, and Anſwer, that the Reaſon is apparent, becauſe our former Divines did apprehend that it is by the <hi>Law of Works</hi> that we are to be juſtified, and there being no Righteouſneſs but Chriſts which Anſwers that Law, it muſt be his alone that can juſtifie us: But this being a miſtake, the fundamental miſtake of our Divines formerly <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and <hi>Papiſt;</hi> and it being not by the <hi>Law,</hi> or according to the <hi>Law of Works,</hi> but by the Law of <hi>Grace,</hi> or according to the <hi>Goſpel</hi> that we are to be <hi>judged</hi> and <hi>juſtified,</hi> it is impoſſible that Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, which is a Righteouſneſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Law,</hi> ſhould be that Righteouſneſs that juſtifies us according to the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> It is impoſſible that Chriſts Righteouſneſs ſhould be that <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> which in oppoſition to Works does juſtifie us according to the Apoſtle, or that <hi>Righteouſneſs of God, which without the Law is manifeſted,</hi> ſeeing this is a Righteouſneſs <hi>with the Law,</hi> being perfectly conformable to it. And it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible (Logically impoſſible) <hi>but</hi> Faith (which is that which the Goſpel requires as the Condition of Life, inſtead of the perfect Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94667:15"/>of the Law) when performed and imputed for Righteouſneſs, <hi>ſhould</hi> be and muſt be that Righteouſneſs which is the Form or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Cauſe of our <hi>Evangelical</hi> Juſtification.</p>
               <p>I will now ſpeak to a Paſſage, that put me to many Thoughts in another Letter, in regard to our ſpeaking of Juſtification as <hi>paſſively</hi> taken. <hi>You ſeem</hi> (ſay you) <hi>to make Juſtification, Active and Paſſive two things. The former, Gods</hi> imputing; <hi>the latter, Faith</hi> imputed <hi>for Righteouſneſs. If they are different, you make two Juſtifications, which you condemn in me: If they are one, they muſt both have the ſame Form, or formal Cauſe. But Juſtification is Gods Act, and it is impoſſible Faith or any thing ſhould be the formal Cauſe of Gods Act, it may be the Condition, not formal Cauſe.</hi> As for this Paſſage, I did wonder to ſee you ſo much in earneſt, which may be objected againſt <hi>Chriſts</hi> being the <hi>meritorius Cauſe,</hi> as well againſt our <hi>Faith</hi> being the <hi>formal Cauſe,</hi> and againſt its being the <hi>Condition</hi> of our Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. What? Becauſe I am not for making a double Juſtification, (which are of two <hi>kinds</hi>) one by the <hi>Law,</hi> another by the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> do you think I may not therefore diſtinguiſh Juſtification into <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive,</hi> when we mean nothing elſe by it, but that Juſtification may be <hi>Actively</hi> and <hi>Paſſively taken?</hi> And as for the Metaphyſical Point, you are concern'd alike with me. It is the <hi>Will</hi> of God by giving us his Law of Grace, that when a Man believes he ſhall by that Law be Made, Accounted and Uſed as a righteous Perſon, and ſo be free from Puniſhment and Saved. Of this <hi>Will</hi> of God now <hi>ex parte Agentis,</hi> we muſt know there is nothing without him can be <hi>Cauſe</hi> or <hi>Condition.</hi> God is <hi>Actus purus.</hi> God acts only by his Eſſence, and his Eſſence is immutable; yet does that <hi>Will,</hi> which is one and the ſame, cauſe all Diverſity, and he that is immutable <hi>cauſe Mutations.</hi> And as that <hi>Act</hi> of his Will, (or <hi>Will,</hi> which is all one) is terminated on the Object, and <hi>recipitur in paſſo;</hi> it cauſeth its ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and is extrinſecally denominated by them. In theſe Effects there is an Order, and one thing the cauſe of another, according to that of <hi>Aquinas. Deus vult hoc propter hoc;</hi> tho' <hi>propter hoc,</hi> he does not <hi>velle hoc.</hi> Now, when in our Juſtification, which is Gods Act, the Will of God by his Law of Grace, does make that Change of <hi>State</hi> in a Believer, or of his <hi>Relation</hi> toward God, ſo as to have thereby a <hi>Right</hi> conferred to Pardon and Life, there are Cauſes of that <hi>Change</hi> and <hi>Right,</hi> which being new in the Object, <hi>Ex conno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione Objecti &amp; Effectus,</hi> denominate Gods Act.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is impoſſible</hi> (ſay you) <hi>that Faith or anything ſhould be the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Cauſe of Gods Act.</hi> Very good! that were abſurd indeed:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94667:16"/>But what is Gods Act here? His Act here is expreſt in the word <hi>[Imputing]</hi> and who thinks Faith the Form of that? Nothing in us can be the <hi>cauſe</hi> of Gods Act, it's true, but ſomething in us may be the Object upon which Gods Act is terminated; and that here is our Faith as he imputes it for Righteouſneſs; and this being the Effect of that Act <hi>in paſſo,</hi> this Faith ſo imputed, is the formal Cauſe of our Juſtification ſo effected.</p>
               <p>As for the Queſtion, Whether Juſtification <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive, Juſtificare</hi> and <hi>Juſtificari,</hi> be one or two Juſtifications, it is a nicer Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (I thought) than need be anſwered, but ſeeing it falls in (and muſt) I ſay. There is no diſtinction without a difference, and where things differ and are diverſe, their Form and Definition muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. Juſtification <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> therefore muſt have two <hi>Forms,</hi> but the <hi>Matter</hi> is the ſame. Faith in the <hi>Imputation</hi> of it, and in its being <hi>imputed</hi> to us for Righteouſneſs, is the ſame; So that <hi>formally</hi> they are two, <hi>materially,</hi> they are one and the ſame Juſtification.</p>
               <p>Well, Juſtification (to proceed upon what hath been ſaid) tho' Gods Act, yet <hi>paſſively</hi> taken, as other things, in the ſenſe ſhewn, muſt have its Cauſes. <hi>Sanctification</hi> is an Act of Gods Grace as well as <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and you will not deny our inherent Grace to be the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Sanctification</hi> for all that. But how? Not as <hi>Actively</hi> but <hi>Paſſively</hi> taken. As for the Cauſes then of <hi>Paſſive</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, Of the <hi>Efficient,</hi> the <hi>Final,</hi> the <hi>Meritorious,</hi> there is no diſpute, but of the <hi>Material</hi> and <hi>Formal</hi> there is; and it is fit to be conſidered. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath taught, that Chriſts Righteouſneſs is not only the <hi>Meritorious</hi> but <hi>Material</hi> Cauſe of our Juſtification: And you have cited Mr. <hi>Anthony Burgeſſe,</hi> holding Chriſts Active Obedience as well as Paſſive, to be the <hi>Matter,</hi> but denying that we are <hi>formally</hi> juſtified by it: Where he ſpeaks after <hi>Ameſius</hi> (I ſuppoſe) ſeeing it is upon the ſame Reaſon, that if it were ſo, we muſt be as <hi>righteous as Chriſt,</hi> which I have mentioned before, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s Objection againſt that Doctrine, and which by <hi>Ames</hi> his waving it, he acknowledges unanſwerable, when yet we know that Doctrine to have been the Common Proteſtants formerly, as <hi>Davenant</hi> before tells us; and ſome more weighty Divines than Mr. <hi>Burgeſſe,</hi> tells us yet thus much further, <hi>Mirum hic videri non debet Chriſti juſtitiam, non Meritoriae ſolum, ſed &amp; Materialis, immo &amp; formalis cauſae rationem habere, cum id fiat diverſimodè, nempe, qua, illa eſt propter quod, in quo, ſive ex quo, &amp; per quod juſtificamur.</hi> So the <hi>Leiden Divines.</hi> For my own part, I have in my Book taken
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94667:16"/>up with Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> upon truſting to his profounder Judgment, but I will now ſhew alſo my Opinion. The <hi>Meritorius</hi> Cauſe comes under the <hi>Efficient,</hi> and is the Efficient <hi>Protatarctick,</hi> or <hi>Impulſive</hi> Cauſe, according to my firſt <hi>Oxford</hi>-Learning, and the <hi>Efficient, Material, Formal</hi> and <hi>Final</hi> Cauſes being the different Species of <hi>Cauſe</hi> in general, I cannot but think they are to be <hi>ſo</hi> held in this Point of Juſtification. The <hi>Efficient</hi> Cauſe then, I ſay, is God; The <hi>Meritorius</hi> is Chriſts Righteouſneſs; The <hi>Material</hi> is not the ſame with that coming under the Efficient, but is, I count, our inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Grace, or Faith as infuſed in our Regeneration; The <hi>Formal</hi> then is the imputing this Faith or Grace inherent, (as the Evangelick Condition is performed by it) to us for Righteouſneſs, when being imperfect, otherwiſe it were none. Inherent Grace is the <hi>Matter,</hi> and the <hi>Form</hi> is brought into it by this <hi>Imputation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This I have before, though tranſiently, fuller explained, I think, and as for my giving way to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> I am ſenſible that he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding how nothing <hi>ab extra,</hi> not Chriſts Merits, is poſſible to move God, or be impulſive to any Act in him, who is uncapable of Mutation, did apprehend Chriſts Merits to fall under the ſame Cauſe as our Merits would if we had them, which is only a <hi>Diſpoſitio Recipientis</hi> according to him, and ſo the <hi>Material</hi> Cauſe, becauſe there can be no <hi>impulſive</hi> Cauſe in regard to God. But ſeeing our Divines do commonly, and the Holy Scripture ſpeak of God Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, Pardoning, Saving, and continually Bleſſing us for the ſake of Chriſt or his Merits (for all that there is nothing indeed <hi>ab extra.</hi> can move him) and this kind of ſpeaking is warranted by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick denomination of Gods <hi>Law,</hi> yea his <hi>Will,</hi> by meer <hi>Conno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of the various and new <hi>Effects</hi> it cauſes, it was I think but an over deep curioſity in this excellent Man, which turn'd him from the obvious and right Notion, as commonly received, that it is <hi>per modum Cauſae Efficientis Protatarcticae,</hi> when we ſay, <hi>Meritoriae,</hi> and not <hi>per modum Materialis,</hi> or <hi>Formalis,</hi> that Chriſts Righteouſneſs does conduce to our Juſtification.</p>
               <p>It is true, I will ſay again, that <hi>Ex parte Volentis,</hi> what Chriſt <hi>himſelf</hi> hath done for us, procures no new <hi>Act</hi> of Grace toward us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſimplicity of the Divine Nature is not capable of any: but <hi>Ex parte rei volitae,</hi> to ſay it procured no new <hi>Effects</hi> of his Grace for us, but only diſpoſes and qualifies us for the receiving thoſe Effects, is a mater ſo nice, ſo ſubtle, and out of the way, that if it were true it could not be taught, and is moſt likely to be untrue, both therefore, and becauſe it ſeems derogatory to Chriſts Satisfaction
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94667:17"/>and Merits, to his Sufferings and Obedience, which the Scripture ſpeaks of as a Price, as a Ranſom, a Purchaſe, not to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> us for, but to <hi>obtain</hi> for us, our Redemption, and conſequently thoſe other Effects of his Grace likewiſe, our Juſtification and Salvation.</p>
               <p>I have now no more to anſwer, and it is time for me to have done. Only I muſt ſumm up what I have here wrote as to the matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us. You and I (my dear Brother) agree in the main Doctrine of Juſtification by Faith, but have been differing in two Points about it, which you ſay are but little, but I ſay are very <hi>momentous</hi> Matters. The two Points are theſe. One is, Juſtification, I ſay, <hi>makes</hi> us juſt, and does not only <hi>ſentence</hi> us ſo: You ſay (or have ſaid) Juſtification is the <hi>accounting,</hi> but not <hi>making</hi> us juſt. The other Point is this, As Juſtification makes us righteous, I ſay, there is a Righteouſneſs within, Faith, or our Evangelical Righteouſneſs, which juſtifying us, muſt therefore be, and is the <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſtification: And this you receive not, or have very hardly received. I will ſpeak it more ſhort. Juſtification, I ſay, <hi>makes</hi> us righteous, and that righteouſneſs whereby we are <hi>made</hi> righteous is, and muſt be the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of it. Here are both Points wrapt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and you do, or have queſtioned both. I will offer you therefore one Argument (and that is <hi>Ad hominem</hi>) for your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction. You maintain Juſtification by Faith as our Evangelical Righteouſneſs as I do. Now if Juſtification do not <hi>make</hi> us righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, then muſt we be juſtified by that inherent Righteouſneſs, which is the Righteouſneſs only of Regeneration, there being with you no other. And then are you the ſtrongeſt Papiſt as to me, as ever writ, for here is a moſt convincing Book of yours, which is all al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Scripture, and yet maintains Juſtification by inherent Grace, and Faith, as the Papiſts do. Here then you can by no means ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate your ſelf from them, when I thus ſay, we are <hi>made righteous by Juſtification<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and by that Righteouſneſs only juſtified, do eſcape.</p>
               <p>As for the Conſequence now of theſe two Points, I think fit before I come to it, that it be firſt conſidered how theſe conſiſt, how neceſſary they are to, and indeed ſuſtain and infer one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For if Juſtification <hi>makes</hi> us juſt, then muſt there be a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſo <hi>made,</hi> that is the <hi>Form</hi> of our Juſtification: and the Righteouſneſs which is that <hi>Form,</hi> is the Righteouſneſs that <hi>conſtitutes us juſt,</hi> or juſtifies us. This being aſſerted, there are theſe two things then as the conſequence of theſe two Points appears, and has been ſhewn in this Letter. <hi>One</hi> is (for I muſt recal them) that whereas
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94667:17"/>our late <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who have been more wary, and come to ſee the Abſurdity of our former Divines, (who in oppoſition to the <hi>Papiſts</hi> making our inherent Grace the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, would put Chriſts Righteouſneſs in its room, ſo making the Righteouſneſs of another our <hi>formal</hi> Righteouſneſs) are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincedly brought off from their Opinion, they have been, and are ever ſince at a loſs, and muſt be, to pitch upon that which is indeed the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſtification: And when you (or I, or you and I together) have been ſo happy to have found out that Righteouſneſs (even <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God</hi>) which is this <hi>formal Cauſe,</hi> for them; Is this in earneſt with you but a little matter? What! And is the clearing the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of your and my way from the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which was the great difficulty lay upon you before, a little matter alſo? It was otherwiſe at your firſt writing to me, and it is an Archeive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment now worthy our mutual Letters. The other Conſequence is, That when the Proteſtants (I ſay, and have ſaid) and our Brethren are among themſelves at difference, ſo much about this Great Article, there is by this means ſome thing found out yet further, as may reconcile them, and that, as it were, (I ſay in my firſt Letter) by a <hi>Word.</hi> For if we can but tell any thing in ſuch ſhort Terms, as does Characterize, or is a Characteriſtical Note, to diſtinguiſh the Sound <hi>Proteſtant</hi> from the <hi>Unſound,</hi> then may the Sound preſently Unite and Drop the other, if they ſtill will be Abſurd. Now here is ſuch a Characteriſtical Note, and let the World that pleaſe know the ſame. Juſtification by <hi>Chriſts</hi> Righteouſneſs, and not our <hi>Own, per modum meriti,</hi> is Sound <hi>Proteſtantiſm:</hi> Juſtification by <hi>Chriſts</hi> Righteouſneſs and not our <hi>Own, formaliter,</hi> is fundamentally <hi>Antinomianiſm.</hi> This many of our Brethren having not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood ſo well as they ſhould hitherto, have been but wildred, and not found their way out to an Orthodox Coalition.</p>
               <p>Not that I ſay ſuch a Union (a Union in <hi>Doctrinals</hi>) is to be ſought in the preſent caſe of our Brethrens, many of whom have ſcarce <hi>thought</hi> of <hi>this Term [formal Cauſe]</hi> ſo far have they been from the uſe of it in this Point. The <hi>Form</hi> of a Thing is, <hi>illud per quod res eſt id quod eſt,</hi> and denominates the Thing. If we know not the <hi>Form</hi> of Juſtification, we know not what Juſtification is; and how then can we tell when we ſay any thing right about it? To be <hi>juſtified,</hi> hath a <hi>Form</hi> paſſively denominating a Man
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94667:18"/>
                  <hi>juſt,</hi> from ſome <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> according to all Divines, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand themſelves, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> or <hi>Papiſts:</hi> What that Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is, is the Queſtion. The Papiſts ſay one thing, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Proteſtants another. You and I come between them, and what it is we have ſhewn.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtian Righteouſneſs</hi> (ſays <hi>Luther,</hi> on <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6.) <hi>conſiſts in two things, Faith in the Heart, and Gods Imputation. Faith is indeed a formal Righteouſneſs, yet this Righteouſneſs is not enough, it is imperfect, wherefore the other part of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs muſt needs be added to finiſh the ſame, to wit, Gods Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> There are more the like words, from whence I have been thinking, ſince I wrote my Book, (See, <hi>Righteouſneſs of God.</hi> Pag. 10. and 20.) that it was happily ſuch a kind of Notion as ours, that <hi>Luther</hi> had in his firſt Thoughts ariſing from the Scripture, howſoever himſelf or others after him, came to run it up to that exorbitancy, as from an Acceptation of our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>inchoate Obedience</hi> (ſo long as it is ſincere) through the Merits of Chriſt, unto Life (inſtead of the Righteouſneſs of the Law) it is come, or came to the cloathing the <hi>Perſon</hi> with the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which is a Righteouſneſs according to the Law, Meritorious and Perfect; ſo that he does ſtand as <hi>juſt</hi> in the <hi>ſight of God,</hi> and (as in <hi>Chriſts Perſon</hi>) to be <hi>juſtified</hi> by the <hi>Law of Works,</hi> altho' the holy Prophet does tell us (<hi>Pſ.</hi> 143.2.) that <hi>in the ſight of God,</hi> and the holy Apoſtle (<hi>Gal.</hi> 3.11.) <hi>by the Law, ſhall no Fleſh living be juſtified.</hi> This Opinion therefore being ſo carried, as to ſubvert the Goſpel, we leave it.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your aſſured Friend, And loving Brother,</hi> John Humfrey.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:94667:18"/>
               <head>To Mr. <hi>Humfrey.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend and Dear Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THere hath paſſed many Letters, and there hath been long De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate between us about two Points; One is of <hi>Conſtitutive</hi> Juſtification, the other is of the <hi>Form</hi> or the <hi>formalis Cauſa</hi> of it. This Letter ſhall ſpeak of thoſe two Points, there being little or no Diſagreement in regard to others.</p>
               <p>I will begin with the laſt, as having coſt more pains in regard to the many Arguments and Anſwers bandied and toſſed to and fro, concerning it. The reſult of all which, is contained, and will be found in what follows.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We are fully agreed, as to the Nature of Juſtification, only differ about applying this Term <hi>[Formal Cauſe]</hi> as to the Point.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You grant that <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Goſpel-righteouſneſs</hi> is not accounted by other Divines that are Proteſtants, to be the <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> hereof; ſo that this is (I have ſaid) a <hi>Veſtrum,</hi> as ſome Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians have their <hi>Noſtrum,</hi> and therefore requires ſo much more caution.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You apply it to Juſtification <hi>Paſſive,</hi> and make our Faith to be only the <hi>Form</hi> of Juſtification <hi>paſſively</hi> taken, and aſſign another <hi>Form</hi> or formal Cauſe to Juſtification <hi>Active;</hi> for you ſay, <hi>[Gods making or conſtituting us juſt, by the imputation of Faith to us for Righteouſneſs, is Juſtification Active; Our being made juſt or conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted righteous by that imputation, is Juſtification Paſſive:]</hi> Which you further explain thus, <hi>Juſtification may be taken either</hi> Subjectivè, <hi>as in God; ſo it is his gracious condeſcention to accept our Faith or imperfect Obedience, unto Pardon and Life: Or</hi> Terminativè, <hi>as in us; and ſo it is nothing elſe but this Faith imputed for Righteouſneſs, as ſo imputed, and this is the</hi> Cauſa formalis <hi>of our paſſive Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Againſt this I argue thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. (a) Hereby you make two Juſtifications, or Juſtification <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> to be two different Things, becauſe they have two <hi>Forms;</hi> one Gods <hi>imputing,</hi> or accepting Faith <hi>for Righteouſneſs;</hi> the other Faith <hi>imputed,</hi> or ſo accepted for Righteouſneſs: Of which more anon.</p>
               <p rend="small">(a) It is true, and if you hold there, and when you cite me, as ſaying Faith is the formal Cauſe of our Juſtification, you will ſupply what you find here, that I mean Faith only, as ſo <hi>imputed;</hi> 
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:94667:19"/>and alſo that I underſtand Juſtification <hi>paſſively</hi> taken, I ſhall have little to anſwer to all that follows, for Juſtification <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> have indeed two <hi>Forms,</hi> and muſt have, or elſe they could not be <hi>diſtinguiſhed,</hi> and it is your fundamental, if not only Miſtake, that you have a belief to the contrary.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Juſtification is Gods <hi>Act,</hi> but nothing in us can be the <hi>Cauſa formalis</hi> of Gods Act. To this you return ſeveral Anſwers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Sanctification is Gods Act as well as Juſtification: But I hope you doubt not to ſay our inherent Grace is the formal Cauſe of our Sanctification. But how? Not as actively, but paſſively taken. The ſame is to be ſaid of the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> God is the Efficient; Grace infuſed the Material; the Act of infuſing or beſtowing the (b) Formal.</p>
               <p rend="small">(b) Right: And if the <hi>infuſion</hi> or <hi>beſtowing</hi> of Grace or Holi-Holineſs on a Man, be the Form of Gods <hi>Sanctifying Act,</hi> then muſt this Grace or Holineſs, <hi>infuſed</hi> or <hi>beſtowed,</hi> be the Form of his <hi>Sanctified State. Vocabulum formae uſurpari ſolet non modo de formis ſubſtantialibus quae dant eſſe ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter, ſed de Accidentalibus quae dant Eſſe tale. Hoc ſenſu dicimus. Doctrinam eſſe illam formam per quam homo Doctus, juſtitiam per quam Juſtus, efficitur.</hi> I hope you can truſt <hi>Davenant,</hi> thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> me for this Information. <hi>Dav. De. Juſ. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al. c.</hi> 27.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You anſwer further, thus, <hi>God is</hi> Actus purus, <hi>and nothing is the Cauſe or Condition of his Will,</hi> Ex parte Agentis: <hi>but as Gods Acts are denominated in regard of the effects upon us, theſe Effects muſt have their formal Cauſe, or elſe be nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The formal Cauſe is Gods (c) Imputation.</p>
               <p rend="small">(c) Right again: The <hi>Imputation</hi> of our Faith for Righteouſneſs is the Form of Gods <hi>Juſtifying Act,</hi> and Faith <hi>imputed</hi> for Righteouſneſs is therefore the Form of our <hi>juſtified State.</hi> It is ſtrange that the <hi>Intus exiſtens</hi> ſhould keep out ſuch open Evidence.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Another Anſwer you give is this; <hi>It is impoſſible</hi> (ſay you) <hi>that Faith or any thing in us ſhould be the Cauſe of Gods Act. Very good; That were abſurd indeed! — Nothing in us can be the Cauſe of Gods Act. True: but ſomething in us may be the Object, about which Gods Act is converſant, and that here is Faith as he imputes it for Righteouſneſs, and this being the effect of that Act</hi> in paſſo, <hi>this Faith ſo imputed, I ſay, is the formal Cauſe of our Juſtification ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Object of Gods Act is Faith or the Believer: The Effect of it in us, Juſtification. Imputation is the formal Cauſe, as has been<note n="(d)" place="margin">And already ſatisfied.</note> already ſaid.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:94667:19"/>
               <p n="5">5. The Arguments which you produce for the proof of it, I have gathered together out of the ſeveral places of their diſperſion, and they are theſe:</p>
               <p>Argu. 1. <hi>All our Divines,</hi> both <hi>Proteſtant and Papiſt, do agree upon it that that Righteouſneſs whatever it be that denominates and makes us righteous in Gods ſight, is and muſt be the Form or formal Cauſe of Juſtification. And certainly theſe Divines underſtood this Metaphyſical Term, better than you or I. And when wee uſe it in their Senſe, and no otherwiſe, there can be no fear. But neither Regeneration, nor Chriſts Righteouſneſs, nor Pardon is that which juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies us</hi> per modum cauſae formalis; <hi>and therefore it muſt be</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">As <hi>imputed for Righteouſneſs,</hi> that is with <hi>Luther,</hi> Faith and Gods Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion together; not Faith of its ſelf.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith. Not Chriſts Righteouſneſs, for that is the meritorious Cauſe; Not Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Grace, for that muſt precede Juſtification, not Pardon, for that comes after it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if Juſtification has any formal Cauſe (which it muſt have, or it is nothing, for</hi> forma dat eſſe) <hi>it muſt be one of theſe or ſomething elſe. What is that? Why the Righteouſneſs of God, revealed in the Goſpel, as that Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs alone which juſtifies the Believer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is ſomething elſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Gods (f) Imputation.</p>
               <p rend="small">(f) To this and the former Anſwer, I ſay that is true, it is <hi>Imputation,</hi> as to <hi>Active</hi> Juſtification, or as to God <hi>juſtifying</hi> us: Therefore ſomething <hi>imputed</hi> muſt be the formal Cauſe of the Perſons being <hi>Justified:</hi> And what is that? Chriſts Righteouſneſs, or the Righteouſneſs of Faith? We agree, as to the laſt.</p>
               <p>Argu. 2. <hi>As</hi> Adam <hi>if he had perfectly obey'd, his Obedience had been his formal Righteouſneſs, in regard to the Law: ſo is this ours in regard to the Goſpel.</hi> Right. of God. p. 20. So again, <hi>Works were the formal Righteouſneſt of Juſtification by the Law: Therefore Faith is the formal Righteouſneſs of Juſtification by the Goſpel.</hi> Right. of God. p. 20. Again preſently after, <hi>Two things go to this formal Righteouſneſs, Faith and the Imputation of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To theſe I anſwer in order.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To the firſt and ſecond. 1. It's without doubt that <hi>Adams</hi> Obedience was (g) formal Righteouſneſs, (and ſo Faith is now) but ſo it might be and yet not be the Form of his Juſtification, as I at firſt ſaid. The formal Cauſe of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Juſtification was Gods owning, accounting, or judging him righteous, upon the account of his perfect Obedience, as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94667:20"/>Gods Imputation of Faith for Righteouſneſs, is the Formal Cauſe of our Juſtification.</p>
               <p rend="small">(g) To be our <hi>formal Righteouſneſs,</hi> and to be the <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and to be the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> that is the <hi>Form</hi> of our Juſtification is all one (ſo ſpoken and underſtood by <hi>Divines.</hi>) Gods accounting <hi>Adam</hi> perfectly righteous was <hi>Active</hi> Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Adam</hi>'s being righteous and ſo accounted was Juſtification <hi>Paſſive;</hi> and Gods <hi>imputing</hi> our Faith for Righteouſneſs, and our Faith <hi>imputed</hi> is the ſame likewiſe. Here is nothing but what is prevented already.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I deny the Conſequence in the firſt Aſſertion, That if <hi>Adam</hi>'s Law-obedience was his formal Righteouſneſs, then our Goſpel-Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is our formal Righteouſneſs, becauſe though Faith comes in the room of Law-Works in ſome reſpects, yet not in all; for it doth not (h) merit the reward, as Law-Works would have done.</p>
               <p rend="small">(h) Whether the reward be of Grace or Merit, that is nothing to the purpoſe, ſo long as Faith is the Condition of the Covenant of Grace, as perfect Obedience was of the Covenant of Works. The Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Evangelick Condition, is the formal Righteouſneſs of the one; The Performance of the Legal was the formal Righteouſneſs of the other. The formality lies in the <hi>Condition performed,</hi> not in the <hi>Meritoriouſneſs,</hi> or <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meritoriouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Performance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To the third, If Faith and Imputation (i) both go to this formal Righteouſneſs, then Faith alone is not the Form of it.</p>
               <p rend="small">(i) By this you ſee that we are agreed: I ſay, and you ſay, that Faith is the <hi>Matter</hi> (as will appear more hereafter) and Imputation that which brings the <hi>Form</hi> into the <hi>Matter;</hi> ſo that it is not Faith alone, but Faith as <hi>imputed for Righteouſneſs</hi> is the formal Cauſe of Juſtification.</p>
               <p>Argu. 3. <hi>If Juſtification has a Form, and that Form muſt be ſome Righteouſneſs,</hi> [Juſtificationis formam juſticia conſtare certum eſt] <hi>What Righteouſneſs is that? It is Gods counting or judging us Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, ſay you. But is this an Anſwer to the Queſtion,</hi> What Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is it whereby we are juſtified? <hi>When I ask, What Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs it is whereby we are juſtified, or what Righteouſneſs that is, which is the Form of Juſtification; I ask, What Righteouſneſs that is whereby, or wherewith, or by reaſon of which, God accounts or judges us righteous? It is not regenerating Grace infuſed, but regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating Grace imputed, that is, Faith imputed for Righteouſneſs. That which makes a Man righteous in Gods ſight, according to the Goſpel, is that which juſtifies us, ſo as to be the</hi> Cauſa formalis <hi>of it</hi> [Per formalem Juſtificationis cauſam juſti conſtituimur]: <hi>What then is that Righteouſneſs which makes or conſtitutes us juſt? It is Gods imputing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94667:20"/>this Faith before infuſed, that makes us righteous, and conſequently is the</hi> Cauſa formalis <hi>of our Juſtification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I ſay the <hi>Cauſa formalis</hi> of Juſtification is Gods counting or judging us righteous, ſo ſay you too. Your Words are theſe, <hi>Gods judging us righteous upon believing, is the</hi> (k) <hi>Form.</hi>
               </p>
               <p rend="small">(k) The Form of a thing does conſtitute and denominate the thing. If Gods judging us righteous, or imputing our Faith for Righteouſneſs does actually make, and denominate God our <hi>Juſtifier;</hi> then muſt our being judged righteous, and our Faith imputed for Righteouſneſs, make and paſſively denominate us <hi>juſtified.</hi> There is the ſame <hi>Efficient</hi> and <hi>Material</hi> Cauſe in both, but the <hi>Form</hi> double.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. I anſwer directly. The Righteouſneſs whereby we are juſtified, as the meritorious Cauſe of our Juſtification, is the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt: The Righteouſneſs of Faith the <hi>material</hi> Cauſe: But the <hi>formal</hi> is (l) Gods judging us righteous, as you agree.</p>
               <p rend="small">(l) Here you are plainly gone. I ask what Righteouſneſs that is, and you Anſwer <hi>Gods judging:</hi> There is ſome Righteouſneſs, as all our Divines agree, that does make and denominate us righteous, and that which ſo makes and denominates us, according to the Goſpel, is that which juſtifies us. When you don't tell this, you are gone. I ſay, (as I have ſaid) It is true that Gods judging, or imputing ſomething to us for Righteouſneſs, is the Form of Gods juſtifying <hi>Act,</hi> but that ſomething that is judged and imputed to us for our Righteouſneſs, is the Form of our juſtified <hi>State</hi> or Condition.</p>
               <p>Argu. 4. <hi>Divines do generally fix it upon ſome Righteouſneſs. The Righteouſneſs of Inherent Grace, ſay the Papiſts: The Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, ſaith</hi> Davenant, <hi>and the Proteſtants generally: The Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Pardon, ſaith Mr.</hi> Wotton.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I do not pretend to compare my ſelf in the leaſt with thoſe Learned Men, who maintain any of the former Particulars, to be the formal Cauſe of Juſtification; but I am willing to ſuſpect my own Judgment rather than theirs. Perhaps it may be my (m) Ignorance in the proper Notion of a formal Cauſe, that hinders me from aſſenting to them. And yet,</p>
               <p rend="small">(m) The Form of a thing (you know) is that whereby the thing is that which it is; that which differences the thing, defines, denominates it. A Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition is made of a <hi>Genus &amp; Differentia,</hi> call'd by others the <hi>Form</hi> (a <hi>Genus</hi> and a <hi>Form</hi>) to wit, that which ſpecifies and differences the thing from others, that which makes the <hi>Ens unum. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num is indiviſum in ſe, &amp; diviſum ah aliis:</hi> The Form makes the thing <hi>diviſum ab omnibus aliis,</hi> and whatſoever dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from another, muſt have its Form (its Deffinition) that makes it differ, or elſe it is nothing. It is not for want of Knowledge of this, but the want of Conſideration of it, makes you here diſagree with me, for ſo long as there is no Diſtinction without a <hi>Difference,</hi> and Juſtification is thus diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive,</hi> they muſt have their <hi>different</hi> Forms, and if that be acknowledged, our Conteſt is at an end.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:94667:21"/>
               <p n="2">2. You (n) agree with me, that it is Gods Imputation or judging us Righteous: But yet that I may yield to you as far as I can, I add,</p>
               <p rend="small">(n) How I agree with you it is manifeſt, as to juſtification <hi>Active,</hi> and that you may agree with me, as to Juſtification <hi>Paſſive,</hi> you ſay enough in that which follows.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That upon the (o) ſame ground that any of theſe may be ſaid to be the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of Juſtification, I ſee not but that the Righteouſneſs of Faith, or the Righteouſneſs of God by Faith, may be allowed to be the formal Cauſe of it. If it be proper in any of the other Caſes or Inſtances, for ought that I know it is proper alſo in this. If it be proper to call Chriſts Righteouſneſs the formal Cauſe, or Pardon the formal Cauſe of Juſtification, it is proper, I think, to call Faith ſo too. There is the ſame Reaſon for one as for the other in my apprehenſion.</p>
               <p rend="small">(o) As for what you yield here to me, it is but honeſt, and tho' condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, no more than what cann't be denyed. If we uſe the Terms of other Divines, we muſt uſe them in their ſenſe, or we cannot elſe be in the right. I thank you for your ſincerity in this.</p>
               <p>Argu. 5. But the moſt plauſible Argument of all (becauſe it is Scriptural) you have omitted, which is, That the Scripture ſaith expreſly, (p) <hi>We are are juſti-fied by Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p rend="small">(p) This is what is to be underſtood in my Book all over, when I ſay, that tho' the <hi>Id propter quod,</hi> be Chriſts Righteouſneſs, the <hi>Id per quod,</hi> we are juſtified, is Faith, and Faith therefore, as imputed for Righteouſaeſs, is the formal Cauſe of our Juſtification.</p>
               <p>Here then we muſt conſider, What intereſt Faith has in our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. This I have ſaid in my Book is as the (q) Condition, Way or Means, whereby we come to have an intereſt in this Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p rend="small">(q) That Faith, Repentance and New Obedience are the Condition and Way of Life, as to the Exerciſe and Practice of them, does not hinder but that performed and imputed by God for Righteouſneſs, they become the <hi>Form</hi> its ſelf of our Juſtification.</p>
               <p>You ſay, As the <hi>formal Cauſe,</hi> but at laſt upon mature delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, you make it to be the <hi>material Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>Imputation</hi> the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94667:21"/>
                  <hi>formal,</hi> and ſo at laſt you ſeem to <hi>(r)</hi> give up the Cauſe you are contending for, your words being theſe, <hi>The Efficient Cauſe is God: The Meritorious Chriſts Righteouſneſs: The Material is not the ſame with that coming under the Efficient, but is, I count, our inherent Grace, or Faith infuſed in our Regeneration: The formal then is the imputing this Faith or Grace inherent, (as the Evangelick Condition performed by it) to us for Righteouſneſs, when being imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, otherwiſe it were none. Inherent Grace is the Matter, and the Form is brought in by this Imputation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p rend="small">(ſ) This is not well obſerved, that when I ſet my <hi>Cauſe</hi> in its true Light, and evince the truth of it ſo to your ſelf, that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but aſſent to it, you ſhould count that I give you my <hi>Cauſe,</hi> when I give you my <hi>Light,</hi> and when the Cauſe which I and you intend and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend is the ſame in this particular altogether. And why do you contend? Do not you know that in ſuch Colliſions that are only for Light, whenever there is ſtruck one Spark that does take, the work is done? for what is but rightly ſaid in one place, is to regulate all that is ſaid beſides otherwhere, when the Reader deals ingenuouſly with him he Reads.</p>
               <p>But then to (ſ) bring your ſelf off, you make it to be the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Cauſe</hi> only of Juſtification <hi>Active,</hi> and Faith to be the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of Juſtification <hi>Paſſive;</hi> and ſo you make two <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications</hi> diſtinct from each other, becauſe they have different <hi>Forms.</hi> So that all the Controverſie between us now, is redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to this one ſingle Point, whether there be two Juſtifications diſtinct from each other: For if Faith be the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> only of Juſtification <hi>Paſſive,</hi> and there be no ſuch thing as Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation <hi>Paſſive</hi> diſtinct from Juſtification <hi>Active,</hi> then Faith is caſhier'd and put out of its Office of being <hi>Cauſa formalis</hi> of Juſtification.</p>
               <p rend="small">(ſ) It is not to bring my ſelf off, but to keep the truth on foot, that I diſtinguiſh, as other Divines do. Who knows not that <hi>Juſtificare &amp; Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari</hi> are diſtinguiſhed, or that Juſtification is <hi>actively</hi> and <hi>paſſively</hi> taken? Alas! that you ſhould not conſider, that all the Diſputes of our Divines, Whether we be <hi>juſtified by Faith</hi> or <hi>Works,</hi> are and can be about Juſtification, no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe but as <hi>paſſively</hi> taken. As for the Queſtion, Whether Juſtification <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> be one or two; I have given a brief determination in this ſecond Letter as now printed (<hi>p.</hi> 28.) and did not do ſo in my Curſory Letter, becauſe I was indeed puzzled with it at firſt ſtarting, and could not at preſent tell what well to ſay to it. It is very true and judiciouſly declared here by you, that upon this (one would have thought) but nice thing, does depend all our difference; ſo that if Juſtification <hi>Paſſive</hi> have a diſtinct Form from Juſtification <hi>Active,</hi> then my all you ſay be true (as it is) of the <hi>One,</hi> and what I ſay to be true too of the <hi>Other.</hi> Now whether they have two Forms or no, ſeeing you and I were at preſent in doubt, and came very ſtrangely to be 
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94667:22"/>reſolved on a contrary Judgment, let us appeal to one that can tell us. <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) <hi>taken actively, as the Act of the Juſtifier, hath one Form: Juſtification paſſively taken, for the State of the Juſtified, hath another Form: And each of theſe are ſubdivided into many Acts and many Effects, which have each their Form.</hi> End of Contro. p. 263. This was the reaſon of the variation in what I writ.</p>
               <p>When I firſt propounded this Objection, and thereby diſcovered this Conſequence, you wrote to me thus; <hi>This diſtinction is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of a Subject into its Adjuncts, where the Form I apprehend to be the ſame, only applyed diverſly, as the Subject is actively or paſſively taken.</hi> But in your very next Letter, you revoke this, and ſay, <hi>That upon further conſideration, Juſtification Active and Paſſive are two Things in earneſt, and have two Forms.</hi> Seeing therefore this is that you ſtick to, I will try my skill to drive you out of this hold.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How (t) can Faith be the <hi>material</hi> Cauſe of one, and the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal</hi> of the other?</p>
               <p rend="small">(t) Very well: Faith as <hi>infuſed</hi> and a part of our Regeneration is the <hi>Matter</hi> (you agree to this.) Faith <hi>imputed</hi> for Righteouſneſs is the <hi>Form</hi> (I ſay) of our <hi>Paſſive</hi> Juſtification.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What (u) is the <hi>Efficient</hi> and <hi>Material</hi> Cauſe of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Paſſive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p rend="small">(u) The <hi>Efficient</hi> and <hi>Material</hi> Cauſe is the ſame in Juſtification <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> (I ſay) both, but the Form is diverſe, and muſt be ſo long as they differ from one another.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You (x) are certainly in the right when you make Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> to be but a diſtribution of a <hi>Subject,</hi> into its <hi>Adjuncts,</hi> and that they have the ſame Form; Therefore the Subject is the ſame, only diverſified by its different reſpects to its Agent and Object.</p>
               <p rend="small">(x) You are certainly in the wrong, in your underſtanding this thus. In a diſtribution of a Subject into its Adjuncts, the Subject is one, and hath one Form, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nius rei unica forma,</hi> and the Adjuncts partake of that Form, but their own Forms are diverſe, and muſt be as that by which they differ from one another. I am ſorry here I gave you occaſion to be confirm'd in your miſtake. But this good ſhall come of it, I will ſhew my Reaſon why I admit of two Juſtifications, <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive,</hi> and not two by the <hi>Law</hi> and by the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> Juſtification by the Law and by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, is a diſtribution of a <hi>Genus</hi> into its <hi>Species:</hi> But Juſtification <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive,</hi> is a diſtribution of a <hi>Subject</hi> into its <hi>Adjuncts</hi> only. When I can admit but of one <hi>kind</hi> of Juſtification only that is by the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> I may allow <hi>that</hi> to have diverſe Conſiderations.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:94667:22"/>
               <p n="4">4. When (y) I ſay God juſtifies <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> is juſtified of God, can any one be ſo void of ſenſe as to ſay, theſe are two Things? Is not the Act the ſame, tho' the Agent and Object be different? When I ſay the Sun enlightens the Air, and the Air is enlightned by the Sun, is not the enlightning the ſame, in both? The Propoſitions indeed are diſtinct in a <hi>Grammatical</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, but they are the ſame in a <hi>Phyſical</hi> Senſe. For,</p>
               <p rend="small">(y) When you ſay God juſtifies <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> is juſtified of God, here is a <hi>Juſtificare</hi> and a <hi>Juſtificari,</hi> that is, Juſtification <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive,</hi> and they muſt have two Forms; But ſeeing the <hi>Matter</hi> is the ſame (wherein you and I agree) they are <hi>formally two,</hi> but <hi>materially one</hi> and the ſame Juſtification.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Juſtification (z) is only of a Perſon: The Perſon to whom this Act of God is applyed is the Subject or Object of Gods Act about whom it is converſant. Juſtification cannot poſſibly be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, but as referring to ſome Perſon: and therefore there cannot be two Juſtifications.</p>
               <p rend="small">(z) The Subject, the Efficient, the Material Cauſe, are the ſame; but the Form different in <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> Juſtification. I pray turn to my Determination, at firſt I had not, then thought enough, and I did not think it ſo neceſſary, as now you make it, to determine this in my Curſory Letters, which you muſt forgive. You ſee then Brother, where the deficiency of <hi>Senſe</hi> does lye, which, ſeeing you have been able to ſay ſo much for, and have ſo much preſumption for, may be excuſed even with ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, though you have been miſtaken in it.</p>
               <p>There is one thing in the forgoing Diſcourſe, that perhaps will need a little farther Explication, and that is, where Faith is ſaid to be the<note n="(†)" place="margin">It is worth our Obſervation that in this Notion that our <hi>Faith</hi> or incho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Grace is the <hi>Materal,</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation</hi> the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, you and I ſhould both in our Letters <hi>coincidere,</hi> without any <hi>Item</hi> one from another.</note> material Cauſe of our Juſtification. Thoſe Terms in Matters of Morality, are ſubject to much uncertainty (as appears by the Learned in aſſigning the <hi>Material</hi> and <hi>formal</hi> Cauſes of Juſtification. I apprehend it thus. When Faith is ſaid to be imputed for Righteouſneſs, here Imputing is the Act, and Faith the Object. Now we agree that this Act of Imputing is the Form, and this Act falling upon this Object is the Form falling on the Matter (as you expreſs it very well) or introduced into it. The Act applyed to the Object, is the Form introduced
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94667:23"/>into the Matter. For why may not the Act and Object in <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> correſpond, or be the ſame with the Form and Matter in <hi>Naturality?</hi> I know ſome make the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to be the <hi>Material</hi> Cauſe of Juſtification, but againſt that Aſſertion I have this Argument. The <hi>Meritorious</hi> cannot be the <hi>Material:</hi> But Chriſts Righteouſneſs is the <hi>Meritorious</hi> Cauſe (none can deny that: Therefore it cannot be the <hi>Material.</hi> The <hi>Major</hi> I prove thus; The ſame thing cannot be both an <hi>External</hi> and <hi>Internal</hi> Cauſe. But the <hi>Meritorious</hi> is an <hi>External</hi> Cauſe (for it belongs to the <hi>Efficient,</hi> as you have alſo obſerved); the <hi>Material</hi> is an <hi>Internal</hi> Cauſe. Therefore the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt (which is certainly the <hi>Meritorious</hi>) cannot alſo be the <hi>Material.</hi> And this Argument will alſo hold againſt its being the <hi>Formal</hi> Cauſe; Mr. <hi>Banter</hi> ſeems to make Faith to be the <hi>Material</hi> Cauſe. <hi>End of Cont.</hi> p. 250.</p>
               <p>This I have long inclined unto, which may be illuſtrated thus: When a Malefactor is Arraigned and Tryed, the Law is the <hi>Efficient</hi> Cauſe of his Acquittal, or Condemnation; the Sentence pronounced by the Judge is the <hi>Formal;</hi> Matter of Fact or what hath appeared upon Tryal, is the <hi>Material.</hi> So here, Gods judging us righteous according to the Law of the Goſpel is the <hi>formal</hi> Cauſe of our Juſtification; and our Goſpel-righteouſneſs or Faith (which is as it were Matter of Fact) ſeems to be the <hi>Material.</hi> But, as I ſaid, there is no certainty in affixing or appropriating theſe <hi>Logioal</hi> Term in <hi>Morality,</hi> at leaſt in all Caſes, and therefore for my part I will contend with no Body about them.</p>
               <p>I will add but one word more about this point. <hi>Juſtification</hi> is Gods judging us righteous, (there's the <hi>Form</hi>) upon believing (there's the <hi>Matter</hi> or Condition): Or judging us to have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Condition of the Covenant of Grace or Goſpel-Law, ſo that we are thereby <hi>Recti in curia,</hi> innocent or guiltleſs in the eye of the Law (which is making us righteous judicially) and then dealing with us as ſuch, by acquitting us from legal Guilt (as Mr. <hi>Gilbert</hi> expreſſes it) or the Curſe of the Law, and giving us right to Life.</p>
               <p>This hath been a tedious Point, the other of Juſtification <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutive,</hi> will be of quicker diſpatch; yet ſince this Point alſo hath been much argued <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> by us, whereby I have gained clearer Apprehenſions of ſome things about it, than I had before; I will firſt gather up your Senſe which you have expreſſed [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>]
<pb facs="tcp:94667:23"/>in ſundry parcells, and then give you my Thoughts, which have been the reſult of the Debate between us.</p>
               <p>For the ſenſe of this <hi>Conſtitutive</hi> Juſtification, which you have expreſt in ſeveral Letters, upon the beſt conſideration I could take, I have reduced the Matter to theſe Particulars following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. You diſtinguiſh between making juſt by Sanctification and by Juſtification. <hi>There is a making us juſt</hi> (you ſay) <hi>which is Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; and that being imperfect and inſufficient to ſave us, there is the making us juſt alſo by Juſtification, which is, the accepting that imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Righteouſneſs of ours, through Chriſt for Righteouſneſs, to give us Right to Impunity and Glory.</hi> This doth fully and clearly diſtinguiſh your Opinion from the Papiſts, who make Juſtification to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but giving us inherent Righteouſueſs, and that is meerly by <hi>Infuſion,</hi> whereas this is by <hi>Imputation,</hi> as you obſerve well. For theſe Words do contain the cleareſt Account or Deſcription of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification <hi>Conſtitutive,</hi> that I have ever yet met with.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Conſtituting us juſt does in order of Nature go before Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting or Uſing us as juſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Conſtitutive Juſtification conſiſts in three Things, Making us juſt, Accounting us juſt, and Uſing us as juſt. Theſe are the three parts of Conſtitutive Juſtification, which though one preceds the other in order of Nature, as Parts, yet as they all three make one whole, they muſt in order of Time conſiſt together. And therefore more fully thus. Juſtification is a judicial Act, and that by the Law of Grace. God by that Law, and the Act of that Law, Makes, Pronounces, and by pronouncing makes the Believer a righteous Perſon, and being ſo made, accounts him ſo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Our Righteouſneſs wrought in us by Vocation, Regeneration or Sanctification, is the ſame Righteouſneſs materially, but not formally with this Righteouſneſs of Juſtification; for if a Man were the moſt righteous Perſon upon Earth, there was no reward due to it, and it were not Righteouſneſs in Gods ſight without the Law of Grace, and Juſtification by it. But when by that Law God imputes it, declares, pronounces it to be ſuch, or the Man who has it to be righteous, then does that Righteouſneſs by vertue of that Law, Declaration, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, give him a Right to Impunity and Salvation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>The beſtowing Faith upon us, which is our Goſpel righteouſneſs, is one thing, and the accounting us juſt upon believing is another.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>This is your Senſe, and I ſhall now give you my Thoughts, which have been the reſult of this Debate between us. I grant,</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:94667:24"/>
               <p n="1">1. That we muſt be <hi>made</hi> righteous before we can be <hi>counted</hi> or <hi>declared</hi> ſo; or rather that Gods counting or judging us righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous according to Goſpel-Law, is his making righteous <hi>Judically,</hi> that is, making guiltleſs or innocent in the Eye of Goſpel-Law; and you expreſs your ſelf to the ſame purpoſe alſo, <hi>God pronounces, and by pronouncing makes the Believer righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Righteouſneſs of <hi>Juſtification</hi> is one thing, and the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of <hi>Sanctification</hi> another: For one is Grace <hi>Real,</hi> and the other but <hi>Relative</hi> in reference to the Law of the Goſpel, that we are conformable to it: One of the <hi>Perſon,</hi> the other of the <hi>State:</hi> One <hi>Phyſical</hi> by <hi>Infuſion,</hi> or beſtowing a Principle of Grace or Holineſs upon us, the other <hi>Judical,</hi> by Sentence, firſt of the Law, ſecondly of the Judge applying the Law to a particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For in Juſtification God may be conſidered,
<list>
                     <item>1. As a <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver,</hi> and ſo he Enacts that Law, that Faith ſhall be accounted for Goſpel-Righteouſneſs:</item>
                     <item>2. As a <hi>Judge,</hi> applying that Law to a Believer, and ſo he judges him to be Evangeiically Righteous (which is making him ſo <hi>Judicially</hi>) or imputing his Faith for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. This makes the difference between the Popiſh Doctrine of Juſtification and ours to be very plain. They make it to conſiſt in the <hi>Infuſion</hi> of Real inherent Grace; We make it to conſiſt in the <hi>Imputation</hi> of Faith, or that Grace infuſed, for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or a Conformity to the Goſpel-Law, which is but Relative Grace, and ſo does conſiſt in ſomething <hi>without us;</hi> whereas theirs doth conſiſt in ſomething <hi>within.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that, upon the matter you and I are agreed in this Particular, as to the Thing, only I confeſs, I cannot approve of the Term <hi>[Conſtitutive Juſtification]</hi> as oppoſed to, and diſtinct from <hi>Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> and <hi>Executive.</hi> True the Words of the Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſhall be conſtituted righteous,</hi> ſound that way: But certainly the Righteouſneſs there ſpoken of, or that <hi>[being made righteous]</hi> there muſt be underſtood in the full Latitude, ſo as to include the whole of Chriſts Performance, in order to our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That by the Obedience and Merit of his Sufferings he obtained a Covenant of Grace, whereby Faith is counted for Righteouſneſs.</item>
                     <item>2. That all the Elect ſhould be judged by God to be righteous in a Goſpel Senſe.</item>
                  </list> And ſo, <hi>By the obedience of one many are made righteous.</hi> So that this Righteouſneſs does include both <hi>Conſtitutive</hi> and <hi>Sentential</hi> Juſtification, and therefore not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94667:24"/>to be appropriated to one of them diſtinct from the other.</p>
               <p>The two Points at firſt mentioned being now ſpoken to, there remains no more, but that I may reſt for hereafter and ever;</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Affectionate Friend,</hi> Samuel Clark.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To Mr. <hi>Clark.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Worthy and Dear Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IT being time to give you reſt, I have choſe rather to write my Notes upon what I differ from you in, than to ſend them, to make you more work.</p>
               <p>Our Velitations have been on two Points; One whether Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication does <hi>conſtitute</hi> us juſt as well as <hi>accoun</hi> us ſo? The other about the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of it. For the former, which you have laſt treated, you was at firſt more at diſtance, and came nearer ſtill in your Letters till at laſt you are brought to perfect Agreement <hi>de re,</hi> only <hi>de nomine,</hi> the word <hi>[Conſtitutive]</hi> you yet boggle at, and it is no matter for that. <hi>Conſtitutive</hi> Juſtification is <hi>Juſtificatio Juris; Sentential, Judicis,</hi> at the great day. When a Man is a True Believer the Goſpel-Law does give him Right to Pardon and Life. This Right goes before the actual Pardon, and this. Right is a Righteouſneſs that makes him righteous; and being ſo <hi>Made,</hi> he is ſo <hi>Accounted</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſed;</hi> which are three parts of <hi>One Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutive</hi> Juſtification. In your Denyal at firſt that Juſtification <hi>makes</hi> us Righteous, you forgot your own Book, where are theſe words: <hi>As condemning the righteous is taking away his righteouſneſs</hi> (Iſ. 5.23.) <hi>So juſtifying the righteous muſt be a conferring a Righteouſneſs upon him,</hi> viz <hi>Not in a Phyſical, or moral Senſe, but Judicial, that is, he ſhall be righteous in the Eye of the Law.</hi> Scrip. Juſt. P. 12. By Righteous, and not Guilty, I hope you do not mean Innocent, as Mr. <hi>Gilbert</hi> in your Quotation of him, ſeems to underſtand, and to make Chriſts Righteouſneſs, which is a Righteouſneſs according to the Law of Innocency, to be that by which we are juſtified. I do not know his Book, whether it be ſo; but there is indeed no <hi>Legal</hi> Juſtification, and Juſtification by the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is the Juſtification of a Sinner, one <hi>Ungodly</hi> ſtill in the Eye of the Law, and <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi> or <hi>Not guilty,</hi> only <hi>Quoad hoc,</hi> in reſpect to the Law of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and that not but he hath ſinned againſt the <hi>Law,</hi> and againſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94667:25"/>the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> but yet is <hi>Not guilty</hi> in regard to the Accuſation, of his <hi>Non-performance of the Condition.</hi> If God looks on him as cloathed with Chriſts Righteouſneſs, he muſt be look'd on as one that never ſinned, when he ſhall be look'd on as never innocent, but pardoned (as I have had it) even in Heaven. For the other Point, wherein you were at firſt more near and grew farther off in your latter Letters, our Difference appears by your Words and my Notes, to depend at laſt altogether upon this nice Matter, Whether Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive,</hi> be <hi>one</hi> or <hi>two</hi> Juſtifications. And by my Notes and your Words or Grant too, it appears, they may be both. They are <hi>one</hi> to pleaſe you, they are <hi>two</hi> to pleaſe me. For the <hi>Matter</hi> is the ſame in both, but being diſtinguiſhed and ſo different, their <hi>Forms</hi> muſt be two. They are <hi>Materally</hi> one three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but <hi>Formally</hi> two: they are <hi>Formally</hi> two, but <hi>Materially</hi> one and the ſame Juſtification.</p>
               <p>I will end now after all with the Confeſſion, That what I offer in theſe two Letters, and my late three Books on this Subject, is but <hi>Digging.</hi> It is but the <hi>Ore,</hi> I ſay, there I turn up, which muſt be refined and made good <hi>Metal,</hi> if it can, by better Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, wherein you for one have not been wanting in your Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. For my own part, it is Truth and Peace, and no Intereſt that I ſeek. I will conclude therefore with that Paſſage of Dr. <hi>Owen, However our Proteſtants have differed in the Way and Methods of its Declaration, yet in this they are generally agreed that it is the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and not our own</hi> Merits, <hi>on Account whereof we receive pardon of ſin, acceptance with God, are declared righteous by the Goſpel, and have a title to the heavenly Inheritance.</hi> There is but this one Word <hi>[Merit]</hi> I put in, and I alſo can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord with them, and add this, That the whole merit of our Salvation, from firſt to laſt is by you and I, as well as by him, and our other Brethren, attributed, not to our own Works, but wholly to the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> (as they go both into his <hi>Satisfaction</hi>) of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. The Dr. goes on, <hi>Herein, I ſay, they were generally agreed, firſt againſt the Papiſt, and afterwards againſt the Socintan: And when this is granted, I will not contend with any Man about his way of declaring the Doctrine of it.</hi> For this benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Doctor, I thank him. The Digger muſt needs put off his Cap, and ſhall therefore for the preſent lay down his Mattock, and leave Work.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Deo gloria, Mihi condonatio,</hi> John Humfrey.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:94667:25"/>
            <head>Sir <hi>Charles Wolſeley</hi> TO Mr. Humfrey, UPON His ſight of the foregoing LETTERS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My very worthy Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Sheets you were pleaſed to ſend me, containing your Letters and Mr. <hi>Clark</hi>'s, pleaſe me very well, and you have obliged me by them. I know no Man has travelled into the Controverſie of Juſtification with better ſucceſs than your ſelf: You have I think with great Accuracy and Judgment ſearched into, and found out the genuine Meaning of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, touching that important Point; And particularly in your clearing to us, what is meant by the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> ſo often mentioned by St. <hi>Paul.</hi> It has generally been taken for the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt, you have made it very evident to me to be meant of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, and that is a Key of ſingular uſe to unlock us into the true Notion of Goſpel-Juſtification. I like what you have written ſo very well, that what I have to ſay to it will be contained in theſe two words, <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi> I am not a little ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:94667:26"/>to find that what I have formerly written on that ſubject, does ſo perfectly Coaleſce with your Sentiments throughout. There is only one thing wherein you and I ſeem any thing to differ, either in Senſe or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and that is touching Pardon of Sin, to which you may poſſibly think I do allow a greater ſhare in Juſtification than I ought; but I think you will find that you and I are upon very good Terms of concord therein. Faith and Goſpel obedience I acknowledge do conſtitute us Evangelically Righteous, but are not ſuch a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs as to make God reckon us for innocent Perſons, for ſo we are not, (for every Man that is in Heaven is there as a pardoned Sinner) as well as a righteous Perſon in Goſpel Senſe, for that is a Righteouſneſs contrived by God to qualifie an Offender for Pardon, and ſtands in direct oppoſition to that Righteouſneſs by Works St. <hi>Paul</hi> inveighs ſo much againſt; but it ſerves us in as much ſtead as if we were ſo, for it entitles us to all the Benefits of Chriſts Satisfaction, qualifies us for, helps us to Pardon of Sin, and Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God, and ſo our Goſpel-righteouſneſs in effect is but to procure Pardon, and therefore it is that the Scriptures that were not writ with any Relation to thoſe nice and ſubtle diſtinctions, which Men have ſince uſed in interpreting of them, do chiefly intend to expreſs their plain and genuine Meaning of Things, and in an eſpecial manner by various Expreſſions of the ſame thing do ſet forth the amplitude of Goſpel-ſalvation. 'Tis evident from the 4th of the <hi>Romans</hi> and the 7th, that imputing Righteouſneſs, and Forgiveneſs of Sin are inſeparable, and therefore ſometimes Juſtification is ſpoken of in Scripture in its <hi>Cauſe,</hi> which is imputing Righteouſneſs by Faith, and ſometimes in its <hi>Effect,</hi> which is Pardon; Therefore I am well pleaſed to ſay with you, to adjuſt and comprehend that matter right, that the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> of Juſtification is Goſpel-faith and Obedience, and Pardon of ſin the neceſſary Conſequent, Concomitant and Effect of it, and he that will give any other account of it, muſt (I believe) make uſe of ſome other Doctor than St. <hi>Paul.</hi> To think of obtaining Pardon any other way than by performing the Goſpel-conditions of Faith and Obedience, is a great Antinomian folly, and a dangerous Error. I am very ſenſible that thoſe that pretend above others to exalt free Grace, and take no notice of the Goſpel Conditions upon the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of which it is only diſpenſed, do it ſeemingly, but not in truth and reality, and as it ſhould be done, and are dangerous Miſ-leaders: Such Notions do generally gratifie all <hi>falſe</hi> Profeſſors, and often
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:94667:26"/>inſnare and miſguide the trueſt. Chriſts part is certainly performed, the great buſineſs is to ſtir Men up to perform their's; for when Chriſt had perfected the Salvation of the World, what then? Was there a a Proclamation publiſhed from Heaven, That all Men were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon actually ſaved? No, 'twas far otherwiſe: but God thereupon enters into a new Covenant with the World, and proclaims a Law of Grace with this Condition annexed, <hi>He that believes ſhall be ſaved, and he that believes not ſhall be condemned.</hi> He becomes the Author of Eternal Salvation only to thoſe that obey him: 'Tis in other words to ſay, He that believes the Goſpel and becomes obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to it ſhall have the benefit of Chriſts purchaſe. I look upon it as a moſt prophane Error to ſay, that God ever intended to carry any Man to Heaven without a perſonal Righteouſneſs, ſuch an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſtands in direct oppoſition to the purity of his Attributes, and the Oeconomy of his Government. What both you and I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, does truly and according to Gods way of diſpenſing it, exalt Grace as much as it can be, for we aſcribe all that we have under the Goſpel intirely to Grace: When we ſpeak of Faith and Goſpel-obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, we only ſpeak of the method in which the Grace of God and the Merits of Chriſt are diſpenſed, for we acknowledge that our Faith and Obedience in themſelves are very impotent and defective, and of no value, as to the Point of Juſtification, farther than God is pleaſed to impute and reckon them out of Grace and Favour to our advantage, as Methods by him appointed to bring us into all the bleſſed effects of Chriſts purchaſe.</p>
            <p>Sir, I am alſo to thank you for that you have in your late Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, Collected, Adjuſted and Interpreted the diſperſed Notions upon this Subject, in the Works of that moſt Excellent Perſon, your particular Friend and mine, Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who was the early Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulger and conſtant Defender of the Right Scripture Doctrine of <hi>Justification.</hi> Tho' no Man pays a greater deference than I do to his Memory, yet this I muſt needs ſay to you, touching what he has writ about this Point and many others, his Writings are haunted with a crowd of Logical Diſtinctions, which do much obſcure, I had almoſt ſaid deface his clear and excellent Senſe; he needed not have choſen that method of expreſſing himſelf, for tho' he never wore the Gowns of either Univerſity upon his back, yet he had the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them both in his Head, and that was very perſpicuous in all his Writings. I am alſo to thank you for rectifying the Notions of that exceeding pious and learned Perſon Doctor <hi>Owen</hi> touching this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherein I think you have been very ſucceſiful. I ſuppoſe you
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:94667:27"/>know his Book of Juſtification was particularly written againſt mine. Very many have preſſed me to anſwer it, which I acknowledge to you I did not look upon as <hi>duram provinciam.</hi> The great Friendſhip that was between him and me, might well ſeem ſufficient to have byaſſed me not to reply; but the true reaſon was, I thought that little Cottage I had erected was in no great danger of being ſhocked or demoliſhed by any thing in that Book. The Doctrine of perſonal Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs to every Believer, which that moſt Learned Perſon aſſerts and defends is ſo Unſcriptural, having not one Text to defend it, has ſo many Unjuſtifiable and contradictory Conſequences attending it; and indeed there are ſo many Triumphs over it by thoſe that have written againſt it in the Bookſellers Shops, that it is ſcarce worth any Mans while to harneſs himſelf for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of that Point. If when Men ſpeak of imputing Chriſts Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to every Believer, they mean the imputing of it only in the Effects and Advantages of it, they ſay what you and I ſay.</p>
            <p>Sir, I am very well ſatisfied you have done this Age very good Service, to convince Men of the neceſſity of performing the Goſpel-Conditions, if ever they will reap the benefit of what Chriſt hath done for us. Faith and ſincere Obedience is the way by which God juſtified and ſaved <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Father of the Faithful, and in him gave an inſtance how all Men, to the Worlds end, are to obtain Heaven and Salvation, even by treading in the ſteps of their Father <hi>Abraham.</hi> Two ways we ſee Men generally miſcarry, either by a prophane Neglect of the Goſpel, or an hypocritical Profeſſion of it. Happy would the World be, if delivered from Prophaneneſs on the one hand, and falſe Godlineſs on the other. I have nothing to add but that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your very affectionate and obliged Friend and Servant,</hi> Charles Wolſeley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:94667:27"/>
            <head>The Animadverſions.</head>
            <p>THere was a Sheet called <hi>The Report,</hi> which I read, and four or five called <hi>A Rebuke</hi> of that Report, which I read like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. I ſuppoſe the Author of the <hi>firſt</hi> thought it neceſſary to inform the Country of the true State of the Difference about Doctrinals there was in the City, and made that <hi>Report</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Conſcience: I ſuppoſe alſo that the Author of the <hi>ſecond</hi> thought it fit in conſcience to rebuke that Report, as giving wrong Information: And if any have been offended at either, it is that ſuppoſed neceſſity muſt excuſe both. There were four Sheets I wrote as a <hi>Friendly Interpoſer</hi> between them, and theſe I write now, I intended as a <hi>Second Port,</hi> in regard to that <hi>Title.</hi> Since theſe, there came out a <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Report,</hi> and more lately a <hi>Vindication</hi> of the <hi>Rebuke,</hi> which Books having not the excuſe of ſuch neceſſity are faulty, and their fault being openly committed, is openly to be reproved, and that is, that they knowingly (ſometimes) <hi>abuſe one another.</hi> Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> upon an <hi>Objectors</hi> ſaying, <hi>In our place and ſtead, with ſome does ſignifie no more than for our good,</hi> anſwers, <hi>It is impoſſible they ſhould.</hi> Mr. <hi>Report</hi> takes up this paſſage and exagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates it as a piece of <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> when it is manifeſt that Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> ſpeaks it as a piece of <hi>Wit,</hi> not meaning that Chriſt dyed <hi>only for our good,</hi> but becauſe what he did and ſuffered <hi>in our place and ſtead</hi> was for our good. On the other hand Mr. <hi>Report,</hi> ſpeaking of the particular matter he was concern'd about, ſays, <hi>This is the ſubſtance of the Goſpel:</hi> Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> hereupon tells him of Regeneration, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Faith, Good Works, that are parts of the Goſpel, and thereby endeavours to expoſe him for <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> as one that excludes theſe things out of the Goſpel; and in the end of his <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication</hi> he cites ſome words out of Mr. <hi>Report</hi>'s <hi>Appeal,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulates his return to himſelf, that now acknowledges Repentance neceſſary to Pardon, and Faith to Juſtfication, in ſome ſuch words, which are all manifeſt <hi>Abuſe</hi> on both ſides, for neither does Mr. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> believe Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> a <hi>Socinian,</hi> nor Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> believe Mr. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> an <hi>Antinomian;</hi> they may as well ſay they are two <hi>Dears</hi> or
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:94667:28"/>two <hi>Birds,</hi> as to ſay that either is a <hi>Socinian</hi> or <hi>Antinomian.</hi> I muſt confeſs there is one Chapter in the <hi>Vindication,</hi> about <hi>Chriſts dying in our ſtead,</hi> that is ſo well, ſo ſolid, ſo appoſitely ſcriptured, ſo brief and convincing againſt the <hi>Socinian,</hi> that (excepting all Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, to his Adverſary) I have been ſeldom pleaſed and ſatisfied with any thing more; and I muſt confeſs moreover my pleaſure in reading the Book, that I left not, though it be ten Sheets (unleſs for a ſpirt) till I had done: Yet does not all his <hi>Wit,</hi> nor his <hi>Eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> recompence ſo ill an Example as the <hi>rendring evil</hi> for <hi>evil,</hi> that is, <hi>Abuſe</hi> for <hi>Abuſe,</hi> which is not only a fault as to Men, but a ſin as to God; and I pray God forgive them both, and I pray them to forgive me the telling them of it. I ſhall let alone therefore theſe Books mentioned, and take notice only of theſe two more, that is, the <hi>Anſwer</hi> of our <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Brethren to Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> ſet out by Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> and the <hi>Appeal</hi> of Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> and ſhall offer a few Animadverſions upon ſome Paſſages, which others it is like would not, at leaſt with that impartiality (whether they offend or not) as I do.</p>
            <p>A great part I perceive of theſe Books is about the Phraſe <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of Perſons,</hi> for Explication whereof the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren diſtinguiſh of a <hi>Natural, Moral</hi> and <hi>Legal</hi> Change (p. 12.) and tell us that there is no change of Chriſts <hi>Natural Perſon</hi> into Ours, or Ours into His, and that Chriſts <hi>Qualities</hi> likewiſe are not made Ours, nor Ours His, which is moſt true without doubt, but who ever thought otherwiſe? Who ever queſtioned any ſuch thing, that there is need of ſuch a diſtinction? If any think that Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> by Chriſts taking our <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Condition,</hi> and we his, did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand theſe Brethrens <hi>Moral</hi> Change, as if the <hi>Accidents</hi> of one <hi>Subject</hi> could migrate into another, they abuſe the <hi>Doctor,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him ſuch a Blockhead as no Scholar is to be ſuppoſed. No, when he tells us that Chriſt was as <hi>compleat a ſinner as we, and we as compleatly righteous as he,</hi> it muſt be conſtrued only by way of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation:</hi> We muſt not wreſt any words of his to make him think otherwiſe. It is true now here, that in this Imputation of our ſins to Chriſt he underſtands it not only <hi>quod reatum paenae,</hi> but <hi>Culpae</hi> alſo, which is his Error, but as for this diſtinction of a <hi>Moral Change,</hi> it does not affect him any more than the <hi>Brethren</hi> themſelves; ſo that they do thereby only beat the Air, not him; It is no more to the confuting <hi>Antinomianiſm</hi> than might be ſpared: And as for the word <hi>Legal Change,</hi> upon which they pitch, they do it not without fear of danger, as themſelves acknowledge, and have reaſon, ſo
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:94667:28"/>that indeed in the Explication of this Phraſe <hi>[Change of Perſons]</hi> they ſhould not have diſtinguiſh'd upon the word <hi>[Change]</hi> but the word <hi>[Perſon.]</hi> The word <hi>[Perſon]</hi> is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, lyable to a diverſe Acceptation; the word <hi>[Change]</hi> to none: <hi>Change</hi> is <hi>Change,</hi> but <hi>Perſon</hi> is not <hi>Perſon.</hi> There is a <hi>Natural Perſon,</hi> and a <hi>Legal Perſon,</hi> which are two of their three Terms; but the Term <hi>[Moral]</hi> as to <hi>Perſon,</hi> hath no place here. And it is Chriſt <hi>Natural</hi> Perſon (tho' there be no <hi>Natural Change</hi>) which comes in the room of our <hi>Natural Perſons,</hi> to bear the Puniſhment of our ſins, that is, the <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> as is neceſſary to the Explication of the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> If there be any change of Perſon elſe, in regard to the Term <hi>[Legal Perſon]</hi> let any of the <hi>Brethren</hi> that can make it our.</p>
            <p>By this Diſtinction mentioned, it is one thing with them for Chriſt to take on him our <hi>Perſon,</hi> and another our <hi>Quality, State</hi> or <hi>Condition,</hi> and our Brethren therefore do impugne Mr. <hi>Lobb's</hi> ſaying, That <hi>Chriſt put himſelf into our Place, State and Condition,</hi> (P. 31.) when even theſe words are, and may be uſed as well as <hi>ſuſtaining our Perſon,</hi> and <hi>ſuffering in our ſtead,</hi> giving them the ſame Orthodox Conſtruction. Such Expreſſions muſt be taken not <hi>ſimpliciter,</hi> but <hi>ſecundum quid,</hi> not in regard to <hi>every thing,</hi> but to <hi>one thing.</hi> Chriſt did take on him our State, Condition or Quality, as we were lyable to Puniſhment, or as obnoxious to the <hi>Curſe</hi> for our ſins, and ſo became a <hi>Curſe</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for us: But when Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> ſays further, that we were Sinners and <hi>deſtitute of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> he muſt be conſtrued to ſpeak ſo alſo in regard to the Puniſhment due to us thereupon, and that Chriſt took upon him that <hi>Condition,</hi> only whereby he was lyable, in our ſtead: But to preſs him therefore with the conſequence, that Chriſt muſt be a <hi>ſinner</hi> and <hi>deſtitute of Righteouſneſs.</hi> is to preſs him too hard, for he is one we know, that denies the <hi>Criſpian</hi> Senſe of <hi>Change of Perſons,</hi> as well as the <hi>Brethren:</hi> And tho' they do here but take him on the hip upon a ſlip of Words, they by and by do him plain wrong, when upon the right Interpretation they make, they ſay, <hi>This will not content him,</hi> for it will and does <hi>content</hi> him, and he means no otherwiſe than they; and as for their making him hold, That <hi>Chriſt was changed to be a ſinful Perſon, deſtitute of Righteouſneſs,</hi> as they go on in the place, <hi>A lapſus linguae</hi> is no <hi>Error mentis,</hi> and the arguing him into what he abhors, is not doing as good Men would be done by themſelves. They are in good earneſt here too heavy upon him.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:94667:29"/>
            <p>In theſe Papers of the Brethren, there is a Letter from the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and part of ſome Letters from <hi>Dr. Edwards.</hi> That which is quoted out of the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſeems to me open, obvious, and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying. That which is ſaid by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> is writ with Prudence and Caution, with Ability and Authority, but not with that openneſs altogether as I, who <hi>ſpeak as a Fool,</hi> could wiſh.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Commutation of Perſons</hi> between Chriſt and us, according to his Lordſhip, may have a threefold ſenſe. <hi>One</hi> which implies Chriſt being appointed to Act in our behalf, for our benefit, which the <hi>Socinians</hi> will grant. <hi>Another,</hi> which implies not only his acting for our benefit, but his being ſubſtituted in our ſtead, in bearing our Puniſhment, to become an Attonement for us, that is, to ſatisfie Gods Juſtice, that ſo by an Act (or New Law) of Grace he might grant us Pardon and Life, upon the Conditions of the Goſpel, which is the ſound Senſe of this <hi>Change of Perſons,</hi> according to <hi>Grotius,</hi> this Learned <hi>Biſhop,</hi> our <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Brethren and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> alſo, which he will not gainſay, tho' whether he will have more to it, let himſelf tell. For,</p>
            <p>There is a <hi>third</hi> Senſe of this <hi>Commutation,</hi> which implies a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of our ſins upon Chriſt and of his Righteouſneſs upon us, which admits of a double Senſe, one of Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> and the <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians,</hi> and the other of ſuch we call <hi>Orthodox,</hi> embracing the Common <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Juſtification.</hi> This <hi>third</hi> Senſe, as owned by Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> the Biſhop hath in ſhort words ſet out right, which is in two Points differing from the <hi>Orthodox.</hi> One is, that Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> accounts our ſins to be tranſlated on, or imputed to Chriſt, not only as to the <hi>Obligation of Puniſhment,</hi> but in regard to the <hi>guilt of the Fault:</hi> The other is, that Chriſts Righteouſneſs is tranſlated on the Elect before they believe, and conſequently they are juſtified without Faith. Now the <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſets himſelf againſt this <hi>third Crispian</hi> Senſe and beſtows a great part of his Letter to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute this known exploded Error; ſo that as I have ſaid of our <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns</hi> Diſtinction before, that they did but beat the Air, and confute no Body, I muſt needs ſay of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> that he does indeed beat ſome Body, that is, confute the <hi>Criſpian,</hi> but his beating is beſides the Cuſhion. This excellent Biſhops Work were to conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhall admit or confute Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> and thoſe that hold ſuch a tranſlation of our ſins on Chriſt, and his Righteouſneſs on us, as is maintained without either of theſe <hi>Criſpian</hi> Errors. To prove that a Man muſt believe before he is juſtified, needs no more than theſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>We have believed, that we may
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:94667:29"/>be juſtified:</hi> The elaborate proving ſuch Doctrine to be againſt the Scripture, is but a prudential declination of that difficult Task, that calls here for his undertaking.</p>
            <p>The common <hi>Proteſtant</hi> I will ſuppoſe when the Scripture ſpeaks of our ſins being laid on Chriſt, or Chriſt bearing our ſins on the Croſs, or the like, do underſtand no other thing than the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> that is, he took on him our ſins, in regard to the <hi>Legal</hi> Guilt, not <hi>Perſonal,</hi> to uſe his words, underſtanding by thoſe Terms <hi>reatum paenae,</hi> not <hi>culpae,</hi> in the ordinary diſtinction (for when the Biſhop makes <hi>Legal Guilt</hi> to imply <hi>deſert</hi> of Puniſhment, as well as the <hi>Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to it, his <hi>perſonal</hi> Guilt is one with <hi>Legal,</hi> beſides the term <hi>[Legal Guilt]</hi> is dangerous, leſt any thereby ſhould underſtand Chriſt to be our <hi>Legal</hi> Perſon, ſo as to be in us Guilty, and we righteous in him) or to ſpeak ſureſt, he took on him our <hi>Puniſhment</hi> without the <hi>deſert</hi> of it, and ſo neither I or the Biſhop, or our Presbyterian Brethren differ in the leaſt, as to this part of the Tranſlation, which is to be granted as neceſſary to the Explanation of the Doctrine of Chriſts <hi>Satisfaction:</hi> But as to the other part of this Tranſlation, which is the transferring his Righteouſneſs on the <hi>Believer</hi> (not on the <hi>Elect</hi> before Faith, for that is <hi>Antinomianiſm</hi>) in ſuch a ſenſe as is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the making out the Doctrine of Juſtification, according to the Common Proteſtant, here is the Point which requires the <hi>Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> of this moſt Learned <hi>Biſhop:</hi> whereof if he dare venture his Credit, ſo as to tell his Judgment plainly (which would tend to the eſtabliſhment of many) he ſhall do a great thing, a daring mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherein yet he is thus far advanced, that he hath in this Letter, made an on-ſet on the greateſt ſtrength of the Antagoniſt, which is <hi>That,</hi> they raiſe upon the words of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>He hath made him ſin for us, who knew no ſin, that we might be made the Righteouſneſs of God in him:</hi> Unto which Text the Biſhop anſwers, That <hi>by Chriſts being made ſin, is meant a Sacrifice for ſin, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Scripture Senſe: And we are made the Righteouſneſs of God in him,</hi> in that <hi>God, upon the account of his Sacrifice and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation to him, does treat us as Righteous</hi> Perſons, <hi>or receive us into his Grace and Favour</hi> upon our believing. I add, <hi>upon our believing,</hi> as what is underſtood by him. And this <hi>is all</hi> (he ſays) <hi>that he can find St.</hi> Paul <hi>underſtood by this Expreſſion.</hi> Here we ſee this Text brought off ſo cleverly, as that there is no Arrow hath toucht him, but withal, ſo cautiouſly and prudentially for fear of ſhot, that I cannot but take notice of that Learned Gentleman that hath wrote on this Subject, Sir <hi>Charles Wolſeley</hi>'s greater Reſolution, who hath
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:94667:30"/>ſaid the ſame thing upon this Text with the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> but without dread of the Bullets. <hi>The meaning is</hi> (ſays he) <hi>this, Chriſt that was without ſin was ordained of God to be a Sacrifice for ſin, that we might thereby be made righteous with the Goſpel-Righteouſneſs, for that is the general meaning every where of the Righteouſneſs of God.</hi> Sir C. <hi>W</hi>'s <hi>Evan. Juſt.</hi> p. 64. The direct anſwer to this Text is this, That <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God in him,</hi> is not the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Christ,</hi> according to our Common Proteſtant Divines, which is manifeſt, becauſe <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Him</hi> are two, as I have it (in my <hi>Right. of God.</hi> P. 11.) with this Argument, <hi>Juſtitia Dei eſt finis ſive effectum ex eo quod Christus peccatum pro nobis factus eſt. Hoc autem ipſum eſt Chriſts obedientia. E'go juſtitia Dei non eſt Chriſti Obedientia.</hi> Wotton.</p>
            <p>The Common <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Opinion accounted <hi>Orthodox,</hi> is that we are juſtified by Faith <hi>Objective,</hi> that is by Chriſts Righteouſneſs, which is its Object, received by Faith as the Inſtrument making it ours, ſo that God looks upon us as righteous in his Righteouſneſs, or <hi>accounts</hi> us ſo, which is our <hi>Juſtification.</hi> The Opinion I hold (as what I think thoſe that go Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s way, are to come to) I declare to be, that we are juſtified by Faith <hi>Formaliter,</hi> and through Chriſts Righteouſneſs,<note place="margin">Si juſtitia eſt opus Dei, quomodo erit opus Dei ut credatur in eum, niſi ipſa ſit juſtitia, ut cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus in cum? <hi>Aug. in Jo.</hi> 6.29.</note> as the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious Cauſe</hi> only. The Scripture is manifeſt, that by Faith we are juſtified. <hi>Was not</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>juſtified by Faith? The juſt ſhall live by Faith.</hi> This is ſtedfaſtly atteſted by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. <hi>By Faith;</hi> ſo that Faith is the <hi>id per quod,</hi> as the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt the <hi>id propter quod,</hi> the Believer is juſtified. The <hi>Meritorious</hi> Cauſe is the <hi>Efficient Protatarctick,</hi> and cannot be the <hi>Formal.</hi> That Chriſts Righteouſneſs therefore, is not the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers <hi>formal Righteouſneſs,</hi> I muſt lay down among the ſet of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as certainly appertaining to Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> way of Juſtification, ſo that the Maintenance of, or Departure from that Aſſertion, does aſſuredly <hi>make,</hi> or <hi>marr,</hi> the right conception of that <hi>Article.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no Point of moment, but hath its ſet of Notions (as I ſay) belonging to it, and whether the <hi>Biſhop</hi> will go the Common way of the Proteſtant, or a way of his own altogether, or the way of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> which I and Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> do go, as to the main, I ſuppoſe that <hi>excellent</hi> Perſon, who is able to perceive that Concatenation of Notions, belonging to the way he takes, will lay them ſo together, as to make the whole agreeable, knowing well, that if he break one of the Set, one Link, he breaks all, the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:94667:30"/>whole Chain. The fundamental Notion in the way that Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and <hi>I,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> go, is this, That it is not by the <hi>Law,</hi> but the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> not by the Law of <hi>Works,</hi> but the Law of <hi>Grace,</hi> that we are to be <hi>judged,</hi> and conſequently <hi>juſtified</hi> or <hi>condemned.</hi> One other Notion of his, near to this, is, that the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is not, cannot be imputed to us (that is, reckoned to us as ours) any otherwiſe than in the <hi>Effects.</hi> The Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is a Righteouſneſs that anſwers the <hi>Law,</hi> and if that be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us <hi>in ſe,</hi> for our Juſtification, then we are juſtified by the <hi>Law.</hi> When Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> therefore ſays with us, that it is by the <hi>Goſpel</hi> (not the <hi>Law</hi>) we are to be <hi>judged,</hi> and yet that <hi>Beſides the effects, the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to the Believer,</hi> that thereby he may be juſtified (which muſt be underſtood) it is a plain Inconſiſtency, a perfect Tergiverſation. As for what Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> offers in <hi>Made made righteous,</hi> p. 76. to 83. I have anſwered, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifica.</hi> p. 35, 36. Let me ask him upon it, when he ſays, <hi>The very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to the Believer,</hi> does he underſtand by the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> that which his Brethren do, or not? If he does, he is held under this Inconſiſtency, and can never come off: If he do not, then the Brethren are deceived in him. He appears to be of their Judgment, about the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and yet underſtands by Chriſts Righteouſneſs another thing than they do. What Man before him, ever ſaid or underſtood that Chriſts <hi>Right to his Reward,</hi> is the Righteouſneſs which is imputed to a Believer? I argue againſt him. The Righteouſneſs which is imputed to a Believer, is that Righteouſneſs which is the Meritorious Cauſe of his Juſtification: But it is not Chriſts Right to his Reward, but the Obedience of his Life and Death (which two things he diſtinguiſhes, and makes a double Righteouſneſs, and brings himſelf off with the firſt, inſtead of affirming the laſt) which is the Meritorious Cauſe of our Juſtification. And as for what he ſays in affirming, Chriſts Right to his Reward, to be the Believers, His own Right, and the Believers to be the ſame Right, it is impoſſible accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Rule of <hi>Accidents,</hi> as I anſwer him in my <hi>Pacification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is another Diſtinction of Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi> uſes in his <hi>Rebuke,</hi> directly contrary to him in the Terms, yet Neither, differing in the Doctrine of it, that I will take this occaſion to remember. Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Phraſe of <hi>Change of Perſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> impugnes, but yet grants a <hi>Change of Perſons.</hi> By Change of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I doubt not but the Dr. meant a Change on both ſides, as appears by his Explication, that Chriſt became a ſinner as we, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:94667:31"/>we righteous as he, and that is a <hi>Change of Perſons.</hi> There is a Change of <hi>Perſon</hi> on one ſide, and a Change of <hi>Perſon</hi> on both ſides. A Change of both ſides is all one with a <hi>Change of Perſons.</hi> When Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> then upon this, diſtinguiſhes between a Change of <hi>Perſon,</hi> and Change of <hi>Perſons,</hi> it is his own Diſtinction, when the Doctor never thought of any; and when it is his own, he may make what Conſtruction of it he pleaſe, and that he puts on it be ſure ſhall be <hi>Orthodox;</hi> for by the one he will have Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation underſtood, and deny it; by the other, the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation, and hold it. Here is his Doctrine found, but his <hi>Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> as he uſes the Terms ſo forced, ſtrained, unnatural, that it is uſeleſs altotether, but to bring himſelf off, and ſerve his occaſion: Whereas the Diſtinction, as uſed by Mr. <hi>Alſop,</hi> is ſo appoſite, eaſie, proper, natural in the Terms, that if it be ſtood to, no Diſtinction can be of more uſe for deciding the Controverſie of our Brethren. By Change of Perſon, Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi> underſtands, One coming in the room of another; By Change of Perſons, Both coming in the room of one another; and when Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> grants a Change of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and denies a Change of Perſon, he (Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi>) does hold a Change of Perſon, and denies a Change of Perſons, and yet both agree (I have ſaid) in the Doctrine they make of it. Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi>'s Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction then fuller explained, is between Chriſts ſuſtaining or putting on our Perſon, his taking our State and Condition, or his obeying and ſuffering in our room or ſtead, and Our ſuſtaining or putting on <hi>Chriſts Perſen,</hi> taking on us his Quality or Condition, or coming in his room or place. The one he maintains, and denies the other. I will add, he does hold, and it is to be held, that Chriſt ſtood in our room and ſtead, and ſo may be ſaid to put on our Perſon in obeying and ſuffering for us, as neceſſary to the Doctrine of <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction;</hi> but he denies, or I do, (as that which is to be denied) that we take on us Chriſts Perſon, or come in his room or ſtead, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary (which others affirm) to our <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To make this appear (as to the right ſenſe of it) we muſt know, that to take anothers Perſon, or to do or ſuffer any thing in, the room or place of another, is to do or ſuffer the thing, to free the other from the doing or ſuffering. When Chriſt then is ſaid to dye for us, or for our ſins, which is all one as taking our Perſon, or ſuffering in our room, place or ſtead, it ſignifies that he obeyed the Law, and ſuffered the penalty, that we might not be bound to that perfect Obedience, as the Condition of Life, and that we might not ſuffer the Curſe of it, and this is neceſſary to the making God Satisfaction,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:94667:31"/>that we may be pardoned and eſcape the ſame: But for us to put on Chriſts Perſon, or come in his room or ſtead, does ſignifie our doing and ſuffering in him, as our <hi>Legal</hi> or <hi>Civil</hi> Perſon, what he did and ſuffered, and ſo be look'd on as having fulfilled the Law, both in obeying and ſuffering; ſo that his Obedience, both of his Life and Death, is <hi>imputatively</hi> ours, and we <hi>in ſenſu forenſi,</hi> as righteous as he in the ſight of God, and juſtified by the <hi>Law</hi> as Chriſt was. This <hi>Commutation of Perſon</hi> therefore we deny, as that Doctrine which ſubverts the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>It was a deep miſtake in the much reading of Mr. <hi>Report,</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that the <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> in the Senſe of <hi>Grotius,</hi> is conducive to the Explanation of the Doctrine of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> according to the Common Proteſtant, as it is to that of <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> There was a Surrogation of Chriſts Perſon in our room, for his making <hi>Satisfaction;</hi> there is no Surrogation of our Perſons in his room, for receiving <hi>Juſtification. Of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to us, as if we had performed it all, and of Faith whoſe Office it is to embrace that Righteouſneſs ſo imputed, there is not one word in the Sacred Letters,</hi> ſays the Learned <hi>Grotius:</hi> If the <hi>Biſhop</hi> before praiſed, dare follow that leading Man in the <hi>one</hi> Point, as in the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will come now therefore to this new Book of Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> which he calls <hi>An Appeal,</hi> that is, from the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Brethren, to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> as Moderator between them. They produce the Biſhops Letter in their Vindication, and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> ſticks to that Letter, as vindicating him, and both are in the right; for when they agree to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> they muſt agree alſo with one another. In this <hi>Appeal,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> looking on Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> as in the Chair of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> to maintain his Doctrine, does collect many Puſſages out of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> which are approaching to the Socinians, and ſuppoſes ſuch Doctrine to be inconſiſtent with the Doctrine of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> that he maintains againſt <hi>Crellius,</hi> in his Book of the <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt.</hi> We ſhall ſee, if the <hi>Biſhop</hi> writer, whether he judges as Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> or rather ſhall ſee cauſe of Agreement, not Difference, with Mr. <hi>B.</hi> in this Point. That which I have to ſay is this.</p>
            <p>There is a vaſt difference in the account that muſt be given of two Men, ſpeaking the ſame things about a Doctrine, which is in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie between them, when one does bring them by way of <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> for <hi>Confutation</hi> of it, and the other by way of <hi>Explication,</hi> for the better clearing and <hi>maintaining</hi> it, in Anſwer to thoſe Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And there is a double Anſwer to an Objection, One is by <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:94667:32"/>when the matter is falſe; and the other is by <hi>Conceſſion,</hi> when the matter is true and reaſonable, but ſhewing that it affects not that Doctrine, which remains firm notwithſtanding that Conceſſion. This is the Caſe of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in regard to the <hi>Socinian.</hi> The <hi>Socinians</hi> ſay many things rationally, and which are true; and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in ſuch matters ſpares not to ſay the like; but the one ſays them for the <hi>Enervating,</hi> the other for the <hi>Elucidating</hi> the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> It is moſt certain, that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> holds the ſame Doctrine which <hi>Grotius</hi> does, and follows him in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, ſhewing the conſiſtency of it with Gods Free Grace, in the remiſſion of ſin, which two things <hi>Socinus</hi> thinks incompatible. To wit, in that when it is <hi>alius</hi> that ſuffers, it is <hi>aliud ſolvitur,</hi> and alſo it being not the <hi>Idem,</hi> but the <hi>Tantundem,</hi> which Chriſt ſuffered, and that it was not therefore the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelf, but the <hi>Law-giver</hi> he ſatisfied: Upon which accounts the Satisfaction was in it ſelf refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable, a <hi>Solutio recuſabilis</hi> as he, after <hi>Grotius,</hi> does call it, that is, ſuch as God in <hi>Juſtice,</hi> was not bound to accept, but in <hi>Mercy</hi> through Grace he did accept it, and what is more, found out this way of Satisfaction himſelf for us, which makes it ſo much more of Grace; ſo that a Free Pardon, I ſay, appears notwithſtanding this <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> as in the Sacrifices of the Jews for ſin, there was an Attonement made by their Blood, in order to the Remiſſion. That Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> does maintain this Doctrine of <hi>Grotius,</hi> this Doctrine that is the Marrow of the Old and New Teſtament, to wit, the Doctrine of <hi>Pardon upon Satisfaction</hi> againſt the <hi>Socinian,</hi> it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent I ſay, as that Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> does hold <hi>Juſtification upon believing</hi> againſt Dr. <hi>Criſp.</hi> And if it ſhall farther appear, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of all that he hath alledged againſt Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> is diſſonant to the mind of <hi>Grotius,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> he will I hope come off at laſt.</p>
            <p>To this end let us obſerve, that this Learned <hi>Biſhop</hi> in his Letter, ſpeaking of Chriſts bearing our ſins, and diſtinguiſhing the <hi>deſert</hi> of puniſhment from the <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> and affirming rightly, that though Chriſt took on him the <hi>Obligation</hi> to undergo the Puniſhment, the <hi>Deſert</hi> could not be transferr'd upon him, he hath theſe words; <hi>No Man can ceaſe to deſerve Puniſhment for his own Faults, nor Deſerve that another ſhould be puniſhed for them.</hi> This Saying is ſo true, plain and reaſonable, that though <hi>Socinus, Crellius,</hi> or any of their Followers, ſhall ſtand upon it never ſo much, it is not to be denied, but granted for all that. Upon this Foundation it follows: If no Man can <hi>deſerve</hi> that another be puniſhed for him, then cannot we
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:94667:32"/>by our ſins deſerve Chriſts ſufferings. We deſerved the Puniſhment (it was a deſerved <hi>Puniſhment</hi>) but we deſerved not that he ſhould bear it. If our ſins then <hi>deſerved</hi> not that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer, they are not the <hi>Meritorious</hi> Cauſe of his Sufferings. If not the Meritorious Cauſe, no proper Cauſe, but the <hi>Occaſion,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is cited by Mr. <hi>Lobb.</hi> And to go on, the reaſon appears, It was not from the <hi>Law</hi> his Obligation to ſuffer did ariſe, for the Law puniſhes only the Tranſgreſſor: <hi>Noxu caput ſiquitur.</hi> It was not <hi>our</hi> Obligation therefore he took on him, for our Obligation is an Obligation of deſert (<hi>Obligatio Criminis,</hi> as it is call'd) but his only <hi>Ex contractu.</hi> And ſeeing it was not <hi>Obligatio ex Lege,</hi> it follows that the Sufferings he bore were <hi>Materially, not Formally,</hi> Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>It was the ſins of Mankind</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) <hi>that were the Occaſion of Chriſts Sufferings, called by ſome an aſſumed Meritorious Cauſe, becauſe by his conſent they were</hi> loco cauſae Meritoriae. <hi>End of Contro.</hi> C. 13. In which Words, and all other Paſſages col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> what is there to be found fault with, unleſs an over perſpicacity, tightneſs, and conſonancy of Judgment in all his Pieces alike, made good all by the reaſon of that undeniable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, that <hi>One Man cannot deſerve that another ſhould be puniſhed for his Faults,</hi> as the Biſhop has it.</p>
            <p>And now to come from the <hi>Biſhop</hi> to <hi>Grotius;</hi> It muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that <hi>Grotius</hi> hath made it his buſineſs to ſhew, that our ſins were the Impulſive, the Meritorious Impulſive Cauſe of Chriſts Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, in his dying for us, which he hath proved no leſs ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially than critically, by the Prepoſitions <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Pro peccatis:</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>cum accuſativo,</hi> Rom. 4.25: <hi>Propter peccuta;</hi> and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5. <hi>Ob peccata noſtra;</hi> which all denote the <hi>Impulſive</hi> Cauſe (ſays he) and not the <hi>Final,</hi> againſt <hi>Socinus.</hi> Upon this, it is ſuppoſed by Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> that what is mentioned before, as ſaid by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> is contrary to this Doctrine, and he hath cited ſuch Paſſages therefore as <hi>Heterodox:</hi> But <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf muſt be the Man to Anſwer and Reconcile what he ſays, with what is ſaid by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> which he does very ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, with one word, that Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> hath not obſerved, at leaſt to make ſo good an uſe of it. For <hi>Socinus</hi> in oppoſition to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Satisfaction, denying that Chriſt could dye for ſin, as the <hi>Meritorious</hi> Cauſe of his Death, (which he will have to be only the <hi>Final</hi> Cauſe in turning us away from it) becauſe this muſt make him (as he argues) a ſinner, and one deſerving to die, <hi>Grotius</hi> takes him up, and tells us, that it was for ſin, but <hi>Imperſonaliter.</hi> This he
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:94667:33"/>explains in that our ſins did deſerve that Puniſhment ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, but ſuch was the goodneſs of God to ſpare us, and lay it upon his Son, who was <hi>wounded for our Tranſgreſſions, and through his ſtripes are we healed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that God might do ſo without Injuſtice, <hi>Grotius</hi> brings many Inſtances, from <hi>David,</hi> from <hi>Ahab,</hi> from the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> from the <hi>ſecond Commandment.</hi> What God himſelf does, or allows, muſt be juſt. <hi>David</hi> ſins, and his Child dies. <hi>Ahab</hi> is wicked, and his Puniſhment is deferred to his Sons Days. <hi>Saul</hi> is cruel to the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> and his Grandchildren are put to death. The Fathers ſin, and God viſits their ſin on the Children, to three or four Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. Here is <hi>Merit,</hi> as the Antecedent Cauſe of the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in all theſe Inſtances, and yet not the Merit of the <hi>Perſon</hi> or Perſons that ſuffer it. And what if I ſhall add here this great thing, (a thing wherein Divines are put ſo hard to it, in giving their account) even the greater Inſtance of <hi>Death paſſing on all Men</hi> (with their innocent Babes among them) for <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſgreſſion. It is ſaid of <hi>Grotius,</hi> and that ſolidly in another place, <hi>Peccata paenae cauſa ſunt non aliter quam per modum Meriti;</hi> which being true, <hi>Socinus</hi> does indeed ſeem to argue ſtrongly, that therefore <hi>prater Dei &amp; ipſius Chriſti voluntatem non poſſe ullam legitimam cauſam reddi mortis Chriſti niſi dicamus Chriſtum meritum fuiſſe ut moriretur.</hi> This <hi>Grotius,</hi> I ſay, takes up and Anſwers thus; <hi>Ineſt quidem in antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente cauſa Meritum, ſed Imperſonaliter:</hi> From hence then we muſt diſtinguiſh, there is a double Merit of Puniſhment, <hi>Perſonal</hi> and <hi>Imperſonal.</hi> When <hi>Grotius</hi> tells us, that in Chriſts ſufferings there was truly <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> becauſe that, though God laid it on his Son, our ſins required the infliction; and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſays, no <hi>formal proper</hi> Puniſhment, becauſe not only without deſert in Chriſt, but which is more, becauſe our deſert could not be transferr'd on him, though the Puniſhment was, they both ſay true, (but rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood only) the one <hi>Perſonaliter,</hi> the other <hi>Imperſonaliter,</hi> as <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> hath decided it.</p>
            <p>And what is this in good earneſt any other but what the Biſhop hath in effect determined likewiſe? <hi>No Man can deſerve that another ſhould be puniſhed for him, and yet becauſe the Execution of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment depends on the wiſdom of God, a Change of Perſons</hi> (that is, of Chriſt to bear it in our room, Chriſt being willing, and the thing juſt) <hi>may intervene,</hi> ſays the Biſhop, in more words, and all appoſite. If Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> then can but reconcile the Biſhop to himſelf, (unto whom he ſeems heartily to ſubſcribe) he muſt reconcile
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:94667:33"/>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and <hi>Grotius,</hi> and be alſo reconciled to both. And that he may be ſo the more eaſily, the Biſhop hath given a Teſt for the diſcovery of the <hi>Orthodox</hi> from the <hi>Socinian,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſhall thereby be tryed. <hi>The true Controverſie</hi> (ſays he) <hi>between the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian and us, is, Whether the Sufferings of Chriſt were to be conſidered as a Puniſhment for our ſins, and as a Propitiatory Sacrifice to God for them: or only as an Act of Dominion over an innocent Perſon, in order to his Advancement to Glory.</hi> The ſame is affirmed after him by our <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Brethren, and who is there can imagine ever Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> denied that Chriſts ſufferings was a Puniſhment for our ſins, and his death a Propitiatory Sacrifice, for them? <hi>He hath made him ſin for us,</hi> ſays <hi>Paul</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.) Upon which, <hi>God hath made Chriſt a Sacrifice for ſin,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> as others, which <hi>Socinus</hi> denies. <hi>Who his own ſelf bare our ſins in his own Body, on the Tree,</hi> ſays <hi>Peter,</hi> (1 Pet. 2.24.) Upon which, <hi>It was the puniſhment of our ſins, which as a Sacrifice, he bare in his ſufferings on the Croſs,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> But what need I quote any ſuch particular Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, when there is no Book of his that is great, that can be without ſuch a Teſtimony, over and over?</p>
            <p>What then you may ask, ſhall we judge here of Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s great Induſtry? Shall we look on him as the Fly upon the Axle-tree, that hath raiſed all this Duſt for nothing? I will not ſay ſo, ſeeing Duſt there is, that muſt be raiſed, if our Wheels do but go, and our Chariot drive to its deſigned end, the quiet of the Brethren. It is not enough that we are agreed indeed in this Doctrine of Chriſts <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> though we are, unleſs we alſo underſtand and know it: Beſides that when we are agreed, there is need of ſome Anthority yet to tell us we are ſo, that our ſelves may believe it. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing a Controverſie by Silence, is but covering the Fire, as Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> obſerves, not extinguiſhing it. If the Matter be ſuch, wherein we indeed do agree, the Ventilation of it muſt ſhew us the ſeeming Difference to be nothing, and ſo compel a Concord: If the Matter be ſuch wherein we really diſagree, there is ſtill need of beating it out, that the <hi>Corn</hi> may be diſcovered from the <hi>Chaff,</hi> by the <hi>threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two Points we know among us, both very great P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>ts, and the one made difficult through the Intanglement of it with the Other. One is of Chriſts <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> wherein indeed we differ not: The other is of our <hi>Juſtification,</hi> wherein we do differ; and there are two ways of Explication, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s, and the <hi>Common</hi> Proteſtants. Upon the Account now of this Difference in the <hi>latter</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:94667:34"/>Point, there are many are ſtumbled in their Explication of the <hi>former.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> he has verily given occaſion for an Accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation between the Brethren by his <hi>Appeal</hi> to the Biſhop, as to the Point of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> for ſeeing indeed there is therein no difference, he is like to effect it: But as for the other, of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> is behind, and it will be a harder matter for any to moderate in it. One thing, in his ſtrowing his way hereunto, is to be preparatively conſidered. He has read (I ſuppoſe) <hi>Socinus de Servatore,</hi> as well as <hi>Grotius</hi> upon him, and <hi>Crellius</hi> then againſt <hi>Grotius,</hi> with other <hi>Socinians;</hi> as alſo Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> and other <hi>Antinomians,</hi> and he is not ignorant where the Water ſticks between us and them both. The Socinian accounts Chriſt to be a good Man, that taught us Holy Doctrine, and dyed to bear Teſtimony to the Truth of it, to the end we might believe it, and live according to it, and ſo be ſaved; and upon this account is our Saviour: But as for his dying for our ſins, any otherwiſe than for turning us away from them by his Doctrine and Example, which is making our ſins the <hi>Final</hi> Cauſe of his Death, he underſtands not; when as for the making it the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious</hi> Cauſe of the Sufferings of an innocent Man, and thereby ſatisfactory to the Juſtice of God (he accounting the whole Office of his Prieſthood, that which did not <hi>reſpicere Deum,</hi> but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> not reconciling God to us, but us to God) for the obtaining our Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, this ſeems to theſe Men not reaſonable. On the other hand, the <hi>Antinomian,</hi> upon this Satisfaction as made to God by Chriſts ſufferings, underſtands our ſins to be ſo laid on Chriſt, as that it was not only our <hi>Puniſhment</hi> that he bare, but our <hi>Guilt,</hi> our <hi>Fault</hi> our <hi>Deſert:</hi> And whereas we are apt to ſay this is blaſphemous, becauſe Chriſt hereby is made a ſinner, and the greateſt of Sinners; they ſay No; for this is to ſay but what <hi>Luther,</hi> and our Orthodox Divines have ſaid before them, and there is no hurt in it, underſtanding it only (as they all do) by way of <hi>Imputation.</hi> For as in the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs to us, we are accounted of God <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous as he,</hi> for our <hi>Juſtification;</hi> ſo in the Imputation of our ſins, he is made as <hi>ſinful as we,</hi> for making God <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> This they take up as the Common Doctrine of our former Proteſtants, which Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> will do well to turn over, and examine, whether they who have wrote before <hi>Baxter</hi> among us, do not ordinarily ſay thus. <hi>That our ſins were imputed to Chriſt ſo as to be counted his. That he was not made only a Sacrifice for ſin, but even ſo ſin for us, that is, by Imputation, as we are made his Righteouſneſs. For
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:94667:34"/>ſeeing this is the perpetual rule of Gods Juſtice, that the ſame Soul that ſinneth ſhould dye, how can it ſtand with Gods Juſtice that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer for our ſins, if they were not in ſome ſort annexed to him? The Scripture evidently affirms,</hi> (Iſa. 53.6, 11, 12) <hi>That Chriſt bare not only the puniſhment of our ſins, but our ſins alſo; what aileth then the Jeſuite, ſo boldly to deny, that our ſins are imputed to Chriſt? Seeing then</hi> (again) <hi>the Scripture ſo ſpeaks, why ſhould we doubt to ſpeak as the Scripture does, that Chriſt was for us counted a Sinner or Tranſgreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, yet in himſelf remained Holy, Juſt and Righteous ſtill? So we in Chriſt are verily reputed righteous, though by nature we are Unjuſt and Unrighteous.</hi> This I quote out of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let's Synopſis,</hi> being Paſſages lying near together, (See <hi>Cont.</hi> 19. <hi>of Juſtification</hi>) ſuppoſing the like to be common in others.</p>
            <p>In ſuch Paſſages then as theſe, which we ſhall find in former Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, we ſee no ſuch Diſtinction made, between our <hi>Merit</hi> of the Puniſhment, and the <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> as we now make, with the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> to whom Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> does ſubſcribe. It is eſſential to Puniſhment, that it be inflicted for ſin, but not eſſential that it be inflicted on the party himſelf that ſinned, ſays <hi>Grotius;</hi> and in another place before quoted, that ſin is the cauſe of Puniſhment no otherwiſe but <hi>per modum Meriti.</hi> Now Chriſt having himſelf never ſinned, if the <hi>Merit</hi> of our ſins was not laid upon him together with the <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> how was it <hi>per modum Meriti</hi> that he was puniſhed? Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> knows whether <hi>Crellius</hi> does not urge ſomething to this purpoſe againſt <hi>Grotius,</hi> and if he can ſolve the difficulty, to defend <hi>Grotius,</hi> that which he muſt grant to do it, will defend Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> againſt him. But as for the Antinomian, who ſtands upon this, as no leſs neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> than that <hi>Chriſts Righteouſneſs be ours,</hi> as neceſſary to the Doctrine of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and accounts it to be no other but the Common Opinion of the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> it does appear that ſome bank or bound muſt be ſet to this Sea, leſt the opinion formerly received as <hi>Orthodox</hi> over-flow into <hi>Antinomianiſm;</hi> and I muſt give notice to Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> and thoſe that retain and uphold it, that if they perſiſt, they muſt come thus far, as to ſay that on one ſide the Believer is by Imputation as <hi>righteous as Chriſt himſelf;</hi> and on the other that Chriſt by Imputation is a <hi>ſinner as we,</hi> which to put in Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s words, is that Chriſt was as <hi>compleatly ſinful</hi> as we, and we as <hi>compleatly righteous</hi> as he, wherein, as before, they conceived no hurt, becauſe underſtood by them only by way of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</hi> If Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> will recede from the Common Opinion here, he muſt recede from all thoſe Notions that are concatenated together in the Explication of it.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:94667:35"/>
            <p>And what is meant by this <hi>Imputation,</hi> in the Senſe of our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Proteſtant?</hi> The Imputation of a thing to a Perſon, is the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it his, in regard to our dealing with him. In Gods impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſins to Chriſt, he does account (as they ſay) him to be a ſinner, or them to be his, and does ſo deal with him, in laying our Puniſhment upon him. In Gods imputing to us Chriſts Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he accounts his Righteouſneſs to be ours, and ſo deals with us in juſtifying us by it. So they. But how can God account our ſins to be Chriſts, and his righteouſneſs Ours, when really they are not ſo, and Gods Judgment is according to Truth? They muſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, If by <hi>really</hi> we mean <hi>Phyſically,</hi> it is indeed impoſſible that our Qualities ſhould become Chriſts, and his ours; there is none that underſtands it ſo: but if by <hi>really</hi> we mean only <hi>legally, in ſenſu forenſi, in conſpectu fori,</hi> or in Law-ſenſe, as Divines expreſs it, it is really ſo (they will ſay) that our ſins are laid on Chriſt, and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs made ours, or elſe that neither could <hi>Chriſt</hi> have <hi>ſuffered,</hi> or <hi>We</hi> be <hi>juſtified.</hi> But what yet is this <hi>Legally,</hi> or in <hi>Law-ſenſe,</hi> which is to be conceived by a <hi>Quatenus,</hi> as God deals with us <hi>according to Law?</hi> Why our Divines ſuppoſe that Chriſt did take on him our Perſon, and ſo our Sins, and as acting in our Perſon, what he did and ſuffered in our behalf, is accounted of God to be done and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by us, even as what my Attorney at Law does for me, it is in Law, or as I am to be dealt with according to Law, all one as if it were done by me. Here then we muſt make a ſtand, and conſider whether <hi>Chriſt</hi> indeed was ſuch a <hi>Repreſentative,</hi> as that in him as our <hi>Legal</hi> or <hi>Civil</hi> Perſon, we are accounted of God to have ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the Law, both in Obedience to the Precept, and bearing the Puniſhment, ſo as to be perfectly righteous, in his Righteouſneſs, and accordingly juſtified. We muſt come thus home, or ſay nothing.</p>
            <p>There is another Explication therefore that is made of this <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> by Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> There is a double ſenſe of it. There is an Imputation, or accounting a thing to a Perſon as his, either <hi>in ſe,</hi> or in the <hi>Effect.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> denies not Imputation, but explains it. An Imputation of our ſins to Chriſt, and his righteouſneſs to us in this Law ſenſe mentioned, is the <hi>Imputation in ſe,</hi> which as the former commonly received Doctrine, and unſound, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owns: But an Imputation in regard to the <hi>Effects,</hi> that the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, being truly the Meritorious Cauſe of our Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Juſtification, Adoption is imputed (<hi>imputatur datur adjudicatur,</hi> ſays he) to us, as the price given to the Victor, is imputed to the Captive in his Deliverance, is that which he ſays, with <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:94667:35"/>
               <hi>Grotius</hi> (I'll add <hi>Forbes modeſtae Queſtiones</hi>) he does maintain. <hi>Meth. The.</hi> Part 3. P. 54. The Scholaſtically Learned and Induſtrious Mr. <hi>Wotton,</hi> has this Diſtinction in other words; for ſpeaking of Chriſts being <hi>made ſin,</hi> and Chriſts righteouſneſs ours, he tells us, it muſt be underſtood not <hi>Formaliter,</hi> but <hi>Effectivè.</hi> This is all one as not <hi>in ſe,</hi> but in the <hi>Effects.</hi> Thus our ſins are imputed to Chriſt in his bearing only the Puniſhment, when by an Imputation <hi>in ſe,</hi> or <hi>formaliter,</hi> he muſt bear the merit alſo: And thus ſhall Chriſts Righteouſneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ours <hi>(Effectivè)</hi> though we are but <hi>Meritoriouſly,</hi> and not <hi>Formally</hi> juſtified by it.</p>
            <p>As for Reaſons againſt <hi>Imputation</hi> in the Common Senſe before mentioned, to wit, that God does not look on us to have obeyed and ſuffered in Chriſt as our <hi>Legal Perſon,</hi> and what follows, there are ſo many in Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Books, that I need not bring any; Only one, among the other <hi>Antinomian</hi> Conſequences, I will men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as what is moſt obvious and convincing, which is, that if this were ſo, then ſhould the Elect be immediately freed from Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and immediately juſtified, before they believed or repented, or without Faith and Repentance, for no terms could be impoſed on them, in order to their Juſtification and Glory, if they be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted already to have fulfilled the Law in Chriſt. This being a Doctrine therefore ſo directly, as dangerouſly contrary to the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> it is to be diſcarded.</p>
            <p>And yet for once I will thus argue, and call Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> to hearken to me. There is nothing can be imputed to us, but either that which we have not, and then it is imputed that we may have it, that is, to have it made ours, or reputed as ours: <hi>Or</hi> elſe if we have it, it muſt be imputed to ſome other <hi>end</hi> than to have it, or for ſome other <hi>thing</hi> than that it ſelf, which is imputed. Now if Chriſt did obey and ſuffer in our Perſons, or as our Legal Perſon, ſo as in <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe</hi> we have, and are accounted to have obeyed and ſuffered in him, then can his Righteouſneſs (conſiſting of his Obedience and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings) be neither imputed to us, that we may have it, or to be made ours, or reckoned to us as ours, ſeeing we have it already, It is ours, it is reckoned as ours, in that it was performed in our Perſons: Nor can it be imputed to us to any other <hi>end,</hi> or for any other <hi>thing,</hi> but <hi>Ad Juſtitiam,</hi> for Righteouſneſs, (juſtifying Righteouſnes) which is to the <hi>ſame end</hi> and for the <hi>ſame thing,</hi> and can be no other. Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> here is a Man of Senſe, and can ſee Reaſon, and of Ingenuity (if any other be) ſo as if it convince him, to acknowledge it. If he keep to the Common Opinion he cann't Anſwer to <hi>Socinus.</hi> There can
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:94667:36"/>be no Imputation upon this account, of Chriſts Righteouſneſs to any. But if he come off, and ſay Chriſt ſuffered not for us, in the Senſe of <hi>in our Perſon,</hi> ſo as in <hi>Law-ſenſe,</hi> we muſt be reckoned to have ſuffered and ſatisfied in him, but ſuffered for us, in our <hi>ſtead,</hi> in the ſenſe only, as to ſave us from ſuffering, then is there room for an Imputation of his Satisfaction to us, that it may be made ours, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to us as ours, which otherwiſe is Chriſts only. But how then ours, or accounted ours? Not ours <hi>in ſe,</hi> (for that brings us back to having ſatisfied <hi>in his Perſon</hi>) but ours in the <hi>Effects.</hi> This, as I take it, is a matter of deep Conſideration: I appeal to Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s, as well as to Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s, own impartial Judgment.</p>
            <p>One thing remains, as yet not ſuggeſted by any other. I have intimated that the entanglement of the two Points, [<hi>Satisfaction</hi> and <hi>Juſtification</hi>] in our diſcourſing of them one with another, does give occaſion of clouding them, and that it will be an edifying matter to endeavour to ſever them ſo, by putting a right difference between them, in relation to the Controverſie, as we may bring ſome light that will clear our Underſtandings in the Doctrine of them both. To this end then let us know, that when the Scripture rells us of Chriſts dying for us, and bearing our ſins, with the like Expreſſions, and we are agreed againſt the Socinians, that what Chriſt did and ſuffered for us, was not only <hi>bono noſtro,</hi> but <hi>loco noſtro,</hi> in our ſtead, our room, our place: Here is the thing I offer to Conſideration, that what is done by Chriſt <hi>loco noſtro,</hi> muſt be applied to his making God <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for us, not to the Point of our <hi>Juſtification.</hi> For explaining this, let us farther know (as ſignified before) that to do or ſuffer any thing in anothers ſtead or room, is to do or ſuffer it to ſave the other from doing or ſuffering. Now in the Point of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> there is nothing that we do, or is required of us to do in order to make it, or procure it to be made, ſo that what was done or ſuffered, in order thereunto, muſt certainly be in our room or ſtead, we being perfectly free from doing or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering our ſelves any thing towards it: But as for the Point of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification,</hi> it is as certain that there is our Duty required, our Faith and Repentance, and ſincere Walking in order to it, and there is nothing done or ſuffered by Chriſt, that frees us from it. It is true, that the perfect Obedience of Chriſt to the Law of Works, is to be accounted (in my apprehenſion, I have ſaid) to be perform'd in our place, ſtead, or room (and not only in regard to his own Perſon as <hi>Juſtitia perſonae</hi>) becauſe we are freed we know from that Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, as the Condition of Life, which we were by nature under,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:94667:36"/>and that therefore his Obedience, as well as Sufferings, I do account, does go into his <hi>Satisfaction:</hi> But as for that Evangelical Obedience that is required of us, our believing, our repenting in order to our Pardon and <hi>Juſtification,</hi> there is nothing done by Chriſt in the room of it. The fulfilling the Law by Chriſt (which he did both in regard to the Precept and Sanction) was in our room, place or ſtead, in order to his <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> but his fulfilling the Law was not in our place, ſtead or room, in order to our <hi>Juſtification.</hi> It was <hi>in order to it,</hi> for obtaining Pardon and Juſtification upon the Goſpel Conditions; but it was not <hi>in our room, place or ſtead,</hi> in order to it. Whether in ſaying this, I ſay ſomething to the purpoſe, or no, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the Judicious Biſhop. Only I muſt add thus much, that this is that which (in effect) I have ſaid in former Books, ſpeaking to that <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> which Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> hath ſtood ſo much upon, and now Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> that it is to be acknowledged, as to the <hi>Impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> but not to go into the <hi>Application</hi> of our Redemption.</p>
            <p>The Death of Chriſt muſt be <hi>loco noſtro,</hi> as it is the <hi>paying</hi> the price, the making <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and ſo the <hi>impetrating</hi> the Benefits we have by it; but it can be onely <hi>bono noſtro,</hi> as to any <hi>Benefit</hi> it ſelf, which is all one as <hi>bono noſtro</hi> only <hi>in the Application.</hi> Pray ſee <hi>Pacif.</hi> P. 30, 31, 32. Upon which words (Repeated, <hi>Right. of God.</hi> P. 35, 36.) I have deſired Mr. <hi>William</hi>'s, and Mr. <hi>Clark</hi>'s, and now beg the Biſhop's fuller Conſideration.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Arminians</hi> upon the Point of <hi>Satisfaction</hi> are cautious in what they grant, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is in both, and they will have Chriſts ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings to be a Vice-puniſhment, or <hi>Vicarious Puniſhment,</hi> rather than a proper and formal Puniſhment: Which Expreſſion ought not to offend Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> nor any worthy Perſon, becauſe when the Scripture ſays, Chriſt <hi>died for us,</hi> and we underſtand by <hi>[for us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>] Vice noſtri.</hi> in our room or ſtead, the Death or Puniſhment it ſelf muſt be in our ſtead, that is, a <hi>Vicarious Puniſhment,</hi> how can it be otherwiſe? And becauſe there is nothing can be urged more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally againſt the Doctrine of <hi>Socinus</hi> than this, that the Juſtice of God requiring a Puniſhment to be inflicted, according to his Law for our breaking it, God was contented or ſatisfied with a <hi>Vicarious Puniſhment,</hi> inflicting one (though not all that was in the <hi>Obligation</hi>) on his Son. The Puniſhment in this ſenſe being <hi>Vicarious,</hi> the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious Cauſe, our ſins are accordingly ſaid <hi>Pro-meritorious, loco cauſae meritoriae,</hi> or an <hi>Aſſumed</hi> Meritorious Cauſe, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> before, and the infliction as Perſonal, be <hi>Materially</hi> not <hi>Formally</hi> Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. If this offends any, when ſaid by <hi>Epiſcopius, Curcellaeus,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:94667:37"/>Limborch,</hi> whom they ſuſpect as favouring <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> it o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n when ſaid by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> whom none can ſuſpect. Nay, though there be ſome <hi>Socinians</hi> who, under ſuch Expreſſions, do ſhelter themſelves, and by appearing Orthodox, ſeduce others (which may raiſe ſome zeal in Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> againſt them, not conſidering their end and ours in ſuch Expreſſions, theirs being (as hinted before) at laſt to <hi>deny,</hi> ours to <hi>own</hi> Satisfaction): Yet is not this ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude againſt the ſame, becauſe there is more of <hi>Antidote</hi> than <hi>Danger</hi> by them. For ſeeing all proper Puniſhment is for ſin, and ſin cauſes Puniſhment (as hath been ſaid) by way of <hi>Merit,</hi> and no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the <hi>Merit</hi> of our ſins, as well as our ſins in the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> muſt be laid on Chriſt, or elſe it is no <hi>proper Puniſhment,</hi> and if the Merit of our ſins as well as the Puniſhment, be granted to be laid on Chriſt, we are then ingulph'd into <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> according to this excellent <hi>Biſhop,</hi> the worthy Dr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf aſſenting to them, and what Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> hath to ſay to this, he muſt conſider.</p>
            <p>The Caſe therefore being this, that either we muſt admit that our ſins in the <hi>Merit,</hi> were laid on Chriſt as well as the <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> or elſe that Chriſts ſufferings was no <hi>proper formal Puniſhment:</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> will rather fall in with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> than Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> and yield in ſome ſenſe at leaſt, that it was no <hi>proper</hi> Puniſhment, which is verily true, as <hi>proper</hi> is oppoſed to <hi>Vicarious,</hi> for a Vicarious Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment it was for certain, being inflicted on Another, and not the Perſon or Perſons that ſinned, and being alſo not the <hi>ſame</hi> (for that ſhould have been <hi>Hell</hi> to them) but an <hi>Equivalent,</hi> that ſo it might be <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> not <hi>Payment,</hi> which would preclude Remiſſion: And ſeeing it was not the ſame infliction, nor inflicted on the ſinner himſelf, the Obligation to undergo it, could not ariſe from the Law, which puniſhes only the Tranſgreſſor of it, and conſequently, tho' <hi>Materially,</hi> yet <hi>Formally</hi> was not Puniſhment as laid on the innocent Perſon of Chriſt. All this Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſays, and it muſt be ſaid as true, plain, undeniable: and nevertheleſs there being a Puniſhment due to us for our ſins, and our ſins the Meritorious Cauſe of it, and the Obligation to the ſuffering it, ariſing from the Law as broken by us, here is conſequently a <hi>proper formal Puniſhment</hi> to be inflicted <hi>Imperſonally,</hi> as <hi>Grotius</hi> before. And it being not againſt the Juſtice of God to take this Puniſhment Imperſonally conſidered, and lay it either on Another, or the Perſon or Perſons that ſinned, ſo long as no diſhonour to his <hi>Law,</hi> nor prejudice to his <hi>Government</hi> comes thereby, Severity being ſhewen againſt <hi>ſin,</hi> as pitty to the <hi>ſinner,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:94667:37"/>and Chriſt Jeſus being willing to take on him the Puniſhment (no wrong being done to the willing) it being his Fathers and his Own Appointment, that he who was the Second Perſon in the Trinity, ſhould become Man, to be a fit Perſon for the Work, it pleaſed God and him, that he did actually take on him this Puniſhment, in ſuch a manner as he was capable of it, (that is, not in regard to the <hi>Merit,</hi> or that he ſhould be held longer than he was under it) and ſuitable to ſuch a Perſon (which made his Temporal ſuffering an <hi>Equivalent</hi>) ſo that by enduring the ſame in our behalf, <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> was made, and God thereupon relaxes his Law of Works, by paſſing a New Law, or remedying Law of Grace, whereby Deliverance and Life, Pardon and Salvation is to be had on the Terms of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>This is that Doctrine, which whoſoever imbraces, be he <hi>Arminian</hi> or <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> let him be <hi>Epiſcopius</hi> or <hi>Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> or Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> it is all one for that: Bring us the Teſt, let us ſee their Books, and if we find in them a conſtant acknowledgment that the ſufferings of Chriſt was <hi>a Puniſhment for our ſins, and a Propitiatory Sacrifice to God for them,</hi> let them differ as they will in accuracy, we are at Unity in the Point. Only let not any one that is more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate about it, deſpiſe him that is leſs accurate, nor he that is leſs accurate be ſcandalized at him that is more accurate, and cautious, leſt by denying or contradicting what is reaſonable to be granted, he ſhould harden the Adverſary, and blunt his own Faith: Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, that be he as cautious as he can, he will hardly be out of danger of one of the Extreams, and alſo that (as I humbly think) he muſt however be more accurate than to go the Common way of the ordinary Proteſtant, or by avoiding the extream of <hi>Socinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm</hi> on one hand, he will fall into <hi>Antinomianiſm</hi> on the other, into which many are already fallen that diſclaim it.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, The ſufferings of Chriſt may be conſidered <hi>Perſonally,</hi> in Relation to himſelf; or <hi>Imperſonally,</hi> in relation to us. <hi>Perſonally,</hi> in relation to himſelf, there being no Merit of his own, and no Merit of ours imputable to that Holy Perſon, his ſufferings could not be formally Penal: <hi>Imperſonally,</hi> in relation to us, the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being in our room, was <hi>ours,</hi> and conſequently muſt be a formal proper Puniſhment, and this <hi>Commutation</hi> only, thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued, is enough for the explaining and upholding the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet again, that this Buſineſs, this difficult Buſineſs, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and <hi>Grotius,</hi> be diſpatched, and thoroughly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:94667:38"/>diſpatch'd, I muſt ſay this over. Here is <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> and deſerved Puniſhment, deſerved by our ſins as the Meritorious Cauſe of it, and therefore Puniſhment, not <hi>Pain</hi> only, but proper <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> and that to be inflicted <hi>ſed Imperſonaliter,</hi> with <hi>Grotius,</hi> and there is our Point maintained: But that this Puniſhment is inflicted on Chriſt and not on the ſinner, there is no <hi>Cauſe</hi> (beſides the fitneſs of the Perſon) can be rendred but only the <hi>will,</hi> the good will of Father and Son in pitty to Mankind, which is ſaid alſo by <hi>Grotius,</hi> and (in effect) acknowledged by the Biſhop, when he ſays, That <hi>One Man for his ſin cannot deſerve anothers Puniſhment;</hi> and therefore when Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſays, our ſins were the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of Chriſts ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, with thoſe other Expreſſions, the Occaſion, and Occaſion only, but of what the Occaſion only? Of the Puniſhment? No, (there was Cauſe of that, an Impulſive Cauſe, that is, an Efficient Protatarctick or Meritorious Cauſe, to wit, our ſins) but of the laying it on Chriſt, and not us; take it ſo, and there is nothing to be found fault with in what Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſays, (unleſs it be that his deeper Judgment than others (I have ſaid) be faulty) by Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> or any other ingenuous Man, any more than there was in what <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> ſays, by <hi>Revenſperg,</hi> who falls upon him as Socinianizing againſt the Orthodox; becauſe he did not maintain, that Chriſt underwent the very infernal Pains which we were to ſuffer, ſeeing <hi>Calvin,</hi> and ſome others after him, did ſo teach and conſtrue Chriſts <hi>deſcent into Hell,</hi> by his enduring ſuch Pains in his Agony, as thoſe are there, which is a private Opinion, and <hi>Grotius</hi> accounts Chriſts ſufferings not the <hi>Idem,</hi> but <hi>Tantundem;</hi> and thereupon (I ſay) did <hi>Raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperg</hi> fall upon him, as one that did but betray our Cauſe, and agree with <hi>Socinus</hi> (which he hath ſo ſubſtantially defended againſt him) in his excellent Book of <hi>Satisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There remains two or three Notes more, I muſt have upon Mr. <hi>Lobb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One is, that whereas he obſerves, that Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> does make the Obligation that lay upon Chriſt to ſuffer for us, or to make Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction by his ſufferings to ariſe from the <hi>Mediatorial Law</hi> only, the Law of <hi>Redemption,</hi> or <hi>Commandment of his Father,</hi> which was <hi>proper</hi> to him, through his voluntary Sponſion or Submiſſion to it, and not from the <hi>Law of Works</hi> which was a Bond that he never was in, neither at <hi>firſt,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> grants, nor at <hi>laſt,</hi> in regard to his ſufferings, becauſe he never brake it, he argues from thence both <hi>ſagaciouſly</hi> as <hi>induſtriouſly,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> muſt hold therefore with Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> that the ſufferings of Chriſt was not <hi>properly</hi> or
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:94667:38"/>
               <hi>formally penal,</hi> and when this is the only Accuſation in theſe Sheets, which he aims at, if Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> denies the Accuſation, Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> hath carried his Cauſe, for the Accuſation is true, the Conſequence being irrefragible. But will Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> deny that he herein agrees with Mr. <hi>Baxter?</hi> I ſuppoſe he will not. What, though Dr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> by whoſe Letters he is vindicated, do ſay that Chriſts ſufferings were a <hi>proper Puniſhment,</hi> and ſtand upon it ſo much, as if the holding thereof was neceſſary to the maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction</hi> (if Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> be not miſtaken in his Conſtruction of them) will he for all that ſtand by Mr. <hi>Baxter?</hi> Yes: I think he will, becauſe he muſt, the Conſequence does hold him. I muſt confeſs, Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> hath put theſe three Perſons here hard to it. He hath put Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> to it, who muſt either forſake Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and ſo himſelf, or elſe diſagree here with thoſe two worthy Men, his Vindicators. He hath put the <hi>Biſhop</hi> to it, who muſt forſake his Reaſon in what he hath ſo clearly and truly aſſerted, That <hi>one Man cannot deſerve that another ſhould be puniſhed for his Faults,</hi> or elſe he muſt conſent with Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and conſequently acknowledge, that ſeeing Chriſt himſelf never ſinned, and our ſins in the Merit of them, could not be laid on him, his ſufferings were <hi>Materially,</hi> but <hi>Formally</hi> no Puniſhment. And he hath put the worthy Dr. to it, who being willing to ſhew his kindneſs to Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> in bringing him off, is carried, whether he will or no, to ſtand by Mr. <hi>Lobb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding this, there is no hurt done, unleſs the giving occaſion of letting out more Light be any hurt, for Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> as well as Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> Dr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>Grotius</hi> do all maintain the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction</hi> againſt <hi>Socinus,</hi> one as well as the other. That Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> does, the Doctor, the Biſhop, and his Preabyterian Brethren, do quote ſuch Paſſages as juſtifies him, beſides his own conſtant Profeſſion. That Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> does, I ſhall quote one Paſſage only in his <hi>Methodus Theol.</hi> In his <hi>Aphoriſms</hi> he propoſed the Queſtion, (as I remember) What is that which is the firſt immediate, or chief End or Benefit of Chriſts Death? And he ſpeaking then with Heſitancy, he does here (in his 17th <hi>Determination,</hi> Part 3. Cap. 1.) after ſo long ſtudy give this peremptory Reſolution, <hi>Proximum mortis Chriſti Effectum ſeu finem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſſe ſatisfactionem Deo offenſo per Juſtitiae ejus demonſtrationem: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motiorem, peccatorum nostrorum remiſſionem &amp; ſalutis donum ſub con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditione fideist paenitentiae per foedus Gratiae.</hi> That Man who underſtood himſelf ſo well as he did, that does declare this for his ſettled and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:94667:39"/>Judgment, that the chief and moſt immediate End, Effect Fruit or Benefit of Chriſts Death, is <hi>the ſatisfaction of an Offended God, through the demonſtration of his Juſtice</hi> thereby, muſt be acquitted from <hi>Socintaniſm,</hi> by all the World that know what <hi>Socinus</hi> wrote: And that Man (I will add) that does maintain the Doctrine of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection,</hi> according to <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and the <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Dort,</hi> however free and conciliating he be otherwiſe in the <hi>five Points,</hi> muſt be acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alſo from <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> by all thoſe that know what <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Epiſcopius, Curcelleus, Limborch</hi> and the <hi>Antiſynodaliſts</hi> have wrote. And therefore I do acknowledge here the Honeſty, that is, Truth and Candour, of Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> in his Epiſtle, where he diſcharges Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> from ſuch Accuſations; and though he looks in his Sheets like one that read Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> only to carp and find fault with him, (when in my Reading the ſame things, I muſt confeſs I did look, and do ſtill, on all as light and Inſtruction) I do yet, for all that apprehend and hope a better end in it, to wit, that upon his propoſing theſe Expreſſions to ſuch worthy and ingenuous Perſons, as the <hi>Doctor</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> he may, by their return, in time have ſuch a moderated and ſmoothed State of the whole Matter (they taking in the light Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> offers with them) as ſhall be reconciliatory both to himſelf, and to his Brethren with him.</p>
            <p>If by Chriſts dying for us, and for our ſins, there is nothing will ſerve the <hi>Common Doctrine</hi> (which is that Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> upholds, in the behalf of his Brethren, reſerving, I will ſuppoſe, the Liberty of following Truth hereafter whereſoever he finds it) but this, that God did look on Chriſt, as appearing in our Perſon, and ſo judged and condemned him for a ſinner, as one (I ſay, being in our Perſon) that deſerved his Wrath and Curſe, and therefore laid it on him, whereby our full and proper Puniſhment was Born, the Law Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and Juſtice Done: and if any will add with <hi>Ravenſperg</hi> farther, that the torments of Hell in his <hi>Agony</hi> and Suffering on the Croſs, when he cried, <hi>Eli, Eli, lamaſabacthani,</hi> were laid on his Soul, that nothing of the very Puniſhment may be abated him, who does not ſee that ſuch a ſatisfaction is ſo ſtrait laced, as will not fit the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt, and that ſuch Divines do more to drive Men to <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> than <hi>Socinus</hi> himſelf could, while they ſtand upon ſuch a <hi>Satisfaction</hi> as no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Man can<note n="*" place="margin">Vera ſatisfactio eſt plen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deliti perſolutio: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nuſquiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> noſtram mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem aternam divinae iſti juſtitiae debelat, <hi>ſays</hi> Socinus. De Ser. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> receive.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:94667:39"/>
            <p>And whereas Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> therefore, and other ſuch more conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſons, do ſee a neceſſity to come off, and allow that it was not and could not be our <hi>very Puniſhment it ſelf,</hi> it being enough that Chriſt was ſurrogated under the <hi>Primordial Nature</hi> of the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhment (to uſe his words) though not under the horrid <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,</hi> we our ſelves were to ſuffer; and does yield moreover, that though the <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> yet the <hi>Deſert</hi> of our ſins could not be laid on Chriſt, (becauſe that would run him into <hi>Antinomianiſm</hi>) which Conceſſions do draw after them ſuch other ſuitable Notions, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> offers; ſo that at laſt we muſt come to this, that the Ends of Gods Law and Government being ſecured, it muſt be left to the Wiſdom of the Father and Son to agree upon what <hi>ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> pleaſed them, for demonſtrating Divine <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> againſt Sin, and <hi>Mercy</hi> toward the Sinner, and that be ſufficient for us to believe. For, I muſt add, that ſo long as we agree in our belief, that Chriſts Death was a <hi>Ranſom</hi> for our Redemption, and a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for our Sins, in the Senſe of the Types of old, where the ſin of the Sacrificer was laid on the Beaſt, and the Blood thereof an Expiation for it, to the end he might be forgiven it; what matter is it tho' one holds this Death to be <hi>Formally,</hi> another only <hi>Materially</hi> our <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> or that one ſays, our ſins were the <hi>proper Meritorious Cauſe,</hi> and the other the <hi>Remote Cauſe</hi> or <hi>Occaſion</hi> of it, they both hold it <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and intend the maintaining the Doctrine thereof.</p>
            <p>Proper Puniſhment is an infliction of a Natural Evil on a Perſon, for Committing a Moral Evil: But Chriſt that endured the Natural Evil, never committed any Moral Evil, and how can that be proper Puniſhment? The Puniſhment laid on him, was not due to him, but to us: The Puniſhment d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to us was <hi>Hell,</hi> but his Sufferings only <hi>Temporal Death:</hi> Is not here then one Puniſhment in the room of another, as one Perſon ſuffering in the room of another? And what Legerdemain can cover the Eye of any, as not to ſee this a <hi>Vicari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Puniſhment?</hi> Again, when all proper Puniſhment is for ſin, as the Meritorious Cauſe of it, and Chriſt ſinned not, and our ſins cannot (according to the <hi>Biſhop</hi>) deſerve that another ſhould be puniſhed for them; ſo that here is Puniſhment without Deſert; how is this <hi>proper Formal</hi> Puniſhment? The Law by vertue of its Sanction, puniſhes none but the Breakers of the Preceptive Part, and how then can theſe ſufferings ariſe <hi>Ex obligatione-Legis?</hi> If they did ariſe from the Obligation of the Law, then was the Law executed in Chriſts ſuffering, but Chriſt ſuffered that the Law might not be executed, but the Penitent Believing Sinner be pardoned.— I might go on and offer other
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:94667:40"/>Poſitions, according to what is ſaid by Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Eighteenth Deterininations</hi> (<hi>Math. Theol.</hi> Part 3. Cap. 1. before quoted) and Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> the Dr, or Biſhop, may as well deny that two and three makes five, as fundamentally to deny any of them, and therefore I ſhall forbear more, being come already to the Compoſition which <hi>Grotius,</hi> in that one word before, hath made for us. <hi>Imperſonaliter</hi> theſe ſufferings as due to us, may be ſaid to be <hi>properly, formally, Puniſhment,</hi> Puniſhment for ſin, as the Meritorious Cauſe of it, Puniſhment ariſing from the Obligation of the Law, upon our break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, puniſhment that was the Curſe of the Law, and which he bare, when if we had our ſelves born it, it had been the Execution of the Law, the Execution whereof theſe Divines, who are for the Common Doctrine, apprehending (as <hi>Socinus</hi>) to be <hi>proper Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> (wherein they are perfectly out, for that, according to the Schools, is contrary to it) it makes them ſo extream, as before mentioned, in their Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> as no Man unprejudiced can abide it: But <hi>Perſonaliter,</hi> on the other hand, as theſe ſufferings are laid upon Chriſt, inſtead of us (that is, <hi>inſtead,</hi> not as in our Perſon, but <hi>inſtead,</hi> that we might eſcape them) they are Nominally and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially</hi> indeed, but they are not, they cannot be <hi>Formally</hi> and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>Penal.</hi> They ariſe not from ſin, as the Metitorious Cauſe, nor from the Obligation of the Law, and are no Execution of it. Why ſhould I go on to ſay the ſame things over and over? I will make bold to conclude with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> againſt any, if there be any that think they have more ſagacity herein than he, to oppoſe him, and ſay, As the Perſon that ſuffered was <hi>loco noſtri,</hi> the ſufferings were <hi>loco paenae,</hi> our ſins <hi>loco cauſae meritoriae,</hi> his Sponſion <hi>loco obligationis ex Lege,</hi> an <hi>Equivalent loco Debiti,</hi> and <hi>loco ſolutionis</hi> here is at laſt effected <hi>proper Satisfaction.</hi> Let Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries be who they will, and let them do what they can, they ſhall never make more of it.</p>
            <p>Another thing which Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> obſerves of Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> that I muſt alſo take notice of, is this. As he does hold, that the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which lay on Chriſt to do as he did, aroſe altogether from the <hi>Mediatorial Law;</hi> ſo does he hold that the Righteouſneſs which conſiſts in his Performance of that Law, is that which is imputed to the Believer for his Juſtification, wherein there does manifeſtly appear that ſlip of Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> which I have before mentioned, for ſeeing that <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> thereof, did belong only, or was proper to the <hi>Mediator,</hi> it is impoſſible it ſhould be imputed otherwiſe to us, than in the <hi>Effects,</hi> which when Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaw
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:94667:40"/>and aſſerted; and Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> does follow him in what he ſays elſe, and yet leaves him in this: I cannot but give him again friendly Warning to retract that ſlip, for otherwiſe the whole Doctrine he is engaged in, which he hath <hi>knit</hi> together out of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and endeavours to maintain by this one <hi>Stitch let fall</hi> (if it be not amended) muſt <hi>unravel,</hi> and come to nothing. The Argument I have uſed in my <hi>Pacification,</hi> (Pag. 40.) which Book I expected to have been anſwered by him, or the Truth (as to what concerns him) acknowledged, before this.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing I will Note in Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> is, <hi>Though a righteouſneſs</hi> (he ſays) <hi>which Anſwers the Obligation</hi> (in the plural, that is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both of the Preceptive and Comminatory Part) <hi>of the violated Law of Works, be neceſſary to our Juſtification, yet we are not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Law, becauſe we did it not our ſelves as the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired;</hi> but by the <hi>Goſpel</hi> he apprehends, in that the Goſpel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides us ſuch a Righteouſneſs (that is, Chriſts Righteouſneſs, made ours by Faith) as anſwers the Law, that we may be juſtified. Here is that apprehended, which is as clearly thought, as any one that will maintain the Common Doctrine can ſpeak: but I muſt Anſwer him, That if the Goſpel muſt provide us ſuch a Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as anſwers the Law, that we may be juſtified by it, then muſt that neceſſarily preſuppoſe, that it is by the Law we are to be judged: but when indeed that is not ſo, for if it be by the Goſpel, and not the <hi>Law</hi> (as himſelf accounts) that we are <hi>juſtified,</hi> it is by the Goſpel we muſt be <hi>judged</hi> (for to be judged is either to be <hi>juſtified</hi> or <hi>condemned</hi>) and accordingly it is not the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> which anſwers the Law that the Goſpel provides for us, but it is <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> that is manifeſted <hi>without the Law,</hi> a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs <hi>revealed in the Goſpel,</hi> in oppoſition to the Works of the Law, that it hath provided, for the Sinners Juſtification.</p>
            <p>To be more full and ſatisfactory, as we draw to an End. The <hi>Law</hi> is ſometimes taken <hi>ſtrictly,</hi> as it requires perfect Obedience to its Precepts, that we may <hi>live in them,</hi> and ſo it is oppoſed to the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> Or it is taken <hi>largly,</hi> for the whole <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which contains Promiſes of Pardon and Life, upon Mens Faith and Repentance, as well as the Goſpel. In the <hi>firſt</hi> Senſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> is manifeſt without the <hi>Law:</hi> In the <hi>ſecond,</hi> that yet it hath <hi>the witneſs of the Law. and the Prophets.</hi> For <hi>Moſes</hi> tells us, that God is <hi>Gracious, Merciful, forgiving Iniquities, Tranſgreſſion and Sin,</hi> and the Prophets call on the People to <hi>Repent, and caſt away their Tranſgreſſions,</hi> that they may <hi>live</hi> and not <hi>die,</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:94667:41"/>which is all one with what the Goſpel Teaches. It is ſtrange now that when this Doctrine of Faith and Repentance, which is ſo plain in both Teſtaments <hi>[The juſt Man ſhall live by his faith]</hi> ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured by the Doctrine of <hi>Imputation,</hi> which is a deviſed Doctrine, not in Scripture; I mean the <hi>Imputation of Christs Righteouſneſs,</hi> in the ſenſe of <hi>per modum formae,</hi> or <hi>formalis cauſae,</hi> when in the ſenſe of <hi>per modum Meriti,</hi> it does but explain and confirm the ſame: Inſomuch as thoſe Scriptures, which are uſually brought for ſuch <hi>Imputation,</hi> do effectually prove the contrary to it. I mean, that it is not <hi>Chriſts Righteouſneſs imputed to us,</hi> but our Faith or Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Righteouſneſs imputed to us, <hi>for Righteouſneſs,</hi> that juſtifies us. This may appear by the Explication of ſuch as theſe Scriptures fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p>The Jews, <hi>being ignorant of Gods Righteouſneſs, and going about to eſtabliſh their own, have not ſubmitted to the Righteouſneſs of God:</hi> That is, not to that way of becoming Righteous, which God hath founded or inſtituted, and ſo declared in the Goſpel, which in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to their <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> is by Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>For Chriſt is the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs, to every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth.</hi> The Law in general was an Inſtruction, in order to the coming of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> that we ſhould believe in him, and obey him when come, and thereby be juſtified and ſaved. So the Apoſtle otherwhere, <hi>Wherefore the</hi> Law <hi>was our School-Maſter unto Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by Faith.</hi> By Chriſts being the <hi>end of the Law</hi> then, we may underſtand, either, The end, or deſign of the <hi>Law,</hi> requiring perfect Obedience, which no Man does or can perform, is to drive us to Chriſt. But how drive us to him? Is it to his Righteouſneſs, to be made ours? No, there is no ſuch thing ſaid any where, but to him for Righteouſneſs, through believing: Or, and for, Chriſt is the end of the Law in that he, by the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his Life and Death, fulfilling the ſame in our behalf, hath freed us from the <hi>Condition</hi> thereof, requiring only our <hi>Faith</hi> inſtead of <hi>That,</hi> and ſo <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> now (or Juſtification) is <hi>to every one</hi> who without the Works of the Law, does perform the Terms of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is no Condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit.</hi> That is, They that are in Chriſt by Faith, and their Faith is ſound, ſo as it cauſes them to walk ſincerely before God, they are freed from Condemnation. <hi>For the</hi> Law <hi>of the Spirit of Life in Jeſus Chriſt, hath made me free
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:94667:41"/>from the Law of Sin and Death.</hi> That is, for the Law of <hi>Grace,</hi> which is the Law of <hi>the Spirit of Life in Chriſt,</hi> doth free ſuch from the <hi>Curſe</hi> of the Law of Works. <hi>For what the Law could not do, in that it was weak through the Fleſh, God ſending his Son in the likeneſs of ſinful Fleſh, and for ſin condemned ſin in the Fleſh.</hi> That is, The Law being not able to free us from Condemnation, or to juſtifie us, ſeeing thro' our Frailty we break it, which elſe would do it, God ſent his Son to take our ſins on him, and by condemning ſin in him, or puniſhing him for them, he hath bereft ſin of its Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natory Power over the Believer. <hi>That the Righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit.</hi> That is, that the Juſtification (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which we ſhould have by the <hi>Law,</hi> if we could perform it, may be had by our performing only the Conditions of the Law of Grace, which is walking not <hi>after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit,</hi> or not after the <hi>Law,</hi> but after the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do we then make void the</hi> Law <hi>by Faith? Yea, we eſtabliſh the Law.</hi> The <hi>Law</hi> taken <hi>largely</hi> (as before) declares Gods Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Sinners Juſtification by Faith and Repentance, as the Goſpel does, and thereby is moſt plainly eſtabliſhed or accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. But to ſay further, The Law is eſtabliſhed (ſays St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>) by the fulfilling it. Now Faith, if it be ſound, does work <hi>by Love,</hi> and <hi>Love is fulfilling the Law.</hi> But how does Faith and Love fulfil it? Not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not in the <hi>Rigour</hi> of it, but the <hi>Equity,</hi> or according to <hi>Acceptation</hi> thro' Chriſt. When God then for Chriſts ſake, does <hi>accept</hi> of our Faith, or our ſincere, though imperfect Obedience, for <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> this is that <hi>julfilling the Law,</hi> which is all that can be in this Earth, and thereby the <hi>eſtabliſhing of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As by one Mans Diſobedience many were made Sinners: ſo by the Obedience of one, ſhall many be made righteous.</hi> This is true, <hi>per modum Meriti,</hi> but not <hi>per modum formae:</hi> To wit, we being all by the Fall of <hi>Adam</hi> become corrupt, ſo that there is, and can be no Righteouſneſs according to the Law of <hi>Works</hi> in the World, the Lord Jeſus by what he hath done, hath procured a Law of <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> thereby, ſo that the ſinner that repents and believes in Chriſt, is by that Law <hi>made righteous,</hi> and enjoys the Benefits as much as if he were as perfectly Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous as the Law requires. In this Senſe we may ſay Chriſts Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is imputed to us, that is, <hi>(per modum meriti)</hi> in the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:94667:42"/>Effects. For as to <hi>impute ſin,</hi> is to inflict puniſhment: So to impute Righteouſneſs is to confer the Priviledges to a Perſon, as belongs to him that is righteous, and ſuch the Believer has, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Life Eternal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He hath made him ſin, that we might be made the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God in him.</hi> The Righteouſneſs of God, is the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Faith; and to be made <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God in him,</hi> is to be made righteous thro' him, by believing; or through his merits, to be juſtified by our Faith. As our ſins are imputed to Chriſt; (which, I ſay, is only in the <hi>effect</hi> of his ſuffering for them) ſo is his Righteouſneſs imputed to us, ſay our Divines. But Chriſt is not made <hi>formally a ſinner</hi> by our ſins: Nor there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we made <hi>formally righteous,</hi> by his Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>I might proceed to other Texts, and then ſhew how upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, though a Diſciple of Chriſt muſt learn to deny himſelf, take up his Croſs and follow him, yet are not his <hi>Commandments grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous,</hi> but his <hi>Yoke eaſie, and Burden light;</hi> Becauſe in that ſweet recumbency, truſt, or reſt which the Soul has upon the goodneſs and mercy of God, for Acceptance of his Performance, though but <hi>Conatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et Deſiderio,</hi> and notwithſtanding all its Imperfection, unto Life, thro' the Merits of Chriſt, there ariſes unſpeakable Conſolation. The true and ſolid Benefit hereof by the other Doctrine, upon an only <hi>pretended ſhew</hi> of more, is Ecclipſed. See <hi>Pacif.</hi> P. 27, 28, 29.</p>
            <p>THE Common Proteſtant Doctrine, is that by the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs, we are juſtified; where the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Matter,</hi> and Gods <hi>Imputation</hi> the <hi>Form</hi> of our Juſtification, <hi>actively</hi> taken; and conſequently <hi>the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed,</hi> the <hi>Form</hi> of it <hi>paſſively</hi> taken. The Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt is the Matter, both of Active and Paſſive Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but the <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Active,</hi> is the Imputation of it, and the <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Paſſive,</hi> is that Righteouſneſs imputed. So it is ſaid in our Proteſtant Schools, <hi>Imputata Chriſti Obedientia eſt formalis cauſae noſtrae. Juſtificationis:</hi> My Opinion now is different, that it is not by the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> but by the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> imputed to us, that we are juſtified. The Righteouſneſs of God is the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Faith,</hi> and Faith, or the Evangelick Condition performed is the <hi>Matter;</hi> and the Imputation of this Faith for Righteouſneſs, is the Form of our Juſtification. <hi>Faith</hi> is oppoſed to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:94667:42"/>
               <hi>Works,</hi> and the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Faith</hi> (or Righteouſneſs of God) oppoſed to the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Works.</hi> Faith then cannot be taken <hi>Objectivè</hi> for Chriſts Righteouſneſs, becauſe Chriſts Righteouſneſs is not oppoſed to, but is it ſelf a Righteouſneſs of Works. It is not Chriſts Righteouſneſs then is that which is imputed to the Believer for Righteouſneſs; (that is to be his formal Righteouſneſs) but it is that for the ſake of which (or the meritorious Cauſe for which) Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is imputed to him upon his believing. I deny not with Mr. <hi>B.</hi> an Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs to a Believer, tho' there be no text for't, but I with him explain it. Our Explication is, that it is imputed no otherwiſe to us for our <hi>Juſtification,</hi> than for our <hi>Salvation,</hi> and other purchaſed Benefits. This is what we intend by an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, not <hi>in ſe,</hi> but in the <hi>Effects;</hi> and that is to ſay, <hi>imputed per modum meriti</hi> only. To be imputed in the <hi>Effects</hi> only, and not <hi>in ſe,</hi> Note it at laſt, is in the full meaning this, that the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt is the <hi>Meritorious</hi> Cauſe, but not the <hi>Formal</hi> Cauſe of our Juſtification, and that does determine all Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, with the truly underſtanding.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:94667:43"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX, With reſpect to the Reverend. Mr. Williams.</head>
            <p>THere is one thing in Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> Books remarkable (as to me) above any other, becauſe it is altogether <hi>de proprio,</hi> and concerns me and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and that is a laborate (I may not ſay <hi>elaborate</hi>) endeavour or contrivance for making good ſome Words of his to this Senſe, That the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is <hi>imputed</hi> to a Believer otherwiſe, or more than <hi>in the effects,</hi> which is Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Explanation of that Phraſe. And having wrote what I have ſaid, by way of Oppoſition, in one or two Places in theſe Sheets, ſuppoſing that Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> might write, and then be engaged to take notice of it, ſo as to yield, or Anſwer to it, I let it ſtand: But leſt he ſhould not, I will my ſelf ſay ſomething to it. The Original Words of Mr. <hi>VVilliams</hi> are theſe: <hi>Goſp. Truth.</hi> P. 39. <hi>Beſides the Effects being made ours, the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to true Believers, as what was deſigned for their Salvation: Tea, is pleadable by them as their Security, and uſeful as if themſelves had done and ſuffered what Chriſt did.</hi> Not that God looks upon the Believer, as having done in Chriſts Perſon what Chriſt did, he never thought ſo, but that it is as good, or <hi>for his uſe,</hi> as much as if he had. <hi>The very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to the Believer!</hi> Here I muſt ask firſt what he means by <hi>Imputed?</hi> And I ſuppoſe he
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:94667:43"/>means, <hi>Being made ours,</hi> as he ſays of the <hi>Effects,</hi> or <hi>Reckoned of God as ours,</hi> for elſe he muſt underſtand by himſelf, till we know what he means. I ask ſecondly, How is the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt Ours, or reckoned to us as Ours? And I anſwer, It is <hi>ours in the Effects,</hi> and can be no otherwiſe. The <hi>Effects</hi> are ours <hi>Really,</hi> and his <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> ours <hi>Relatively,</hi> only in regard to thoſe <hi>Effects.</hi> Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> ſays ſomewhere, <hi>The Effects are not imputed:</hi> Very true; There is no Man ſaid they are, but that Chriſts Righteouſneſs is imputed, or made ours, <hi>in the Effects.</hi> I ask thirdly, When Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and I and he ſay thus much, does Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> ſay more? And ſeeing he does, What is that more? Does he account that Chriſts very Righteouſneſs is made ours ſo as God does account us righteous in his Righteouſneſs, and that to be our Juſtification, according to the Common Proteſtant? No ſure, he does not, for Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being according to Truth, he cannot look on that which is a Quality or Accident in Chriſt to be alſo in us, for that is ſuch an <hi>Imputation</hi> as the <hi>Antinomian</hi> himſelf is not to be ſuppoſed (without wrong) to believe: But it is conceived that he looks on us as having obeyed and ſuffered in Chriſt, as our <hi>Legal Perſon,</hi> and ſo to have his Righteouſneſs reckoned to us as Ours, in <hi>Law Senſe,</hi> for our Juſtification. This is the Notion of the Common Proteſtant, and Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> as undertaking their Cauſe, underſtandingly baulks it not: But does Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> by his <hi>Imputation</hi> own this? Certainly, by all his Books, he ſets himſelf to beat this down, as that which is, or muſt lead to the Antinomian Error. This being ſo, I muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin here to open my Eyes, and ſee that in this ſaying of Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> there lyes not any Oppoſition to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> or me, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I may attend to what he offers to make it good, and be glad if he can come off well in it. That which he ſays, we have in the Book and Place before quoted, and in his <hi>Anſwer to the Report.</hi> p. 87. The Righteouſneſs of Chriſt he diſtinguiſhes into his <hi>Performance of the Conditions of Redemption,</hi> and into his <hi>Right</hi> (or <hi>Jus adjudicatum</hi>) by that Covenant <hi>to the Believers Pardon</hi> and Salvation. As to the one, which is that our Divines all underſtand and ſpeak of, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the Obedience of his Life and Death, he ſays that it is <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted</hi> only <hi>Mediately,</hi> which is all one, as imputed only <hi>in the Effects,</hi> with Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> for he explains it by the very <hi>ſimile</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> does. The Redeemed Captive hath the <hi>Ranſom</hi> or <hi>Money</hi> only in his <hi>Liberty.</hi> But as to the other Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which with him conſiſts in his <hi>Right to his Reward,</hi> he ſays it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted <hi>Immediately,</hi> that is, imputed <hi>in ſe,</hi> in our phraſe, and upon
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:94667:44"/>that account makes good this ſaying, that <hi>Beſides the Effects being ours, the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to Believers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God promiſes Chriſt, that if he perform theſe Conditions, he ſhall <hi>ſee his Seed,</hi> and <hi>by his Knowledge</hi> (or Faith in him) <hi>ſhall many be juſtified.</hi> Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> now phraſes this, the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, as it is his adjudged Right, to the Believers Pardon,</hi> and Salvation, and this Right of Chriſts, the very Right is alſo (as he counts) the Believers. <hi>They have</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Chriſts Right; They are inveſted in Chriſts Right to the Benefits.</hi> By all which, he muſt intend an <hi>Imputation in ſe;</hi> for I argue for him upon this Suppoſition, that if this <hi>Right</hi> of Chriſt is an <hi>Effect</hi> of his <hi>Performance,</hi> and his Right be ours, the <hi>Effects,</hi> we all agree, are ours <hi>in ſe;</hi> ours <hi>really,</hi> when the <hi>Performance</hi> it ſelf is not ours, but <hi>relatively</hi> in thoſe Effects. If his Invention then here be ſound, he hath brought himſelf clear off as to me and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and this ſaying of his not hurting us, I will ſay ſomething in its behalf, in anſwer to my own Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections.</p>
            <p>One and the firſt is, that Chriſts Righteouſneſs is a perfect Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and anſwered the Law: If that be imputed <hi>in ſe,</hi> for our Juſtification, then we are judged and juſtified by the <hi>Law,</hi> and not the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> The anſwer to this is, that according to the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of the Common Proteſtant, the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which is imputed to us, is his fulfilling the Law in our behalf, and Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> agrees with us, that this Righteouſneſs of his is <hi>imputed</hi> only <hi>Mediately,</hi> that is only in the <hi>Effects.</hi> But it is the other Righteouſneſs which is it ſelf an Effect of Chriſts Perfor mance that is imputed to us <hi>in ſe;</hi> ſo that upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof he hath affirmed, that <hi>the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to the Believer.</hi> We have not Chriſts own <hi>Performance,</hi> which is a <hi>Real</hi> Righteouſneſs, but we have his <hi>Right,</hi> which is a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative</hi> Righteouſneſs, to be ours (he counts) for our Juſtification.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Objection is, that the Brethren are hereby deceived in him, who may think he means the ſame Righteouſneſs as they and others do, when it is another. The Anſwer to this is, It is true, they are, or may be deceived in him, but not by him, ſeeing he hath made his Explanation in ſix or ſeven Pages, in the Book mentioned, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he hath acquitted himſelf of this Accuſation, as to me and Mr. <hi>B.</hi> very well; whether it be ſo well to them, let themſelves judge.</p>
            <p>A third Objection is, that the Right of Chriſt, and the Right of the Believer cannot be one. The Right of the Believer can be no more the very Right of Chriſt, than the Believers Perſon can
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:94667:44"/>be Chriſt. This is from my <hi>Pacification;</hi> the anſwer to it is this. It is true, that Chriſts Right and the Believers Right, cannot be the ſame <hi>Phyſically,</hi> that is indeed impoſſible; but they may be the ſame <hi>Legally,</hi> (as our Divines underſtand the Imputation of Chriſts <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to us) and that is plainly Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> meaning here, as appears by his <hi>Simile,</hi> of a Man buying Part of a Purchaſe, the Purchaſers Right to the whole is in Law his Right for that Part he hath of it.</p>
            <p>A laſt Objection is from the Argument here offered, That Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to us for our Juſtification, which is the Meritorious Cauſe of it. It is not this <hi>Right</hi> of Chriſt to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but his <hi>Performance,</hi> was that. The anſwer to this, which as to the Common Proteſtant, that knows no other Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, but this <hi>Performance,</hi> is unanſwerable, muſt be left to him to anſwer, who hath found out another, and the <hi>Major</hi> muſt be denyed. It is true, that Righteouſneſs which is <hi>Meritorious,</hi> is imputed, but not that <hi>alone,</hi> but Chriſts <hi>Right</hi> alſo. This <hi>Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately,</hi> that <hi>Mediately;</hi> but both together, I ſuppoſe he intends it.</p>
            <p>It muſt be ask'd therefore after this, what we are indeed to judge of this <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> as to the Reality and Truth of it? Here is a prudential ſober ſort of Notion propoſed, not ariſing from any Scripture or Senſe thereof, conſtraining it, but invented rather (I ſay) for the retaining that Phraſe, the gratifying the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed, and ſubſcribing ſuch Confeſſions as the <hi>Savoyes,</hi> yet without forſaking any of the Doctrines, which he owns after Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> which being not an ordinary attempt, but ſhewing a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſtudies Men what they can bear, as well as Scripture what that enjoyns, I cannot but in <hi>Intereſt</hi> approve, and in <hi>Sincerity</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my ſuſpicion of it.</p>
            <p>It muſt be granted, that there is a Covenant (as our Divines con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) made between Chriſt and God, as there is one made with us in the Goſpel, That there was a Promiſe of God to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as a Promiſe to <hi>us,</hi> upon <hi>his</hi> Performance, as upon <hi>ours,</hi> and that a double Security may he had and pleaded from thence, that upon believing we ſhall be pardoned and ſaved, Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> may make as much of this as he pleaſes, as a greater matter of Security than others, who truſt to the Goſpel-promiſe only, without more concernment, for ſuch Doctrine is innocent, harmleſs, affecting perhaps to ſome, and unexceptionable, ſo as to be received without Queſtion: But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Right to his Reward,</hi> which Chriſt had by his Performance
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:94667:45"/>of the Commandment given him by his Father, is communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with the Believer? That is, Whether Chriſts Right to <hi>have a Seed, and ſuch as ſhall believe on him,</hi> can poſſibly be the Believers? Or, whether the Promiſe that Chriſt ſhall have ſome to believe in him, and ſo be ſaved, be of the ſame import with that which ſays, <hi>He that believes ſhall be ſaved?</hi> Again Whether there be any <hi>Imputation</hi> by God, of Chriſts Performance to the Believer as there is, or may be an <hi>Application</hi> of it, by the Believer, <hi>for his ſecurity,</hi> in regard to the Benefits? And, Whether ſuch an Imputation (if there be ſuch) of Chriſts Performance for the Believers <hi>Security,</hi> be of the ſame import as the Imputation of it for his <hi>Juſtification?</hi> Theſe and the like, are Queſtions which require the ſecond thoughts of Mr. <hi>Williams.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, there is one Conſideration, eſpecially the Conſideration of what confuſion it muſt make in the minds of moſt, to underſtand by the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs, another Righteouſneſs than that our Divines hither to have underſtood, and to draw their Words to a Senſe they never thought, which is to make them all equivocate or lie, is a matter of ſuch dangerous Conſequence, that I muſt come to a Reſolution and Anſwer to my Reverend Brother; which is, that omitting the Reply, that this <hi>Right of Chriſt,</hi> he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts on, is it ſelf <hi>one Effect</hi> of his <hi>Performance,</hi> and if that become Ours, the Righteouſneſs of his performance here is imputed (or made ours) ſtill in regard to the <hi>Effects</hi> only: And omitting the queſtionableneſs of this Right being ours, already mentioned, I muſt ſay plainly, that this Talk of his, (in his <hi>Anſwer to the Report</hi>) that there is a <hi>Judicial Imputation of this Right of Chriſt</hi> (which is one Effect) <hi>immediately,</hi> intervening between the Imputation of his <hi>Performance,</hi> which is <hi>Mediate,</hi> in order to the Effect of our Juſtification and Pardon (which he muſt intend, or all is nothing to the Point) I ſay, is to me a <hi>Figmentum,</hi> a Fiction, an Imaginary and <hi>Operoſe</hi> ſomething, which indeed is nothing, even according to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who tells us that <hi>The effects are not imputed.</hi> Alas! when it is ſo hard to take in what our Divines ſay of the Imputation of Chriſts Performance for our Juſtification (for how much eaſier is it of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to ſay, that for the ſake of what Chriſt hath done, God does forgive and ſave us on the Terms of the Goſpel, or does accept of Faith inſtead of perfect Obedience, than to talk of <hi>Imputation,</hi> which is a Phraſe, as applyed to <hi>Chriſts Righteouſneſs,</hi> invented by Man, though as applyed to <hi>Faith</hi> expreſs Scripture?) to come to the multiplying and doubling theſe <hi>Imputations,</hi> of Chriſts <hi>Right,</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:94667:45"/>as well as of his <hi>Performance,</hi> is a matter of ſo troubleſom a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo clutterſom an invention <hi>(Eutia non ſunt multiplicanda ſine neceſſitate)</hi> ſo turning and over-turning what hath been ſaid by our Divines, as it were topſie turvy, and indeed ſo preſumptuous (as well as untrue, according to his own Axiom) upon that account, that if it were not that by this means he gets a Liberty of Compliance, to uſe the Phraſe with the Brethren (who the moſt of them never concern'd themſelves as to his Explanation) it would not be endured.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore known to all Men, by theſe preſents, that I <hi>J. Humfrey</hi> do acquit Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> of the Inconſiſtency I ſuppoſed in his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which concerns me and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> upon this Notion or Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if this invention of his be good: but if it be found not good, but upon further Conſideration, a piece of humane Wiſdom only and a Shift, I do yet conjure him to retract it.</p>
            <p>But to offer ſomething before I have done moreover, for ſatisfaction to my Friend Mr. <hi>Lobb.</hi> There is a Compact, it is conceived by him, of Chriſt with the Father, that he will come <hi>under the Law,</hi> both in regard to the <hi>Precept</hi> and <hi>Sanction,</hi> and that the <hi>Sanction</hi> thereupon takes hold on him, his voluntary Sponſion <hi>Anteceding</hi> not <hi>Intereeding,</hi> the laying the Penalty on him. This now cannot be. That Chriſt entred not our <hi>Bond</hi> at firſt with us, Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> ſees, and ſays. The Bond ran not, that if we, or our Surety performed it, the Obligation ſhould be void, for then upon Chriſts keeping the Law there could be no Puniſhment due to him or us: but he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred our Bond when we had broken it, he entred into the <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of the violated Law of Works</hi> (he ſays) and ſo the <hi>Law</hi> taking him as under that Violation, and Conſequently as under its Sanction, it laid the Puniſhment immediately on him, as the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be puniſhed, and in that regard, even in regard to the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> it was (he acconnts) a <hi>proper Puniſhment.</hi> This I take to be the Error of the Common Proteſtant, and ſo Mr. <hi>Lobbs</hi> upon that account. It is true, that Chriſt voluntarily undertook or compacted to come under the <hi>Precept</hi> of the Law (unto which yet it ſelf, as a <hi>Divine Perſon</hi> (<hi>Actiones</hi> being <hi>Suppoſitorum</hi>) he could not have been obliged otherwiſe, ſay Divines) and to undergo the Curſe, or Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due to us, but not to come under the <hi>Sanction,</hi> that being impoſſible, becauſe the <hi>Sanction</hi> (as to the <hi>Comminatory</hi> Part, we
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:94667:46"/>underſtand) does puniſh only him that breaks the Precept, which Chriſt never did, but we do, ſo that it is the <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> not the <hi>Fault,</hi> or <hi>Merit</hi> thereof that he took on him, which conſequently aroſe not from the <hi>Sanction</hi> but his <hi>Undertaking,</hi> and that Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking being to ſuffer in our room, it could not be a <hi>proper Puniſhment</hi> in Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s Senſe of <hi>Proper,</hi> which is <hi>Ariſing from the Sanction,</hi> but a <hi>Vicarious</hi> Puniſhment, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> over and over does tell us.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt came under the Sanction of the Law, ſo as the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment was due to him <hi>Ex obligatione Legis,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> holds (but as pleading only the Common Proteſtants Cauſe, I will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) then muſt he be accounted of God as a <hi>Sinner,</hi> nay, as the greateſt of Sinners, and be puniſhed as ſuch, which hath indeed been formerly affirmed by great Divines, and ſo taken up by the <hi>Antinomian,</hi> accounting that our ſins was laid on him in the <hi>Merit,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> which my Friend ſeeing, that here indeed is the <hi>Gulph,</hi> he makes his ſtand, and comes off in an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> for his oppoſing <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in this Point, that <hi>there is ſuch a Change of Perſons, which implies a Tranſlation of the Perſonal Guilt</hi> (or Merit of their ſins, which is all one) <hi>of the Believer on Chriſt,</hi> which he confutes as the Doctrine of the <hi>Antinomian,</hi> and which Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> diſclaims, as heartily as any. O thou my Friend therefore, Mr. <hi>Common Proteſtant,</hi> be it known to all, that Chriſt ſuffered not as a <hi>Sinner,</hi> but as an <hi>Interceder,</hi> and not from the Obligation of the <hi>violated Law of Works</hi> (which he violated not) but of his <hi>Fathers Commandment,</hi> which was proper to him, or of the <hi>Law of Redemption,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams</hi> after Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> does ſtedfaſtly teach. Chriſt indeed took on him the Obligation to ſuffer for our ſins, but not <hi>Our</hi> Obligation: He bare the Puniſhment of our ſins (let me ſay), yet <hi>Perſonally</hi> not <hi>Our</hi> Puniſhment. When Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>made under the Law</hi> (<hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4.) I underſtand it of the <hi>Law of Moſes,</hi> as a <hi>Jew</hi> born, for redeeming the <hi>Jews</hi> from it: Yet as one of Mankind was he alſo under the <hi>Law of Works</hi> as to the <hi>Precept,</hi> and fulfilled it for freeing us from that perfect Performance, as the Condition of Life, and from its being to us the Rule of Judgment: but he was not under the <hi>Penal Sanction,</hi> nor could be, being innocent. He was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.) <hi>made a Curſe,</hi> but not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:94667:46"/>(<hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.) <hi>under the Curſe,</hi> which none but the Tranſgreſſor is. And ſeeing Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> is come already to ſee he muſt part with the <hi>Common Doctrine,</hi> ſomewhere, or fall into Antinomianiſm, he is ſo rational and fair a Man (I believe) as his own <hi>Genius</hi> (when once he can be cool and conſider) will ſuggeſt to him, that it is better not to ſet out at all, than to halt by the way, and not to go quite home. If he be convinced that the <hi>Perſonal Guilt of our ſins</hi> could not be tranſlated on Chriſt, ſo as to make him a <hi>Legal Sinner</hi> (which is all that the <hi>Criſpian,</hi> as well as the <hi>Common Proteſtant</hi> Doctrine, ever meant), then will he ſee that the <hi>Perſonal Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt</hi> cannot be tranſlated neither on us, ſo as that we ſhould be <hi>Legally Righteous</hi> in him; and conſequently agree with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and me (leaving Mr. <hi>VVilliams,</hi> if he wont come on, behind) in the Doctrine both of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and <hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt add as a <hi>Corollary,</hi> that the Phraſes (my Friend does ſtand ſo much upon) of Chriſts ſuffering <hi>in our Perſon,</hi> or in our <hi>ſtead,</hi> if they be uſed as the ſame, and ſignifie no more but that Chriſt being a Divine Perſon, did ſuffer a Temporal Death, as an Equivalent to ſave us from ſuffering Eternal Damnation, they are equally to paſs: But if either of them be made to bear ſuch a Senſe, as that Chriſt did <hi>Legally perſonate</hi> us, ſo as we are to be accounted to have done or ſuffered in him, that which he did or ſuffered, or what may ſeem leſs, that this <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> did put Chriſt under <hi>Our</hi> Obligation of the <hi>violated Law of VVorks,</hi> ſo making him to be accounted of God <hi>a Sinner,</hi> and dealt with as a Sinner, to the end that his ſufferings may be maintained to be a <hi>proper Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the Phraſe, or Phraſes are ſtretch'd beyond the Staple, become dangerous, the Senſe Antinomian, and to be diſallowed.</p>
            <p>And now to diſmiſs Mr. <hi>VVilliams</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> both. The ſumm of Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s <hi>Appeal</hi> comes to this Syllogiſm. That Perſon who holds that the ſufferings of Chriſt was not a <hi>Proper</hi> Puniſhment, but a <hi>Vicarious</hi> Puniſhment; Not <hi>Formally,</hi> but <hi>Materially</hi> Puniſhment; That our Sins were not the <hi>Proximious</hi> Meritorious Cauſe, but the <hi>Remote,</hi> the Pro-meritorious Cauſe, or <hi>Occaſion</hi> of them; That they aroſe not from the Obligation of the <hi>Law,</hi> or from the <hi>Sanction</hi> of the Law of <hi>VVorks</hi> (which includes with Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> that <hi>Commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:94667:47"/>of Perſons,</hi> as makes Chriſt <hi>Guilty,</hi> taken, judged, and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>in our Perſon</hi>) but from his voluntary Sponſion, or ſubmiſſion to his <hi>Fathers Commandment</hi> proper to him (which implies with Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> that the inflicting of Sufferings on Chriſt, could be no act of Gods <hi>Rectoral</hi> Juſtice, but of <hi>Dominion,</hi> when I take it to be an act of God both as <hi>Rector,</hi> and <hi>Supra Leges</hi> together, and ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxation of his Law as <hi>Zaleucus</hi> Fact was); That conſequently the <hi>Law</hi> (in the Threat) was not fulfilled by him, ſuch a Perſon is a <hi>Socinian,</hi> and denies the Doctrine, or denies that which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to explain the Doctrine, of Chriſts <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> But Mr. <hi>VVilliams</hi> is ſuch a Perſon. <hi>Ergo</hi> Mr. <hi>VVilliams</hi> is one that denies that which is neceſſary to this Explanation.</p>
            <p>Here Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> makes it his buſineſs to prove the <hi>Minor,</hi> which he hath effectually done in quoting Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in many places (and many more might be added) ſaying theſe things, and then producing Conſiderations and Paſſages out of Mr. <hi>VVilliams</hi> to prove that he muſt be of the ſame Opinion. Now if Mr. <hi>VVilliams</hi> denies the <hi>Minor,</hi> and goes to vindicate himſelf as to that, he may be aſhamed, for Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> has done his Work. But Mr. <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams,</hi> I ſuppoſe, as well as I, will deny the <hi>Major.</hi> And what hath Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> to ſay for that, but all <hi>Gratis?</hi> Why here is a <hi>Suppoſition</hi> preſumed that the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> Chriſt made for our ſins, was to be <hi>ſuch</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> as they have fancied, or elſe it muſt be no ſatisfaction, when the miſtake is ſo great, that if all that were neceſſary thereto, which they pretend, the Lord Chriſt was a Perſon uncapable to make it, and ſo there muſt be none, and we be all Socinians. I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore two Anſwers to give Mr. <hi>Lobb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> ſhall be from himſelf, who when Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> is arguing, That <hi>if we may very properly be ſaid to be puniſhed in Chriſt for our ſins, then muſt it be granted, that we made ſatisfaction in Chriſt, and are our own Redeemers,</hi> He anſwers, No, becauſe <hi>the ſatisfaction aroſe not</hi> (ſays he) <hi>from our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings in Chriſt, nor indeed from Chriſts Sufferings, conſidered abſolutely and</hi> in ſe, <hi>but from the Fathers acceptation of the Sons ſufferings.</hi> This is judiciouſly ſaid, The words he adds, <hi>as they were</hi> Ex obligatione Legis, <hi>and an Equivalent to the demerit
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:94667:47"/>of our ſins are</hi> Petitio Principii, for he might put in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> well; <hi>as our ſins were the</hi> Proximous <hi>Meritorious Cauſe of them, and as they were a proper Puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer him therefore accordingly, That ſeeing the <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> Chriſt made was not indeed a Satisfaction of the Law it ſelf but of the Law-giver, who though <hi>Rector,</hi> is alſo <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra Leges</hi> (the <hi>Law</hi> indeed which requires <hi>Supplicium delinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> being not <hi>executed,</hi> but <hi>Satisfaction</hi> made, that it might not be fulfilled on the Sinner) and ſeeing the Satisfaction lay Fundamentally in the <hi>Acceptation</hi> of the Father, or as perform'd according to the <hi>Will</hi> of both; What if it pleaſed God to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point and accept of a <hi>Vicarious</hi> Puniſhment, inſtead of a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> Puniſhment, who is there can have any more to ſay againſt it.</p>
            <p>I will add in regard to ſome freſh Sheets of Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> come out, called, <hi>A further Defence,</hi> which in ſetting forth Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Doctrine as oppoſite to that which is commonly Received (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Dr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> and others) has done Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> Right and Honour, as I account; That for as much as God acts (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to him, and Truth) both as <hi>Rector</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> alſo <hi>Supra Leges,</hi> and the great Ends of <hi>Government</hi> in general, ſuch as the Demonſtration of Gods Righteouſneſs, his hatred to ſin, the deterring the Sinner by exemplary Puniſhment, and even his greater Glory, might be attained in the way which God took, without fulfilling the direct end of the Law in a <hi>proper puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> on the Sinner, (or on Chriſt, as a Sinner) It is ſuch a <hi>Satisfaction</hi> as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> offers (that is, a Satisfaction of the <hi>Law-giver</hi>) and not that Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> ſtands upon (a Satisfaction of the <hi>Law</hi>) which is to be maintained: For this being <hi>Socinus</hi> fundamental Errour, That <hi>True Satisfaction lies only in a full payment of the Debt,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Death</hi> being due to every Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction</hi> ſeems to him apparently Falſe, Chriſt ſuffering not that Puniſhment; and thoſe Divines now that fall in with him into that Conception, have not an Anſwer to give <hi>Socinus:</hi> whereas Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> hath ſet out Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Doctrine in the ſeveral branches, to be ſo tight and uniform, that the light thereof (though wrapt in his Clouds of Blame about it) does ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:94667:48"/>moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onvictive and irreſiſtible; and I cannot but think that Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> himſelf, when he can be cool, and lay by oppoſition, muſt be ready to embrace it. It is Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> which can be juſtified againſt <hi>Socinus.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Doctrine is ſuch as does force even the <hi>Socinians</hi> to yield, and acknowledge themſelves over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by it. This is ſuch Doctrine as needs no more but the ſame more friendly diſplay of it (See Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> own 18 Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions together) for Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Vindication, and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> Anſwer I have, is made already in theſe Sheets, and that is, that there is one <hi>Word,</hi> and that taken from <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf, which hath done it. The word <hi>[Imperſonaliter]</hi> does reconcile <hi>Grotius</hi> and <hi>Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> the Biſhop and us all; and that word therefore, without any thing more, is enough to ſolve the difficulty; and conſequently to explain and make good this Great Doctrine of Chriſts <hi>Satisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 9. line 27. my read <hi>your.</hi> p. 14. l. 21. r. <hi>exiſtimare.</hi> p. 22. l. 9. <hi>Premium:</hi> r. <hi>Praemiant.</hi> p. 74 in the Margin, <hi>deliti,</hi> r. <hi>debiti.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="bookseller_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94667:48"/>
            <head>THE BOOKSELLER TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe <hi>Letters</hi> and <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> put thus together by my Appointment, were intended to come out aſunder; the <hi>Animadverſions</hi> as a <hi>ſecond Part</hi> of the <hi>Friendly Interpoſer,</hi> and the <hi>Letters</hi> as the <hi>finiſhing Work</hi> to that Doctrine <hi>propoſed</hi> by Mr. <hi>H.</hi> in his <hi>Middle Way,</hi> and <hi>confirmed</hi> in his <hi>Righteouſneſs of God;</hi> unto which Book he would have had them annex'd alone by themſelves: But in regard that the ſeveral Papers of his, concerning the <hi>late Difference</hi> among the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> in <hi>Doctrinals</hi> (whereof the Point of <hi>Juſtification</hi> is the chief) will come with theſe to forty Sheets, <hi>I</hi> have thought beſt my ſelf (and have found good Cauſe ſo to do) to bind the whole in one handſom Book, that any that will (ſo long as each of a ſort holds out) may have it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
